<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2</transcript-id>
    <title>Digest of Decisions and Announcements and Important Speeches No 8  - Period 20th November 1941 to 27th November 1941 </title>
    <prime-minister>Curtin, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19411007 - 19450705</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/11/1941</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000002_3.pdf</document>
    <subjects />
    <content>&lt;p&gt;COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT.&lt;br /&gt;-DIGEST OF DECISIONS&lt;br /&gt;AND ANNOUNCEMENTS AM4&lt;br /&gt;IMPORTANTSPEECHES THE PRIME MINISTER&lt;br /&gt;( THE HON. JOHN CURTIN).&lt;br /&gt;No. 8.&lt;br /&gt;PERIOD-2nTu NOVEMBER, 1941, To 27TH NOVEMBER, 1941.&lt;br /&gt;By Atbcwribt:&lt;br /&gt;L F. Joamm. Cnamonwc Comvrnnt PrinM. Cibm.&lt;br /&gt;( Printed in Ajstli&amp;amp;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BANNING OF BOOKS.&lt;br /&gt;ARMY MINISTER'S STATEMENT.&lt;br /&gt;In Parliament.-On 20th November, 1941, the Minister for the&lt;br /&gt;Army ( Mr. Forde) said-&lt;br /&gt;" The questions which have been directed at the Army Censorship&lt;br /&gt;recently fall into three sections. The first concerns the list of publications&lt;br /&gt;which are on the banned list prepared for the Army; the second&lt;br /&gt;the alleged impounding of books being imported as cargo; and the&lt;br /&gt;third whether Major Cameron, is associated in his military&lt;br /&gt;capacity' with the banning of literature.&lt;br /&gt;At the moment 171 publications, including books, magazines,&lt;br /&gt;newspapers, pamphlets and cyclo-styled circulars, are on the Army&lt;br /&gt;banned list on the ground that they are subversive. Of these, 83 come&lt;br /&gt;under the broad description of Leftist"; 16 have a distinct Nazi&lt;br /&gt;flavour and the remainder consist of certain Japanese periodicals and'&lt;br /&gt;material which is militantly pacifist or anti-British. Of the 171&lt;br /&gt;publications, 64 are published in England, 57 in the United States of&lt;br /&gt;America, 16 in Japan, 9 in Russia, 4 in Australia, 3 in Manchuria,&lt;br /&gt;3 in Mexico, 2 in each of France, China, Brazil, Ireland and Sweden&lt;br /&gt;and 1 in each of New Zealand, Argentine, Finland, Switzerland and&lt;br /&gt;India; 49 are printed in foreign languages and the rest in English.&lt;br /&gt;Included in the list of banned " Leftist" publications are the Russian&lt;br /&gt;newspapers Pravda and Izvestia, as well as a number of the works&lt;br /&gt;of Ienin and others. I have ordered a review of the 171 publications&lt;br /&gt;with a view to seeing if any of them can safely be released for&lt;br /&gt;circulation without ' any risk to national security. Recently two&lt;br /&gt;publications were removed from this list because it was found that&lt;br /&gt;they did not contain any subversive or objectionable propaganda.&lt;br /&gt;They were the Moscow News, a weekly newspaper published in English&lt;br /&gt;in Moscow, and the Left News, a periodical published by the firm of&lt;br /&gt;Gollancz, London.&lt;br /&gt;" The Army is responsible for the censorship of matter passing&lt;br /&gt;through postal and telegraphic channels. At present if any of the&lt;br /&gt;publications on the Army's banned list are intercepted in the post they&lt;br /&gt;are stopped. The procedure which was adopted in compiling the list&lt;br /&gt;of banned publications was as follows: Publications intercepted in&lt;br /&gt;the mail by postal and telegraphic censorship authorities, and suspected&lt;br /&gt;of being subversive or detrimental to the efficient prosecution of the&lt;br /&gt;war, were submitted to the Department of Information, which is the&lt;br /&gt;press and publicity censorship authority. That department decided&lt;br /&gt;whether or not a publication contravened the provisions of National&lt;br /&gt;Security ( General) Regulation 17. If that department decided that a&lt;br /&gt;publication did contravene the regulation, it was placed by the&lt;br /&gt;Controller of Postal and Telegraphic Censorship on the banned list&lt;br /&gt;and was stopped by the censors. The procedure for removing a&lt;br /&gt;publication from the list is that if, in the course of examining materials,&lt;br /&gt;a District Censor thinks that the tone of a listed publication has&lt;br /&gt;changed, it is submitted by the Controller of Postal and Telegraphic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Censorship to the Department of Information. If that Department&lt;br /&gt;finds that the publication is not subversive it is removed from the list.&lt;br /&gt;The next question is the impounding of literature after the&lt;br /&gt;importation and before sale or distribution. I am informed by&lt;br /&gt;Military Intelligence authorities that they go no further than the&lt;br /&gt;censorship action I have just detailed. The power to impound&lt;br /&gt;" Leftist" literature exists in National Security ( General) Regulation&lt;br /&gt;17, which provides that a Minister may, by order in the Gazette,&lt;br /&gt;declare printed matter to be a prohibited paper. The printed matter&lt;br /&gt;then becomes automatically banned and forfeited. Under National&lt;br /&gt;Security ( Subversive Associations) Regulations, the Attorney-General&lt;br /&gt;has certain powers in regard to the property of associations which are&lt;br /&gt;declared to be subversive, but these do not appear to be relevant here&lt;br /&gt;except where they relate to the impounding of the literature of those&lt;br /&gt;organizations which have already been declared subversive.&lt;br /&gt;' Complaints have been made that the Customs Department referred&lt;br /&gt;doubtful publications to the Army which the Army banned without&lt;br /&gt;explanation and that the Army refused to inform booksellers whether&lt;br /&gt;or why the ban had been imposed. I am informed that the Army&lt;br /&gt;in theal matters acts on the advice of the Department of Information.&lt;br /&gt;Apart altogether from Army Censorship, the Customs Department has&lt;br /&gt;power under their Prohibited Imports Regulations to stop certain types&lt;br /&gt;of Communist literature.&lt;br /&gt;In regard to the statements which have been made that the&lt;br /&gt;Military Intelligence organization in Southern Command, of which&lt;br /&gt;Major Cameron, is a member, has taken action to impound or&lt;br /&gt;suppress literature other than that which is included in the banned&lt;br /&gt;list, I am in a position to state definitely that Southern Command has&lt;br /&gt;not at any time since the outbreak of the war, either within or outside&lt;br /&gt;the scope of their powers, impounded any literature, imported or&lt;br /&gt;otherwise, either on their own initiative or at the request of some other&lt;br /&gt;authority, or in any other circumstances. Southern Command has&lt;br /&gt;not been concerned in any way in association with the Criminal&lt;br /&gt;Investigation Branch or with the police in the impounding of&lt;br /&gt;literature. It is true that Major Cameron, in his military&lt;br /&gt;capacity, was connected with Intelligence Censorship in name for&lt;br /&gt;about a month, but his actual work was not very great. There are no&lt;br /&gt;instances in which he was concerned with the banning of literature in&lt;br /&gt;his military capacity."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 4, page 9.)&lt;br /&gt;MR. A. CAMERON, M. H. R.&lt;br /&gt;On 21st November, 1941, Mr. Forde said-&lt;br /&gt;" I can see no justification for appointing a court of inquiry to&lt;br /&gt;investigate the allegations made against Mr. Cameron, by a&lt;br /&gt;section of the press. My investigation into the whole question of the&lt;br /&gt;banning of books -showed that there were no instances in which&lt;br /&gt;Major Cameron was concerned with the banning of literature in his&lt;br /&gt;military capacity."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RUSSIAN NEWSPAPERS.&lt;br /&gt;On 21st November, 1941, Mr. Forde said-&lt;br /&gt;" In view of our changed relationship with Russia I now cannot&lt;br /&gt;see any justification for banning the two important Russian newspapers&lt;br /&gt;Pravda and Izvestia. They are quoted every day in the cables, which&lt;br /&gt;proves they contain no subversive propaganda against the best interests&lt;br /&gt;of the Allies, either in their leading articles or propaganda columns,&lt;br /&gt;and that Russia has everything in common with the British Empire&lt;br /&gt;in this struggle." CENSORSHIP CONTROL.&lt;br /&gt;In Parliament.-On 21st November, 1941, the Minister for Trade.&lt;br /&gt;and Customs ( Senator Keane) said-&lt;br /&gt;" Recently I had occasion to intervene with regard to a large&lt;br /&gt;consignment of books from overseas that had been delivered in&lt;br /&gt;Melbourne and had been held up since last March. Although-the:&lt;br /&gt;books number about 600, only one of them was opei to challenge.&lt;br /&gt;Despite that fact, all books had been held under the. direction of some&lt;br /&gt;Army authority, but, on the position being explained, the: books were&lt;br /&gt;released. The main point is that there is dual control. " I have asked&lt;br /&gt;the Army authorities to communicate to me their views. as to whether&lt;br /&gt;the power of censorship, from the point of view of subversive activities;&lt;br /&gt;should not reside in one authority. When I receive from the Minister'&lt;br /&gt;for the Army a reply to my recent request for a full statement on the&lt;br /&gt;matter, I shall answer at greater length."&lt;br /&gt;On 26th November, 1941, Mr. Forde said-&lt;br /&gt;The matter of censorship control is one that will be discussed by.&lt;br /&gt;me at the first opportunity with the Minister for Trade and Customs&lt;br /&gt;( Senator Keane) and the Minister for Information (' Senator Ashley).&lt;br /&gt;There is a desire that there should be a centralized control of:&lt;br /&gt;censorship." PRIMARY INDUSTRIES.;&lt;br /&gt;SAGR[ CULTURAL COUNCIL MEETING.'&lt;br /&gt;On 20th November, 1941, at a meeting of the Australian Agricultural&lt;br /&gt;-Council at Canberra, the Minister for Commerce ( Mr. Scully).&lt;br /&gt;. said-" I thank the various State Ministers for attending this meeting&lt;br /&gt;and welcome them to the deliberations of the first meeting over which&lt;br /&gt;it is my privilege to preside. I am fully conscious of the very difficult&lt;br /&gt;task which confronts the Government, and particularly the Minister&lt;br /&gt;a. isisting the Minister for Commerce ( Senator Fraser) and myself in::&lt;br /&gt;guiding marketing policy through the problems which war brings I&lt;br /&gt;have had considerable personal experience of agricultural . industries.:&lt;br /&gt;I face the task as a man acutely aware of the primary producers'&lt;br /&gt;problems. In this war shipping has suffered greatly, and the British&lt;br /&gt;7780.-2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Governent finds it necessary to make changes in the disposition of&lt;br /&gt;shipping at short notice. Supplying countries have to cope with&lt;br /&gt;baffling problems and adjust their policy to variations in market&lt;br /&gt;demands which cannot be foreseen.&lt;br /&gt;" The new Government conmes to office with its own distinctive&lt;br /&gt;policy in regard to agriculture. It has its own ideas in regard tothe&lt;br /&gt;method of improving the general economic position of&lt;br /&gt;the farmers; and&lt;br /&gt;methods of control of marketing.&lt;br /&gt;The Government believes that the financial position of farmers can&lt;br /&gt;be improved by a better system of long-term finance. The farmer&lt;br /&gt;should be able to secure, at reasonable rates of interest, financial&lt;br /&gt;. At~ imodation over a long term of years in respect of the proper&lt;br /&gt;capital vaoue of his farm. The present Government believes this can;&lt;br /&gt;be made good by a properly constituted Mortgage Bank. To enable&lt;br /&gt;the Mortgage Bank to function with benefit to the farmer and to&lt;br /&gt;improve his general cconomic status, the Government is studying all&lt;br /&gt;possible measures which may be summed up under the general title&lt;br /&gt;of rural reconstruction. As the Minister for Commerce I Will do&lt;br /&gt;everything t~ o improve the farmer's income; to enhance the importance&lt;br /&gt;of rural life; to reverse the present tendencies towards rural depopulation,&lt;br /&gt;and to establish the foundations of a greater rural prosperity. The&lt;br /&gt;individual farmer must be protected against too heavy a load of debt.&lt;br /&gt;TPhis protcction must come from control of land values and from&lt;br /&gt;control of his general debt structure, with guidance to him as to the&lt;br /&gt;capacity of his property to bear the load of indebtedness. Too great R&lt;br /&gt;share of the income fronm the* farmn goes to the creditor.&lt;br /&gt;" The rural community requires national effort to provide in the&lt;br /&gt;country the amenities which are commonplace in the cities. This joint&lt;br /&gt;effort at improvement of the individual farmer's position and the&lt;br /&gt;provision of amenities for rural districts will comprise the subject&lt;br /&gt;matter of rural reconstrucetion. Details of this policy will be dealt&lt;br /&gt;with from time to time. I hope to have the States' co-operation to&lt;br /&gt;improve the status of agriculture.&lt;br /&gt;Regarding control of marketing, Ministers will have observed that&lt;br /&gt;it. is to he the Government's policy to afford to growers a more complete&lt;br /&gt;control over the marketing of their products. Efficient marketing of&lt;br /&gt;any commodity requires specialized knowledge, but specialized knowledge&lt;br /&gt;must be reinforced by an interest in the return to be secured.&lt;br /&gt;It is, therefore, the Government's policy t~ o ensure adequate grower&lt;br /&gt;representation on all marketing organizations. We hope to arrange&lt;br /&gt;that efficient representatives of the growers shall attain a predominant&lt;br /&gt;position on the marketing boards. This can be achieved without in&lt;br /&gt;any wayv diminishing the technical e* fficiency of those or'Yani7ation&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 1, page 11.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AGRICULTURAL COUNCIL DECISIONS.&lt;br /&gt;On 21st November, 1941, the Agricultural Council decided several&lt;br /&gt;matters. RURAL REHABILITATION.&lt;br /&gt;It is desirable to continue debt adjustment for the time being and the&lt;br /&gt;States urged that the Commonwealth continue to find funds for State plans.&lt;br /&gt;The whole system of debt adjustment should be examined on a Commonwealthwide&lt;br /&gt;basis with a view to bringing these plans into line with the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;Government's plans for rural rehabilitation. The States accepted the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;view that it is desirable to hasten the completion of plans for removing&lt;br /&gt;wheat farmers from marginal areas.&lt;br /&gt;INTERNATIONAL WHEAT AGREEMENT.&lt;br /&gt;Mr. Scully reported the nature of discussions in Washington between representatives&lt;br /&gt;of the United Kingdom, United States of America, Canada, Argentine&lt;br /&gt;and Australia. Consultations on the progress . made in the discussions are&lt;br /&gt;regarded as satisfactory by State Ministers who expressed their confidence that&lt;br /&gt;the Commonwealth, if it decided to participate in an International Wheat&lt;br /&gt;Agreement, would safeguard the best interests of Australia.&lt;br /&gt;APPLES AND PEARS.&lt;br /&gt;The Commonwealth has not yet considered the matter but will do so soon&lt;br /&gt;and will then have the benefit of the views of the States.&lt;br /&gt;SUPERPHOSPHATES.&lt;br /&gt;Council adopted a method of rationing superphosphates which was submitted:&lt;br /&gt;by the Department of Commerce. It is based on the use by each producer&lt;br /&gt;of 65 per cent. of the quantity of superphosphates used in 1939-40.&lt;br /&gt;POTATOES.&lt;br /&gt;Council agreed that it was inadvisable to increase acreage or stimulate&lt;br /&gt;production with the anticipated demands of the Supply Department. It was:&lt;br /&gt;felt that the Supply Department should advise the State Departments of&lt;br /&gt;Agriculture of its likely requirements and, having done this, should untilne&lt;br /&gt;itself to operating on the market in a normal way.&lt;br /&gt;MUNITIONS CONTRACTS.&lt;br /&gt;REFUNDS TO GOWERNMENT.&lt;br /&gt;On 21st November, 1941, the Minister for Munitions ( Mr. Makin)&lt;br /&gt;said that voluntary refunds aggregating at least &#339; 100,000 had been&lt;br /&gt;made to the Government by two large Australian-wide organizations.&lt;br /&gt;The refunds were from proceeds of war-time activities by these firms.&lt;br /&gt;It was a healthy sign when big companies acted in such a way,&lt;br /&gt;especially when, as far as he knew, the only reason for their action had&lt;br /&gt;been that the right spirit had prompted them. He hoped that other&lt;br /&gt;firms would follow the excellent example. Much of the money from&lt;br /&gt;one firm had been made in the erection of a munitions annexe and he&lt;br /&gt;wished to acknowledge publicly the company's patriotic gesture.&lt;br /&gt;MUNITIONS PRODUCTION.&lt;br /&gt;NITRIC ACID AND METHANOL.&lt;br /&gt;On 21st November, 1941, the Minister for Munitions ( Mr. Makin)&lt;br /&gt;said he had approved of a recommendation which should make Au.-&lt;br /&gt;tralia self-contained in respect of nitric acid and methanol, the requirements&lt;br /&gt;of which at present amounted to &#339; 1,000,000 annually. This&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;would involve an expenditure of &#339; 2,500,000. Factories would be&lt;br /&gt;erected at Ballarat and Maribyrnong ( Victoria), Villawood ( New&lt;br /&gt;South Wales), and Salisbury ( South Australia). They would be&lt;br /&gt;located on the sites of government explosives factories.&lt;br /&gt;TANK MANUFACTURE.&lt;br /&gt;On 24th November, 1941, the Minister for the Army Forde)&lt;br /&gt;said-" The conference on the production of tanks in Australia considered&lt;br /&gt;the type of tank to be built and the whole question of the supply of&lt;br /&gt;eugines for these tanks. Its object was to decide definitely the type&lt;br /&gt;of tank to be built and the type of engine to be used."&lt;br /&gt;[ Ministers who attended the conference were Mr. Forde, the&lt;br /&gt;Minister for Munitions ( Mr. Makin) and the Minister for Air ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;Drakeford).] CHRISTMAS ARRANGEMENTS.&lt;br /&gt;On 27th November, 1941, Mr. Makin said that State Boards of&lt;br /&gt;Area Management would confer with workers' organizations as to what&lt;br /&gt;days would be most suitable to ' constitute the Christmas holiday period.&lt;br /&gt;The department was anxious that production should be maintained at.&lt;br /&gt;the highest possible maximum but it was recognized that, after the&lt;br /&gt;continuous and fatiguing hours which had been necessary to overcome&lt;br /&gt;the shortage of technical skill, some break at Christmas was necessary.&lt;br /&gt;The rest period for munition workers would allow for overhaul of and&lt;br /&gt;repairs to machinery. ( For earlier references, please see No. 2, page 23.).&lt;br /&gt;CONTROL OF FORGINGS.&lt;br /&gt;On 27th November, 1941, Mr. Makin said that in consequence of&lt;br /&gt;the heavy demands on industry in respect of steel forgings, particularly&lt;br /&gt;in respect of heavy forgings necessary for gun manufacture&lt;br /&gt;and shipbuilding, it had been necessary to establish machinery within&lt;br /&gt;the department to control production of forgings. An Assistant-&lt;br /&gt;Controller of Forgings ( Mr. W. Noad) had -been appointed to the&lt;br /&gt;Directorate of Materials Supply. It would be his business to ascertain&lt;br /&gt;the requirements of steel forgings throughout the Commonwealth; the&lt;br /&gt;forging capacity available and the full utilization of that capacity.&lt;br /&gt;WOMEN'S WAR ORGANIZATIONS.&lt;br /&gt;PATHOLOGY COURSE FOR WOMEN.&lt;br /&gt;On M1st November. 1941, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Forde)&lt;br /&gt;sid-", Six women medical officers,: bearing the rank of captain, are at&lt;br /&gt;present undergoing an intensive three months' course in the science of&lt;br /&gt;pathology at the School of Tropical. Medicine. The course is especially&lt;br /&gt;devised to give these women an intensive post-graduate experience of&lt;br /&gt;the requirements of clinical pathology.. The object is to make them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;proficient and competent to take charge of laboratories in Australia for&lt;br /&gt;thorough investigation of the diseases to which an army is subject.&lt;br /&gt;Their appointment would make it possible to release male doctors . f&lt;br /&gt;the Australian Army Medical Corps for service' overseas."&lt;br /&gt;AUSTRALIAN WOMEN~ S ARMY SERVICE.&lt;br /&gt;On 22nd November, 1941, Mr. Forde announced the appointment . of&lt;br /&gt;further officers to the Australian Women's Army Bervice-&lt;br /&gt;Assistant Controller at Army Head.-quarters, Melbourne, Miss Jean&lt;br /&gt;Wood; Tasmanian Commandant, Mrs. E. G. B. Scriven; Assistant&lt;br /&gt;Commandants in Victoria, Misses Patricia Turner, E. F. Ratten, 1. V.&lt;br /&gt;Murphy, M. Michelmore,. Dorothy May, and Mesdames E.&lt;br /&gt;Jamieson and E. F. Parry;-Assistant ' Commandant, Western Command,&lt;br /&gt;Miss J. Robertson. ( For earlier references, please see No. 5, page 18.)&lt;br /&gt;WOMEN'S AUXILIARY AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE&lt;br /&gt;RECRUITING.&lt;br /&gt;On 26th November, 1941, the Minister for Air ( Mr. Drakeford)&lt;br /&gt;said-" There has been a gradual but modified intake of recruits for the&lt;br /&gt;Women's Auxiliary Australian Air Force in the last six weeks.&lt;br /&gt;Authority has ' been given for two separate drafts to be enrolled,&lt;br /&gt;approximately doubling the strength of the organization since the&lt;br /&gt;change of Government. An impression seems to have grown up that&lt;br /&gt;recruiting for the Women's Auxiliary Australian Air Force. has been&lt;br /&gt;stopped. I am sure that this announcement will correct that impression.&lt;br /&gt;The general principle of the future employment of women&lt;br /&gt;in the Women's Auxiliary Australian Air Force and other defence&lt;br /&gt;services will be considered by Cabinet with a review of man-power&lt;br /&gt;problems, housing, uniforms and costs of such services."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 3, page 9.)&lt;br /&gt;WEARING OF UNIFORMS.&lt;br /&gt;On 28th November, 1941, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) said--&lt;br /&gt;" The following are the women's organizations within the Defence&lt;br /&gt;Services for whom uniforms have been authorized-&lt;br /&gt;Navy.-Women's Royal Australian Naval Service;&lt;br /&gt;Army.-Australian Army Nursing Service, Australian Army&lt;br /&gt;Women's Service, Voluntary Aid Detachments;&lt;br /&gt;Air.-Women's Auxiliary Australian Air Force, Royal Ajistralian&lt;br /&gt;Air Force Nursing Service.&lt;br /&gt;Outside the Defence Services, the Red Cross Society, St. John'z,&lt;br /&gt;Ambulance and Girl Guides have long been recognized as bodies&lt;br /&gt;wearing uniforms.&lt;br /&gt;" Numerous other outside women's organizations throughout the&lt;br /&gt;Commonwealth at present wear uniforms. The recently gazetted&lt;br /&gt;amendment to the National Security ( General) Regulations, relating&lt;br /&gt;to the wearing of uniforms, is not designed to prohibit the wearing of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;uniform by members of women's unofficial organizations created in&lt;br /&gt;connexion with the war effort, if some type of uniform is desired by&lt;br /&gt;them, provided that it is not ' similar to any uniform or emblem of the&lt;br /&gt;Naval, Military or Air Forces of the Commonwealth, or of any other&lt;br /&gt;part of the King's dominions, or of any women's auxiliary force,&lt;br /&gt;detachment or service established by the ' Commonwealth ii connexion&lt;br /&gt;with any of those Forces SPORT IN WAR-TIME.&lt;br /&gt;PRIME MINISTER'S STATEMENT.&lt;br /&gt;On 21st November, 1941, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) said:-&lt;br /&gt;In my judgment, sport is not detrimental to the war effort. There&lt;br /&gt;are thousands of the population who are engaged in the war effort, and&lt;br /&gt;for whom the playing of games is a positive refreshment and a good&lt;br /&gt;thing for their own physical welfare and for the morale of the country.&lt;br /&gt;It is also a matter for great satisfaction that so many men who have&lt;br /&gt;been prominent in sport have enlisted in the forces, and that others&lt;br /&gt;who have not enlisted, but are engaged in the war effort, have intimated&lt;br /&gt;that they are not available for a regular programme of games. I do not&lt;br /&gt;see why attending football matches-which attract huge crowds-should&lt;br /&gt;not be a positive benefit to people who work indoors all the week; many&lt;br /&gt;on war jobs. I see more merit in such outdoor recreation than in&lt;br /&gt;recreation indoors, provided, of course, that moderation and common&lt;br /&gt;sense are observed.&lt;br /&gt;" It would be a demonstration to the world of the spirit of the&lt;br /&gt;British race if Australia and England resumed test matches immediately&lt;br /&gt;~ fter the war. Our race does not live by bread alone. I think&lt;br /&gt;that sport, such as cricket, is just as important to the British race&lt;br /&gt;as the performance of Shakespeare. I think the two things go together&lt;br /&gt;in making us what we are. The English lord and the London bus&lt;br /&gt;driver both regard Hobbs as their common property. They watch the&lt;br /&gt;weather with equal anxiety before a test match.&lt;br /&gt;" Things of the spirit and grace, and courtesy, are not merely&lt;br /&gt;valuable traits of our character. They are the things that distinguish&lt;br /&gt;us from other races, and enrich our whole lives. Demands by some&lt;br /&gt;sections that racing should be restricted will be discussed at a Premiers'&lt;br /&gt;Conference in Canberra early in the new year. Ample powers for&lt;br /&gt;control of racing are vested in the States and if there is to be any&lt;br /&gt;regulation of racing the States should be the responsible authority to&lt;br /&gt;take uniform action." AIRCRAFT PRODUCTION.&lt;br /&gt;INQUIRY INTO FINANOES.&lt;br /&gt;On 21st November, 1941, the Minister for Aircraft Production&lt;br /&gt;( Senator Cameron) said that Mr. W. T. Harris, of the Sub-Treasury,&lt;br /&gt;Melbourne, had been appointed full-time finance member of the Aircraft&lt;br /&gt;Commission and had been asked to go thoroughly into the Commission&lt;br /&gt;and make a report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;COTTON FABRIC FOR. AEROPLANE WINGS.&lt;br /&gt;On 29th November, 1941, the Minister for Air ( Mr. Drakeford)&lt;br /&gt;said " An Australian-made cotton fabric, embodying improvements&lt;br /&gt;designed to conform with the more rigid war-time requirements 9f&lt;br /&gt;Royal Australian Air Force machines, is now being fitted to the wings&lt;br /&gt;of trainer aircraft. A shortage of the imported prdduct vill resulf: in&lt;br /&gt;an extension of the use of locally manufactured material. This represents&lt;br /&gt;yet another step in Australia's policy of maximum self-sufficiency,"&lt;br /&gt;WAR-TIME PROFITS TAX.&lt;br /&gt;PROPOSED COMMITTEE.&lt;br /&gt;In Parliament.-On 21st November, 1941, the Prime Minister&lt;br /&gt;( Mr. Curtin) said-&lt;br /&gt;" I give Mr. Holt, an assurance that the suggestion that a&lt;br /&gt;Parliamentary Committee on war-time profits tax legislation be set up&lt;br /&gt;will receive the most sympathetic consideration. I had hoped that: such&lt;br /&gt;a committee would hav* e been established last year. Mr. Holt is no&lt;br /&gt;doubt aware that representatives were actually named by the Opposition&lt;br /&gt;to sit on such a committee. It was subsequently discovered, however,&lt;br /&gt;that the activities of the proposed committee were to be restricted to&lt;br /&gt;an examination of the sales tax measures of the Government. I had&lt;br /&gt;hoped that it would be empowered to make a general review of the&lt;br /&gt;Government's taxation arrangements."&lt;br /&gt;WOOL AGREEMENT.&lt;br /&gt;REVIEW NOT MADE.&lt;br /&gt;In. Parliament.-On 21st November, 1941, the Minister for the&lt;br /&gt;Interior, on behalf of the Minister for Commerce ( Mr. Scully), said.-&lt;br /&gt;" The Government finds that the understanding between the United&lt;br /&gt;Kingdom and Australian Governments is that the price of wool may be&lt;br /&gt;reviewed in May of each year. The Government has also ascertained&lt;br /&gt;that the previous Government failed to initiate any such review. On&lt;br /&gt;account of this failure it may not be possible to arrange any change&lt;br /&gt;in the price until the 1942-3 clip. The Government at present has this&lt;br /&gt;matter under consideration."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 3, page 8.)&lt;br /&gt;ARMY INVENTIONS BOARD.&lt;br /&gt;MINISTER TO REVIEW.&lt;br /&gt;' On 22nd November, 1941, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Forde)&lt;br /&gt;said he intended to review the present set-up of the Inventions&lt;br /&gt;Boards and particularly the Army Head-quarters Inventions Section&lt;br /&gt;with a view to ensuring a more expeditious consideration of submissions.&lt;br /&gt;Six hundred inventions a week were submitted to the inventions&lt;br /&gt;section of the Army. Only about ten had been accepted but a considerable&lt;br /&gt;number, which showed great promise, were being investigated.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No 2, page No 5, page 7.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LEASE-LEND NEGOTIATIONS.&lt;br /&gt;On 23rd November, 1941, the Prime Minister'( Mr. Curtin) said-&lt;br /&gt;There is no substance in the suggestions made that there have&lt;br /&gt;. been hitches in Lease-Lend negotiations between the United States&lt;br /&gt;and Australia, caused by the change of Government in Australia. The&lt;br /&gt;United States-Government ' has not asked the Commonwealth Government&lt;br /&gt;to give guarantees not to expand or establish new industries in&lt;br /&gt;Australia because of the benefits being derived by Australia under&lt;br /&gt;Lease-Lend from the United States. The undertakings given by the&lt;br /&gt;United Kingdom Government to the United States Government are&lt;br /&gt;fully set out in the White Paper which was issued on 10th September.&lt;br /&gt;1941. The decisions embodied in this White Paper were made by&lt;br /&gt;President Roosevelt and Mr. Churchill during the period when they&lt;br /&gt;were drawing up the Atlantic Charter in August, 1941.&lt;br /&gt;" Discussions are proceeding in the United States concerning sur-J&lt;br /&gt;plus products, particularly on the effect of the supply of primary products&lt;br /&gt;by the United ' States to the United Kingdom under Lease-Lend&lt;br /&gt;on the marketing of Australian primary products in surplus production.&lt;br /&gt;' The Government has not received any detailed reports on this subject&lt;br /&gt;from its officers in the United States."&lt;br /&gt;SHIPBUILDING.&lt;br /&gt;MARINE ENGINES.&lt;br /&gt;On 24th November, 1941, the Minister for the Navy ( Mr. Makin)&lt;br /&gt;said that a marine engine factory to cost &#339; 700,000 would be built at&lt;br /&gt;Fisherman's Bend ( Victoria). With the Minister for Health ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;Holloway) and the chairman of the Australian Shipbuilding Board&lt;br /&gt;( Rear-admiral McNeil), he had inspected sites for the factory-&lt;br /&gt;( For earier references, please see No. 5. page 22.)&lt;br /&gt;SIR EARLE PAGE, M. P.&lt;br /&gt;STATUS IN GREAT BRITAIN.&lt;br /&gt;On 24th Novemiber, 1941, commenting on a question to be asked in&lt;br /&gt;the Rouse of Lords by Lord Davies, concerning the status of Sir Earle&lt;br /&gt;Page, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) said-&lt;br /&gt;" It is for Mr. Churchill and not for me to answer the questiona.&lt;br /&gt;I know of no reason, however, why there should be any question&lt;br /&gt;concerning the status of Sir Earle Page. Re has attended meetings of&lt;br /&gt;teBritish War Cabinet; had consultations and discussions with&lt;br /&gt;Ministers and has had regular contact with the Prime Minister. He&lt;br /&gt;has met him separately and also in the War Cabinet. Sir Earle Page iFs&lt;br /&gt;not a member of the British War Cabinet, but has attended meetings&lt;br /&gt;of it. As I have said before, Sir Earle Page is an accredited representative&lt;br /&gt;of the Australian Government to the British Government to&lt;br /&gt;represent our views on war policy. The British Prime Minister said&lt;br /&gt;he would be pleased to receive him. Communications I have received&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;from Sir Earle rage intim.* a ' te* that he, ' w' a* s received mst cordially and&lt;br /&gt;that every facility was given to him to carry out his mission-which&lt;br /&gt;was to state the Australian Government's views on war policy in&lt;br /&gt;Great Britain. There is no occasion to define Sir Earle Page's&lt;br /&gt;position. He is the representative of the Australian GoverlirnentA. and&lt;br /&gt;not my personal representative. He was nominated by the preiious&lt;br /&gt;Govern * ment to proceed to England and we authorized him to continue&lt;br /&gt;his mission. He is the spokesman for the Australian Government.&lt;br /&gt;Both Mr. Churchill and Sir Earle Page have expressed satisfaction&lt;br /&gt;with the position and until either of them finds the present position&lt;br /&gt;unsatisfactory, I do not propose taking any notice of Lord Davies."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 2, page 12.)&lt;br /&gt;GENERAL SIR THOMAS BLAMEY.&lt;br /&gt;RETURN TO MIDDLE EAST.&lt;br /&gt;On 24th November, 1941, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Forde)&lt;br /&gt;said-" General Sir Thomas Blarney, General Officer Commanding the&lt;br /&gt;Australian Imperial Force in the Middle East, will leave later this&lt;br /&gt;week for the Middle East."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 4, page 3; No. 5, page&lt;br /&gt;OWEN SUB-MACHINE GUN.&lt;br /&gt;CONFERENCE ON PRODUCTION.&lt;br /&gt;On 24th November, 1941, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Forde)&lt;br /&gt;said-" The conference to-day on the Owen gun was completely satisfactory,&lt;br /&gt;and a number of points which were holding up production&lt;br /&gt;were cleared up. I believe that the facto~ ry will be in full swing&lt;br /&gt;producing the gun within a week or so. The first order is for 2,000&lt;br /&gt;guns, but I have no doubt that further orders will be given. I am&lt;br /&gt;satisfied that the gun is an efficient weapon and it is the Government's&lt;br /&gt;aim to see that our men are given an adequate supply of modern&lt;br /&gt;equipment at least equal to the best our enemies can produce. -The&lt;br /&gt;question of paying royalty to Mr. Owen did not arise. It is a matter&lt;br /&gt;on which the Government will give an equitable decision. Mr. Owen&lt;br /&gt;is at present concentrating on getting the gun into production, and has&lt;br /&gt;not worried about royalties." AMMUNITION IMPORTED.&lt;br /&gt;On 27th November, 1941, Mr. Forde said-*&lt;br /&gt;The ammunition to be used in the Owen sub-machine gun will be&lt;br /&gt;of 9 ' millimetre calibre. Until production in Australia starts, the&lt;br /&gt;amnmunition will be imported in ample quantities."&lt;br /&gt;&#339; For earlier references, please see No. pages 6-7.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;COAL-MINING INDUSTRY.&lt;br /&gt;STRIKE ARBITRATOR.&lt;br /&gt;On 24th November, 1941, the Minister for Labour ( Mr. Ward)&lt;br /&gt;said-" Unfortunately, the chairman of the Central Reference Board&lt;br /&gt;( Judge Drake-Brockman) has ' been unable to act because of." severe&lt;br /&gt;illness, and another mIember of the Arbitration Court, who, he&lt;br /&gt;suggested, might replace him during his temporary absence, was unable&lt;br /&gt;to act this week. In these circumstances, I decided to appoint a&lt;br /&gt;special Conciliation Commissioner to hear and determine the matters&lt;br /&gt;in dispute expeditiously, and I have asked the Attorney-General, Dr.&lt;br /&gt;Evatt, to make the services of the Deputy-Registrar of the Federal&lt;br /&gt;Arbitration Court ( Mr. D. Morrison) available. Mr. Morrison has&lt;br /&gt;had great experience in industrial matters. I have asked that the&lt;br /&gt;hearing be begun forthwith."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 6, page 9; No. 7, page&lt;br /&gt;PRIME MINISTER'S APPEAL.&lt;br /&gt;On 25th November, 1941, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) said--&lt;br /&gt;" I have to-day sent the following urgent telegram to the General&lt;br /&gt;President, Central Council, Australian Coal and Shale Employees'&lt;br /&gt;Federation, Sydney:-&lt;br /&gt;am obliged, having regard to the total national problem, to request&lt;br /&gt;in the most positive terms, the co-operation of your Council on behalf of the&lt;br /&gt;Federation in ensuring the maximum production of coal which is indispensable,&lt;br /&gt;as things stand, to the prosecution of the war.&lt;br /&gt;For the information of your Council, I can say that the priority of requests&lt;br /&gt;we have from our Allies for supplies cannot be met unless coal is available in&lt;br /&gt;greater quantities of munitions and related production than has been the case.&lt;br /&gt;' The policy of the Government is to ensure the speediest impartial decision&lt;br /&gt;in respect of industrial grievances. Any such grievances which you represent , to&lt;br /&gt;me will have my immediate attention followed by action.&lt;br /&gt;' On your part I request that your influence be exerted fully in ensuring that&lt;br /&gt;no stoppage of production occurs anywhere. My information is that last&lt;br /&gt;fortnight approximately, 00,000 tons more coal would have been produced but&lt;br /&gt;for stoppages which were avoidable and in my view should not have happened.&lt;br /&gt;.' Two things are paramount with the Labour Government, namely justice&lt;br /&gt;for the workers and victory in the war. The first, even if we get it now,&lt;br /&gt;would only'. be temporary if the second were not accomplished. These two&lt;br /&gt;things are inseparably associated.&lt;br /&gt;' I sincerely hope that these vital considerations will appeal to the members&lt;br /&gt;of the Federation all over Australia. JoHN CUBTIN, Prime Minister.'&lt;br /&gt;Later that day, Mr. Curtin said-&lt;br /&gt;" I have to-day received, in answer to my telegram, the following&lt;br /&gt;reply from the general president ( Mr. C. Nelson) and the general&lt;br /&gt;secretary ( Mr. G. W. S. Grant) of the Coal Employees' Federation:-&lt;br /&gt;" Acknowledge receipt your telegram relative to importance of continuous&lt;br /&gt;coal production and other observations contained in your telegram.. Central&lt;br /&gt;Executive definitely assures you their fullest co-operation and are taking all&lt;br /&gt;steps to ' see that your telegram reaches every rank and file member throughout&lt;br /&gt;the Commonwealth of Australia.'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WALLARAH STRIKE SETTLED.&lt;br /&gt;In Parliament.-On 25th November, 1941, Mr. Ward said-&lt;br /&gt;" I am pleased to announce that the men are no longer underground&lt;br /&gt;( at Wallarah Colliery). As the result ' of negotiations with&lt;br /&gt;the representatives of the men they decided to leave the mine at&lt;br /&gt;11.30 o'clock to-day. There is now no stoppage, of. pr6duction on&lt;br /&gt;the coal-fields." ( For earlier references, please see No. 7, page&lt;br /&gt;HEALTH AND YOUTH WELFARE.&lt;br /&gt;SDEPUTATION TO MINISTER.&lt;br /&gt;On 24th November, 1941, the Minister for Health ( Mr. Holloway)&lt;br /&gt;met representatives of 75 refugee doctors who had adopted Australia as&lt;br /&gt;their permanent home. They asked for recognition, and for permission&lt;br /&gt;to practice in Australia. Mr. Holloway told the deputation that their&lt;br /&gt;request would be given serious consideration. He would seek advice of&lt;br /&gt;State health authorities and of the ' Commonwealth 1Attorney-General&lt;br /&gt;on the possibility of using the services of, at least, some of the&lt;br /&gt;applicants, with proper safeguards. It wourd fiecessary to ensure&lt;br /&gt;that if refugee doctors were admitted to practice in Australia, they must&lt;br /&gt;stay in the district in which they were required, and that their&lt;br /&gt;practice would not worsen the conditions of Service medical men when&lt;br /&gt;they returned to private practice.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 7, page&lt;br /&gt;SOCIAL SECURITY.&lt;br /&gt;GOVERNMENT'S PLANS FOR FUTURE.&lt;br /&gt;On 24th November, 1.941, the Minister for Social ; Services ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;Holloway) said-&lt;br /&gt;" It is hoped to extend the Invalid and Old-age Pensions Act to&lt;br /&gt;cover Australian aborigines living under civilized conditions, and to&lt;br /&gt;exempt from income the amount invalid and olId-age ,. pensiners&lt;br /&gt;receive by way of war pensions. So far as child, endowment&lt;br /&gt;is concerned, piat eits chsosp. ede r to introduce arienidments. providing&lt;br /&gt;for cases where parents are separated and their children, are&lt;br /&gt;living under divided control, and also to provide child endowment for&lt;br /&gt;all children under sixteen years of age of a widowed mother. It is&lt;br /&gt;the Government's intention to introduce a scheme of pensions for&lt;br /&gt;widows, unemployment insurance, and a housing planning authority as&lt;br /&gt;soon as possible after Parliament meets in the New Year."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 2, page&lt;br /&gt;TASMANIAN WAR INDUSTRIES.&lt;br /&gt;COMMITTEE TO BE APPOINTED.&lt;br /&gt;In Parliament.-On 25th November, 1941, the Prime Minister&lt;br /&gt;( Mr.. Curtin) said-&lt;br /&gt;The Commonwealth Government has approved of a , request by the&lt;br /&gt;Premier of Tasmania that an investigation . on,. lines, similar, to . that&lt;br /&gt;recently conducted in Western Australia should be made into the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;economic position Of ' Tasmania as affected by conditions arising from&lt;br /&gt;the war. A committee will be appointed to make a survey.. of the&lt;br /&gt;economic position of Tasmania as affected by, and in relation to,&lt;br /&gt;Australia's war problems, and war effort and will report thereon to the&lt;br /&gt;Commonwealth Government with such general recommendations as its&lt;br /&gt;survey suggests. Details regarding the composition of the committee&lt;br /&gt;will be the subject of consultations between the Commonwealth and&lt;br /&gt;Tasmanian Governments." ( For earlier references, please see No. 7, page 14.)&lt;br /&gt;BRITISH EMPIRE MEDALS.&lt;br /&gt;On 25th November, 1941, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) said&lt;br /&gt;that His Excellency the Governor-General had communicated to. him&lt;br /&gt;the text of an announcement which His Majesty the King had approved&lt;br /&gt;shall be promulgated. The announcement is-*&lt;br /&gt;His Majesty the King has approved a recommendation that any person to&lt;br /&gt;whom British Empire Medals has been or may be awarded may on all occasions&lt;br /&gt;when use of such letters is customary piace after his or her name the letters&lt;br /&gt;This includes recipients of Medal of Order of British Empire awarded&lt;br /&gt;pirto December 29, 1922, as well as those who received Medal of Order of&lt;br /&gt;ritish Empire for Meritorious Service after that date."&lt;br /&gt;WHEAT-STABILIZATION SCHEME.&lt;br /&gt;BREACHES OF REGULATIONS.&lt;br /&gt;In Parliament.-On 25th November, 1941, the Minister for Commerce&lt;br /&gt;( Mr. Scully) said-&lt;br /&gt;" Representations have, been made concerning the position of a&lt;br /&gt;number of wheat-growers who have planted excess areas and are unable&lt;br /&gt;to secure sufficient labour to prevent this excess from maturing to&lt;br /&gt;grain. As those growers had broken the regulations they were instructed&lt;br /&gt;to cut the excess areas for hay or to prevent it maturing, but rural&lt;br /&gt;labour was not available. In the circumstances provision is being&lt;br /&gt;made for growers to harvest the excess wheat. This is intended to&lt;br /&gt;apply only to those who find it impossible to dispose of their surplus.&lt;br /&gt;Growers who can deal with their surplus wheat must do so. Provision&lt;br /&gt;is being made to protect the interests of growers who have observed the&lt;br /&gt;regulations. Excess wheat harvested will be delivered to the Wheat&lt;br /&gt;Board, but the first advance paid to growers for wheat acquired will&lt;br /&gt;not be paid on the excess. The payment for it will ' be determined later..&lt;br /&gt;and will not be sufficient to show a profit to those who have evaded the&lt;br /&gt;regulations." ( For earlier references, please see No. 5, pages 8-15.)&lt;br /&gt;ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE.&lt;br /&gt;AWARDS FOR GALLANTRY.&lt;br /&gt;On 25th November, 1941, the Minister for Air ( Mr. Drakeford)&lt;br /&gt;said-" Since the war began 71 Australians serving in the Air Forces of&lt;br /&gt;the British Empire have been awarded decorations for*' gallantry.&lt;br /&gt;These decorations include a Victoria Cross,. 83 Distinguished. Flying&lt;br /&gt;Crosses and seven Distinguished. Flying Medals."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S TOBRUK ACTION.&lt;br /&gt;On 26th November, 1941, Mr. Drakeford said-&lt;br /&gt;" An Australian squadron has been in action against enemy forces&lt;br /&gt;over Tobruk. Many other Royal Australian Air Force airmen, trained&lt;br /&gt;under the Empire air scheme, are also participating in the Battle of&lt;br /&gt;Libya as'' inembers of Royal Air Force squadrons."&lt;br /&gt;CHRISTMAS LEAVE.&lt;br /&gt;On 27th November, 1941, Mr. Drakeford said that Royal Australian&lt;br /&gt;Air Force Christmas leave would amount to nine days in some cases.&lt;br /&gt;Christmas Day, Boxing Day and New Year's Day would be observed&lt;br /&gt;as holidays for all Royal Australian Air Force personnel and wherever&lt;br /&gt;practicable, the week-end following Christmas Day would be regarded&lt;br /&gt;as th'" monthly long week-end period, Personnel whose normal&lt;br /&gt;quarterly leave credits fell due over this period would also be given&lt;br /&gt;Christmas Day, Boxing Day and New Year's Day. Trainees at&lt;br /&gt;Schools of Technical Training would-be granted leave from 21st&lt;br /&gt;December to 29th Decemnber, inclusive. The Empire air training&lt;br /&gt;scheme involved the maintenance of numerous courses with a scheduled&lt;br /&gt;intake and output. An extended period of leave could not be granted&lt;br /&gt;to the whole Royal Australian Air Force without a dislocation of&lt;br /&gt;training, the effects of which would be felt for some months afterwards.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 5, page 18.)&lt;br /&gt;AIR TRAINING SCHEME INVESTIGATION.&lt;br /&gt;Oh 28th November,. 1941, Mr. Drakeford said-&lt;br /&gt;To secure information on overseas air training methods,' the&lt;br /&gt;Royal Australian Air Force Director of Training ( Air-Commodore&lt;br /&gt;G. Jones) will shortly undertake a coiprehensive tour of Empire&lt;br /&gt;air scheme schools in Canada. Air-Coinmodore Jones was expected:&lt;br /&gt;to bring back to Australia information ' which would be of value in&lt;br /&gt;the peifection of our own training methods. Progress in the'" training&lt;br /&gt;of Aiistralian airmen in Canada and the general welfare of Australian&lt;br /&gt;trainees there will also be investigated."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 7, page 3.)&lt;br /&gt;INCOME TAX.&lt;br /&gt;REPORT OF PARLIAMENTARY COMMITTEE.&lt;br /&gt;In Parliament.-On 25th November,. 1941, the Treasurer ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;" I. table the report of the committee. which was appointed to inquire&lt;br /&gt;into certain income tax proposals contained in the amending income tax&lt;br /&gt;legislation at present before this House. : The report relates solely to,&lt;br /&gt;deductions allowable under the Income Tax Assessment Act in respect&lt;br /&gt;of calls paid to mining companies.&lt;br /&gt;" The recommendation of the committee is to the effect that, in lieu&lt;br /&gt;of the provision in the existing law for the deduction of the amount paid&lt;br /&gt;I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as calls to mining companies, oil companies, and afforestation companies,&lt;br /&gt;the act should make provison for a rebate, calculated at onethird&lt;br /&gt;of the rate of income tax imposed for the financial year. on . the&lt;br /&gt;amount of calls paid; The recommendation was made unanimously by&lt;br /&gt;the members of the committee, and the Government proposes to bring&lt;br /&gt;forward during the-committee stages of the bill the necessary amendment&lt;br /&gt;to implement it.&lt;br /&gt;" The Government has decided that the committee shall continue to&lt;br /&gt;function for the purpose of examining, in the New Year, the position&lt;br /&gt;in regard to the taxation of dividends received from ex-Australian&lt;br /&gt;mining companies. It will also survey the incidence of taxation on&lt;br /&gt;private companies, and investigate any anomalies, submitted to it in&lt;br /&gt;writing, ' which experience of the new legislation may bring to light."&lt;br /&gt;S[ The-miemrbers.: of the committee, were Messrs. Chifley, Scullin,&lt;br /&gt;Menzies, Fadden, Coles and Spooner, M's. P.]&lt;br /&gt;PETROL. SUPPLIES.&lt;br /&gt;LAKES ENTRANCE FIELD.&lt;br /&gt;On 25th November, : 1941, the Minister for Supply and Development&lt;br /&gt;( Mri Beasley) said:--&lt;br /&gt;" The Commonwealth Government has decided to make available a&lt;br /&gt;sum of &#339; 33,333 to the Austral Oil Drilling Syndicate ( Lakes Entrance,&lt;br /&gt;Victoria). In addition to this sum, the Victorian Government will&lt;br /&gt;make available &#339; 16,667. In each case the money advanced will be by&lt;br /&gt;way of loan to the company. Approval has been given for the company&lt;br /&gt;to raise &#339; 150,000. The Government has also approved of effect being&lt;br /&gt;given to the Ranney-Fairbanks report on the Lakes Entrance oilfield.&lt;br /&gt;The report claims that oil can be recovered on a commercial&lt;br /&gt;basis and can be used for rough lubrication purposes as it comes from&lt;br /&gt;the well and, if filtered, would be suitable for finer lubrication; but&lt;br /&gt;probably not for continuous use in motor cars unless refined. . The oil&lt;br /&gt;is in demand for flux required in the making of bitumen roads and also&lt;br /&gt;has distinct possibilities as a fuel oil. The Commonwealth Geological&lt;br /&gt;Adviser ( Dr. Raggatt) estimates that the time required to reach&lt;br /&gt;production will be about eighteen months."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 6, page&lt;br /&gt;WAR CONTRACTS.&lt;br /&gt;PAYMENT OF ROYALTIES.&lt;br /&gt;In Parliament.-On 25th November, 1941, the Attorney-General&lt;br /&gt;( Dr. Evatt) said:-&lt;br /&gt;The investigation which I have caused to be made up to the&lt;br /&gt;present is preliminary. I am giving. close consideration to the present&lt;br /&gt;legal and administrative position to prevent.. the Commonwealth from&lt;br /&gt;being buidened with expenditure in relation to real or alleged monopoly&lt;br /&gt;rights, and, what is equally important, extravagant legal claims which&lt;br /&gt;are often put forward in connexion therewith for so-called .' manufacturing&lt;br /&gt;rights' and ' proprietary processes' or the like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;" I am invoking the valuable assistance of the Auditor-General and&lt;br /&gt;his officers to assist me in seeingthat&lt;br /&gt;no payments for royalties or right akin thereto are&lt;br /&gt;made by the Commonwealth unless they are fully justified&lt;br /&gt;by the law and the facts; and&lt;br /&gt;that so far as possible payments which have been made&lt;br /&gt;without sound legal foundation are disgorged.&lt;br /&gt;After I have had an opportunity of making a more complete&lt;br /&gt;investigation I shall be in a position of throwing further light."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 4, page&lt;br /&gt;AUSTRALIAN MILITARY FORCES.&lt;br /&gt;TEMPERANOE DEPUTATION.&lt;br /&gt;On 25th November, 1941, a deputation representing the Australian-&lt;br /&gt;Temperance Council waited upon the Mipister for the Army ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;Forde) and urged that the Government should reconsider the policy of&lt;br /&gt;having wet canteens in military camps; extend facilities for the use&lt;br /&gt;and sale of fruit juices for troops at Darwin and abroad; increase hostel&lt;br /&gt;accommodation and recreation facilities for troops, and have military&lt;br /&gt;control of hotels near military camps; prohibit the sale of intoxicating&lt;br /&gt;liquor to soldiers and women in uniform; prohibit, for liquor advertising&lt;br /&gt;purposes, pictures showing soldiers, sailors, airmen and women&lt;br /&gt;in uniform. Mr. Forde said the matters were of major policy and&lt;br /&gt;would be submitted to Cabinet.&lt;br /&gt;BANKING CONTROL.&lt;br /&gt;WAR-TIME REGULATIONS.&lt;br /&gt;On 26th November, 1941;-the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin). said-&lt;br /&gt;The National Security ( War-time Banking Control) Regulations,&lt;br /&gt;tabled in Parliament to-day, give effect to the Government's decisions,&lt;br /&gt;as outlined in the recent financial statement, to bring the operations&lt;br /&gt;of the trading banks under effective war-time control. The Regulations&lt;br /&gt;implement certain recommendations of the Royal Commission on the&lt;br /&gt;Monetary and Banking Systems and make other provisions to meet&lt;br /&gt;the present conditions of war finance. Before finalizing the regulations&lt;br /&gt;the Government had conferences with the representatives of the trading&lt;br /&gt;hanks and the Commonwealth Bank.&lt;br /&gt;It is generally agreed that the private banks play such an important&lt;br /&gt;part in our financial system that control of their activities is&lt;br /&gt;essential to an effective war finance policy. Experience elsewhere confirms&lt;br /&gt;this view and in the United Kingdom, United States of America&lt;br /&gt;and other countries the authorities , have exercised greatly increased&lt;br /&gt;direction of banking and financial policy generally.&lt;br /&gt;The Regulations are planned primarily to achieve two purposes.&lt;br /&gt;Firstly, they ensure that the investment and loan policy of the banks&lt;br /&gt;should accord with the general principle laid down to govern civil&lt;br /&gt;investment, thus closing a major gap hitherto existing. Secondly,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;they are designed to prevent the war financial policy of the Government&lt;br /&gt;increasing the. profits of the private banks and providing the basis&lt;br /&gt;for an-unsound expahsion of credit.&lt;br /&gt;To aciieve these purposes the regulations provide that the banks,&lt;br /&gt;in making advances and linvestments, shall comply with the policy laid&lt;br /&gt;down by' tie. o ii'nwqbe alth Bank from time to time and provide also&lt;br /&gt;that the trading-bank . shall lodge in a special account with the Commonwealth'Bank,&lt;br /&gt;a. substantial part of the increase in their total assets&lt;br /&gt;since' August, 1939. It is. intended that surplus investible funds which&lt;br /&gt;accrue in the -future shall also be lodged with the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;Bank. These funds will remain the property of the private banks and&lt;br /&gt;will bear interest to lie paid. by the Commonwealth Bank&amp;gt;: The rate&lt;br /&gt;of interest payable will be, determined by the , Commonwealth Bank&lt;br /&gt;but itmay not exceed a maximum rate fixed. by the Treasurer..&lt;br /&gt;" The trading banks are required . also to provide such information&lt;br /&gt;and returns, as are necessary to the Commonwealth Bank and the&lt;br /&gt;Treasurer &#339; for . the purposes of the regulations. The accounts of the&lt;br /&gt;banks will, b. e. in. vatigated periodically by the Auditor-General.&lt;br /&gt;bdli'ev&amp;amp; that' ' i'hse Regulations mark a definite step forward.&lt;br /&gt;Not only can we be assured that the operations of the financial system&lt;br /&gt;will, iiifutitre,' b directed wholly towards our common national purposes,-&lt;br /&gt;ut'iiW: e bcanfiel even more confident than before of the stability&lt;br /&gt;of that system.&lt;br /&gt;" One important effect of the Regulations is that the' Government.&lt;br /&gt;and the Commonwealth Bank will now be in a position to ensure that&lt;br /&gt;every private bank follows a policywhich will operate in the national&lt;br /&gt;interest and at the same time provide additional safeguards for the&lt;br /&gt;security of the deposits of the public with the banks. In concise terms,&lt;br /&gt;the Regulations provide--&lt;br /&gt;1. Within three weeks of the coimencement of the Regulations all private&lt;br /&gt;banks will be'licenied bly-the Governor-General.&lt;br /&gt;,,. 2.. 2, rijg te ; bankto beplicensed will be the Ballarat Banking, Co. Ltd.; the&lt;br /&gt;Bank of Adelaie;. the'Ban' of Australasia; the Bank of New South Wales; the&lt;br /&gt;Baih'ki'F; NW-Zdealand;' thleBrisbane Permanent Building and Banking Co. Ltd.;&lt;br /&gt;the Commdreial'ai. B nki oftAustralia Ltd.; the Commercial Banking Co. of&lt;br /&gt;Sydney. Limited FCqpNtoatiiro nal d'Escompte de Paris; the English Scottishand&lt;br /&gt;a " us'liBaannIk the National Bank of Australasia Ltd.; ' the QueenslandN'-.&lt;br /&gt;Nif nal BihnlMCLtd the Union Bank of Australia Ltd. and the Yokohama&lt;br /&gt;Specie;' ak; LtdE&lt;br /&gt;3. The ' Governor-General may withdraw a bank's licence only on a High&lt;br /&gt;Court judge's recorimen'dations.&lt;br /&gt;Private banks can make advances only in accordance with Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;Bank policy. Subscriptions ' to loans and the purchase of securities by private banks&lt;br /&gt;must be made only with the prior consent of the Commonwealth Bank.&lt;br /&gt;0. The Commonwealth Bank, in accordance with general principles approved&lt;br /&gt;by the Treasurer, -will determine what portion of the private banks' surplus&lt;br /&gt;funds available for' inestment are to be deposited in a special account,&lt;br /&gt;7. Surplus funds, available for investment mean . the amount by which a&lt;br /&gt;bank's, total assets ' at any time exceed the average of the total assets on the&lt;br /&gt;weekly balancing. days ih"-August, 1939.&lt;br /&gt;8. Interest is. to be paid by the Commonwealth Bank to banks -on their&lt;br /&gt;balances in the speqial account at a. rate not above the maximum fixed by the&lt;br /&gt;Treahur. asn&amp;amp; desidge'd" td eisure that the banks' profits shall not exceed the&lt;br /&gt;average foi; tIth ree, yirended: August 31, 1939.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9. Private banks' balance-sheets and profit and loss accounts will be published&lt;br /&gt;in a' form specified by the Treasurer. More detailed profit and loss accounts&lt;br /&gt;shall be furnished to the Treasurer through the Commonwealth Bank.&lt;br /&gt;The Treasurer and the Commonwealth Bank shall be furnished with&lt;br /&gt;such statements of private banks' business as required but not details of&lt;br /&gt;individual customers' accounts.&lt;br /&gt;11. The Auditor-General is empowered periodically, and as directed by the&lt;br /&gt;Treasurer, to inspect the books, accounts and transactions of the private&lt;br /&gt;banks and report to the Commonwealth Bank and the Treasurer.&lt;br /&gt;12. Exemptions from the Regulations may be made by the Treasurer.&lt;br /&gt;An exemption from the Regulations is being granted for two&lt;br /&gt;months to all institutions ( other than the private banks referred to)&lt;br /&gt;which are, or appear to be, carrying on in Australia the business of&lt;br /&gt;banking. This exemption will cover the Launceston and Hobart&lt;br /&gt;Savings Banks, also pastoral companies and other institutions which&lt;br /&gt;carry on some banking functions. This temporary exemption will give&lt;br /&gt;time for inquiry and consideration as to whether any of these institutions&lt;br /&gt;should be brought within the Regulations.&lt;br /&gt;It will be seen that the Treasurer will work in close collaboration&lt;br /&gt;with the Commonwealth Bank in administering the Regulations.&lt;br /&gt;Broadly, the powers the Regulations confer are divided almost evenly&lt;br /&gt;betw9en the Treasurer and the Commonwealth Bank with joint powers&lt;br /&gt;in some instances.&lt;br /&gt;The Regulations mean that banking will be subject to the same&lt;br /&gt;kind of control as are all other phases of our national life that are&lt;br /&gt;vital to the war effort.&lt;br /&gt;" In future a person or corporation ( other than a bank of the&lt;br /&gt;Commonwealth or of any State) shall not carry on the business of&lt;br /&gt;banking except under licence from the Governor-General."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 1, page 24; No. 3, page 22; No.&lt;br /&gt;page&lt;br /&gt;NEW GUINEA.&lt;br /&gt;ENTRY INTO UNCONTROLLED AREAS.:&lt;br /&gt;On .26th November, 1941, the Minister for External . Territories&lt;br /&gt;( Senator Fraser) said he was unable to vary the decision that applica&lt;br /&gt;tions could not be granted at present to enter uncontrolled areas of;&lt;br /&gt;New Guinea. to prospect for petroleum. A system. had bee-established&lt;br /&gt;to ., prate. t the natives-as. well as prospectors and others. Owing to&lt;br /&gt;the enlistment of many administration officers in the fighting services&lt;br /&gt;the Administration was unable to take measures to extend its influence&lt;br /&gt;to the more remote areas of the Territory. The areas which had been,&lt;br /&gt;the subject of representations by companies anxious to prospect for&lt;br /&gt;petroleum were deep within uncontrolled areas.&lt;br /&gt;RECRUITING FOR SERVICES.&lt;br /&gt;SIR THOMAS BLAMEY'S REPORT:' i&lt;br /&gt;On 26th November, 1941, the Minister for the Armiy ( Mr. Forde)'&lt;br /&gt;said-.. " General Sir Thomas Blamey's report on recruiting ' aS not beeni&lt;br /&gt;before me yet, but when it arrives it will be fully considered&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AUSTRALIAN MILITARY FORCES.&lt;br /&gt;EAST-WEST STRATEGIC ROAD.&lt;br /&gt;On 26th November, 1941, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Forde)&lt;br /&gt;said that the reconstruction of the east-west strategic road, linking&lt;br /&gt;Adelaide and Perth, was rapidly nearing completion. When rebuilt&lt;br /&gt;the road would be able to carry traffic in. any kind of weather.&lt;br /&gt;RECREATION HUTS AT DARWIN.&lt;br /&gt;On 29th November, 1941, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Forde)&lt;br /&gt;said he had approved the construction of fourteen huts for recreation&lt;br /&gt;and educational facilities for troops in the Northern Territory. The&lt;br /&gt;huts would be in various camps and some would be near Darwin. The&lt;br /&gt;total cost of the huts, furnishings and fittings would be &#339; 8,540.&lt;br /&gt;1941-42 BUDGET.&lt;br /&gt;EXCISE ON BREWERY PRODUCTS.&lt;br /&gt;In Parliament--On 26th November, 1941, the Minister for Supply&lt;br /&gt;( Mr. Beasley) said-&lt;br /&gt;" Mr. Clark,' asked me whether breweries were permitted to&lt;br /&gt;issue invoices stamped with the condition ' Subject to alteratibn in&lt;br /&gt;price owing to, increase in excise'.-The Minister for Customs ( Senator&lt;br /&gt;Keane) rferred the matter to the Prices Commissioner, who&lt;br /&gt;stated that under the present order fixing the price of beer, . breweries&lt;br /&gt;are not permitted to make sales on such conditional terms. If Mr.&lt;br /&gt;Clark, will supply to the Prices Commissioner information as&lt;br /&gt;to any transaction of that kind, suitable action will be taken:."&lt;br /&gt;SUPPLEMENTARY STATEMENT.&lt;br /&gt;In Parliament.-On 27th. November, 1941, the Treasurer ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;" In my financial statement of the 29th October, 1941, I set out&lt;br /&gt;the financial proposals of the Government. Certain ameiidments to&lt;br /&gt;the" proposal relating to taxation have been made by Parliai~ it I&lt;br /&gt;shall biiefly summarize these amendments, and show their effect on&lt;br /&gt;the budget for 1941-42.&lt;br /&gt;" It was proposed that the taxable incomes of husbands and wives&lt;br /&gt;should be aggregated in order to determine the rate of tax to be paid&lt;br /&gt;by both husband and wife on their taxable incomes. This proposal&lt;br /&gt;was considerably modified, and the new principle of aggregation' for&lt;br /&gt;rating purposes will operate only in respect of income fioin assets&lt;br /&gt;transferred after the 29th October, 1941, by a husband to his wife if&lt;br /&gt;the taxable income of the wife exceeds &#339; 200.&lt;br /&gt;" The Government' had proposed to remove the present exemption&lt;br /&gt;so as to provide that dividends received by Australian residents from&lt;br /&gt;companies,; the profits, of which are derived wholly or partly from outside&lt;br /&gt;Australia, should be -taxable in the hands of the recipients. By&lt;br /&gt;an amendment dividends from. this source which were receiv&amp;amp; l prior&lt;br /&gt;to the 29th October, 1941, will not be subject to tax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;" It was proposed to discontinue the practice of allowing as deductions&lt;br /&gt;in arriving at taxable income calls paid on shares in mining&lt;br /&gt;companies. The law has been amended by Parliament. This means&lt;br /&gt;that the value of the tax concession on mining calls will be approximately.&lt;br /&gt;the same as the concession which was enjoyed before the war.&lt;br /&gt;The ' Government had proposed that the war-time" company tax&lt;br /&gt;should be amended to provide for a statutory percentage of 4 per cent..&lt;br /&gt;and that the commencing rate of tax should be 6 per cent.' until a&lt;br /&gt;maximum rate of 78 per cent. is reached on the taxable profit in excess&lt;br /&gt;of 16 per cent. on capital employed. The Government accepted an&lt;br /&gt;amendment and the commencing rate of tax will now be' 5' per cent.&lt;br /&gt;progressing by 6 per cent. steps for every 1 per cent: boh capital'employed&lt;br /&gt;by . which profits are in excess of the statutory percentAge of 5 per&lt;br /&gt;cent. on capital employed until a maximum rate of 78 per'cent. is&lt;br /&gt;reached' on ' the taxable profit in excess of 17 per cent. on capital&lt;br /&gt;employed. The effect of these alterations is to reduce the estimated revenue&lt;br /&gt;for 194142 by &#339; 1,800,000, viz.:--Estimate of Revised&lt;br /&gt;29th October, Reduction. Estimate.'&lt;br /&gt;1941.&lt;br /&gt;Income Tax' 56,950,000 1,000,000 55,950,000&lt;br /&gt;War-time ( Company Tax and Super Tax 8,000,000 800,000 .7,200,000&lt;br /&gt;Other Revenue items ( unaltered) 120,677,000 120,677,000&lt;br /&gt;185,627,000 1,800,000 183,827,000&lt;br /&gt;" As a result, the amount which it is estimated will be available&lt;br /&gt;from the revenue budget for war expenditure,, is reduced from&lt;br /&gt;&#339; 82,147,000 to &#339; 80,347,000. The revised budget ' summary will thereforebe-&lt;br /&gt;Estimated total revenue 183,827,000,&lt;br /&gt;Estimated expenditure-&lt;br /&gt;. Services other than War Services as&lt;br /&gt;shown in the Financial Statements of&lt;br /&gt;29th October, 1941 103,480,000.,&lt;br /&gt;Proportion of cost of War Services to be&lt;br /&gt;S -charged to the budget 80,347,000' .183,827,000&lt;br /&gt;" There will be a consequential increase of &#339; 1,800,000' in the amount&lt;br /&gt;of war. expenditure to be met from loan fund. The estimated total war&lt;br /&gt;expenditure of &#339; 221,485,000 for the year will, therefore, be financed as&lt;br /&gt;follows:-1941-42&lt;br /&gt;( Estimated).&lt;br /&gt;Loan cash balances at beginning of year 2,229,000&lt;br /&gt;Revenue 80,347,000&lt;br /&gt;Loans 138,909,000&lt;br /&gt;221,485,000&lt;br /&gt;" The estimated total loan expenditure for 1941-42 will now be&lt;br /&gt;increased to &#339; 143,738,000, of which &#339; 2,600,000 is for civil works, and&lt;br /&gt;the balance for war purposes."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 3, page 3; No. 4, page 19; No. 6,&lt;br /&gt;page 6.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DEPARTMENTS -AT CANB, ERRA.&lt;br /&gt;:* GOVERNMEN'S ACTIVITIES.&lt;br /&gt;Sl Parliament.-On 26th November, 1941, the Minister for the&lt;br /&gt;Interior ( Senator Collings) said-&lt;br /&gt;" Shortly after the assumption of office, this Government transferred&lt;br /&gt;to Canberra the central office staffs of the Pensions Branch and the&lt;br /&gt;Departmentof Home Security. The provision of accommodation for&lt;br /&gt;the transfer, of, additional departments depends upon the funds that ' i&lt;br /&gt;can be, made available by the Treasurer. Funds for the successful&lt;br /&gt;prosecution of the , war must have first call on the money available to i&lt;br /&gt;the Treasury... Tenders are now being called for the. completioh of&lt;br /&gt;Melbourne. Buildings at Civic Centre. The buildings, when completed,&lt;br /&gt;will be used for -office accommodation. The staffs to be transferred to&lt;br /&gt;the. new buildings will be decided upon when the work is nearing completion&lt;br /&gt;in about nine months' time. The buildings will accommodate&lt;br /&gt;about 350 officers. This year there will be a re-vote of &#339; 87,000 and an&lt;br /&gt;additional sum of &#339; 200,000 for housing under the Department of the&lt;br /&gt;Interior. It has been stated publicly that it is the intention of the&lt;br /&gt;Government to transfer to Canberra as many of the government&lt;br /&gt;departments as possible, with the exception of the Service departments,&lt;br /&gt;which must remain in Melbourne during the war. The Government&lt;br /&gt;will do everything within its power to bring to Canberra the central&lt;br /&gt;staffs of as many departments as possible, subject to funds being&lt;br /&gt;available for the purpose."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 1, page 13; No. 5, page&lt;br /&gt;ROYAL AUSTRALIAN NAVY.&lt;br /&gt;AWARDS FOR GOOD SERVICE.&lt;br /&gt;On 26th November, 1941, the Minister for the Navy ( Mr. Makin)&lt;br /&gt;said-" The King has approved the following awards to Australian&lt;br /&gt;personnel for good service in the Mediterranean:-&lt;br /&gt;Distinguished Service Order-Commander A. S.... Rosenthal,&lt;br /&gt;R. A. N.&lt;br /&gt;Distinguished Service Cross-iSub-Lieutenant P. S. Colclough,&lt;br /&gt;R. A. N. V. R.&lt;br /&gt;Distinguished Service Medal-Acting Leading Seaman R. J.&lt;br /&gt;Anderson, R. A. N."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 7, page&lt;br /&gt;S FLINDERS NAVAL DEPOT LEAVE.&lt;br /&gt;On 27th November, 1941, Mr. Makin said that men at Flinders&lt;br /&gt;Naval Depot would receive 21 days at Christmas instead of the&lt;br /&gt;customary fourteen days. This would compensate for the lost of long&lt;br /&gt;week-end leave from Friday to Monday which the demands of war had&lt;br /&gt;made it necessary to withdraw. Long week-end leave would be allowed&lt;br /&gt;to all ratings not directly concerned with training routine.&lt;br /&gt;By Authority: L. F. JOHNSTON, Commonwealth Government Printer, Canberra.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>