<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6</transcript-id>
    <title>DIGEST OF DECISIONS AND ANNOUNCEMENTS AND IMPORTANT SPEECHES BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RIGHT HON. J. B. CHIFLEY - NO. 116</title>
    <prime-minister>Chifley, Ben</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19450713 - 19491219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/07/1946</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000006_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects />
    <content>&lt;p&gt;No. 116.&lt;br /&gt;
PERIOD. 1ST1! JUNE, 1946, TO 10TH JULY, 1946.&lt;br /&gt;
By Autboh,:&lt;br /&gt;
L F. Jomm#. C~ mmonwealh Govenimem Pdnt. CAbs&lt;br /&gt;
( Printed in Awiufim)&lt;br /&gt;
COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT.&lt;br /&gt;
DIGEST OF DECISIONS&lt;br /&gt;
AND ANNOUNCEMENTS&lt;br /&gt;
IMPORTANT SPEECHES&lt;br /&gt;
BY&lt;br /&gt;
THE PRIME MINISTER&lt;br /&gt;
( THE RIGHT HON. J. B. CHIFLEY). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MIGRATION.&lt;br /&gt;
PASSPORTS--RESTRICTIONS, RELAXATIONS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 18th June, 1946, the Minister for Immigration ( Mr. Calwell) announced&lt;br /&gt;
that restrictions imposed under National Security Act Regulations on the&lt;br /&gt;
issue of passports would be lifted from 1st July, 1946. Passports for Japanl&lt;br /&gt;
would be excepted. Any person would then be able to secure a passport&lt;br /&gt;
to leave Australia by complying with the usual conditions. Restrictions&lt;br /&gt;
on the issue of passports to doctors and nurses would be lifted. Previously,&lt;br /&gt;
passports had been issued only to doctors and nurses wishing to do postgraduate&lt;br /&gt;
courses or gain experience in overseas hospitals. Persons going&lt;br /&gt;
to Britain must undertake to remain away for twelve months or until shipping&lt;br /&gt;
facilities became available for their return without inconveniencing&lt;br /&gt;
persons in the priority classes.&lt;br /&gt;
BRITISH MIGRANTS-CHILDREN.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
Legal guardianship of British children who were evacuated to Australia&lt;br /&gt;
during 1940 for the duration of the war was vested in the Minister for the&lt;br /&gt;
Interior ( later changed to the Minister for Immigration), and through him&lt;br /&gt;
in the various State Child Welfare Departments under National Security&lt;br /&gt;
( Oversea Children) Regulations. Of the 577 children who came to Australia,&lt;br /&gt;
over 100 are remaining here, some temporarily to complete educational&lt;br /&gt;
courses or apprenticeships and others permanently.&lt;br /&gt;
Cabinet decided to-day that, with the expiry of the National Security&lt;br /&gt;
Act on 31st December, 1946, legislation be introduced to enable the Minister&lt;br /&gt;
for himnigration to continue as the legal guardian of overseas children who&lt;br /&gt;
remain in Australia and also as the legal guardian of children brought to Australia&lt;br /&gt;
under any governmental or non-governmental immigration organization."&lt;br /&gt;
INDUSTRIAL.&lt;br /&gt;
STRIKES-COMPARATIVE FIGURES.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 19th June, 1946, the Minister for Labour ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
Holloway) said-&lt;br /&gt;
The number of industrial disputes and working days lost fron 1939-45&lt;br /&gt;
inclusive have been-Disputes. Days Lost.&lt;br /&gt;
1939 416 459,154&lt;br /&gt;
1940 350 1,507,252&lt;br /&gt;
1941 567 984,174&lt;br /&gt;
1942 602 378,195&lt;br /&gt;
1943 785 990,161&lt;br /&gt;
1944 941 912,752&lt;br /&gt;
1945 45 2,119,641&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 103, page &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;STRIKES-PRIME MINISTER'S SPEECH.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 4th July, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley)&lt;br /&gt;
said-Rightly or wrongly, and I am not entering into that at the moment,&lt;br /&gt;
men in Queensland are on strike. I am not attempting to condone the&lt;br /&gt;
strike I merely point out that if the men have decided that they will not&lt;br /&gt;
work, they cannot be forced by law to go to work. What then is the next&lt;br /&gt;
step They may be fined, and if they do not pay the fine they may be&lt;br /&gt;
sent to jail. But the application of such a policy has never been successful&lt;br /&gt;
in settling an industrial dispute. 1 defy anybody to prove to me that such&lt;br /&gt;
action has ever produced industrial peace or effected a settlement of an&lt;br /&gt;
industrial dispute. I have been associated with many industrial disputes.&lt;br /&gt;
Even if a mistress has a difference with her house-maid, I am expected to&lt;br /&gt;
intervene. The Leader of the Country Party ( Mr. Fadden) wants me, on&lt;br /&gt;
behalf of the Government, to intervene in the Queensland meat dispute,&lt;br /&gt;
Ilthough the State Industrial Court is in control of it and the State Govltenent,&lt;br /&gt;
under its emergency powers, is operating the. relevant legislation&lt;br /&gt;
to deal with it. What form of intervention does he propose Does he&lt;br /&gt;
want me to order the men back to work&lt;br /&gt;
I cannot visualize the Commonwealth Government intervening in this&lt;br /&gt;
dispute, regrettable though it is. I do not attempt to condone it. The&lt;br /&gt;
State Industrial Court, and the State Government with its emergency powers,&lt;br /&gt;
has all the law that is needed. Will the enforcement of that law bring&lt;br /&gt;
the dispute to an end We know that it will not. Intervention ly tile&lt;br /&gt;
Commonrwealth Government would only make confusion worse confounded.&lt;br /&gt;
All the parties to the dispute have been strong-minded, and have&lt;br /&gt;
hotly supported the stand they have taken. There is too much strongmindedness&lt;br /&gt;
in many industrial disputes. I do not deny that I would have&lt;br /&gt;
tried to induce the parties to come together. I could not, of course,&lt;br /&gt;
approach the Industrial Court. I do not know whether the State Government&lt;br /&gt;
or the Premier would be able to make any approach to the court,&lt;br /&gt;
because it has made the declaration, You must go back to work before&lt;br /&gt;
we shall do ; nything'. The employers say, We will not meet you until&lt;br /&gt;
you go back to work The reply of the employees is, We will not return&lt;br /&gt;
to work except under pre-strike conditions'. Mr. Fadden has urged that&lt;br /&gt;
the Commonwealth Government should intervene because of the influence&lt;br /&gt;
that is being wielded by Communists. I have received hundreds of telegrams&lt;br /&gt;
from those whom he has described as Communists, asking me to&lt;br /&gt;
intervene in total disregard of the State Industrial Court and the State&lt;br /&gt;
Government. To do that would be to destroy the effect of the Queensland&lt;br /&gt;
law and the judgment of the Industrial Court; not that that would worry&lt;br /&gt;
me very much, because I believe that there are some faults on that side.&lt;br /&gt;
In my opinion, had the employers been prepared to give way a little, the&lt;br /&gt;
strike could have been settled.&lt;br /&gt;
Mr. Fadden wants me to override the State Industrial Court and the&lt;br /&gt;
State Government, by the exercise of a power possessed by the Common.-&lt;br /&gt;
wealth in other words, to flout the Queensland law and the State court.&lt;br /&gt;
We have been unable to discern in what way any law that we could operate&lt;br /&gt;
would be more effective than the laws which the Queensland Government &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;has the power to operate. Their application, of course, does not get the&lt;br /&gt;
men back to work. There a great deal that I could say about the dispute&lt;br /&gt;
but I do not waut to add fuel to the fire. I have been very disappointed&lt;br /&gt;
at the trend of events. As a matter of fact, almost every day since I&lt;br /&gt;
returned front abroad I have been told that negotiations were proceeding&lt;br /&gt;
, and that the dispute would be settled. Yet it has dragged on from day to&lt;br /&gt;
day. I do not want Mr. Fadden or this House to believe that I am happy&lt;br /&gt;
about the position. If the Commonwealth were to engage in a fight not&lt;br /&gt;
nily with the strikers, but also, if you like, with the'employers, the Queensland&lt;br /&gt;
Government and the State Industrial Court, the state cf affairs would&lt;br /&gt;
be akin to legislative anarchy. Had the Commonwealth Government issued&lt;br /&gt;
an order stating that the meat-workers should return to work under prestrike&lt;br /&gt;
conditions, the order would have been obeyed. But that would&lt;br /&gt;
have been a complete flouting of the Queensland Industrial Court. It&lt;br /&gt;
would have 1le e totally at variance withl the wishes of the State Government&lt;br /&gt;
; aid would have been violently opposed by the employers. Merely because&lt;br /&gt;
we did not wish to flout other laws that were operating in respect of the&lt;br /&gt;
matter, such an order was not issued.&lt;br /&gt;
The matter does not involve a return to work at award rates.&lt;br /&gt;
Apparently, some agreements between the employers and employees have&lt;br /&gt;
been operating for a period of years, giving to the employees considerable&lt;br /&gt;
benefits which are not provided for in the award. At least, that claim is&lt;br /&gt;
made by the employers and the court. The matter does not . touch the&lt;br /&gt;
tour men who were dismissed from their employment in a bacon factory.&lt;br /&gt;
I believe that their dispute could have been settled by the court separately.&lt;br /&gt;
The Communists, near-Communists, or Cryptos-call them what you willare&lt;br /&gt;
the very people who have been asking us to step in and override the&lt;br /&gt;
State laws by saying to the employees, ' Go back to work on pre-strike&lt;br /&gt;
conditions The dispute is most unfortunate. I do not make any apology,&lt;br /&gt;
nor does the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Scullv), for having asked the&lt;br /&gt;
Meat Controller to see whether personal contact would produce a better&lt;br /&gt;
feeling and result in the men returning to work.&lt;br /&gt;
We cannot drive men back to work. They are really in no different&lt;br /&gt;
position from that of the milk producers who refused to supply milk. Men&lt;br /&gt;
have the right to refuse to work. I admit that it is unjust to the community.&lt;br /&gt;
In the final analysis, I suppose men have the right to dispose&lt;br /&gt;
of their labour just as the man who produces wheat or any other commodity&lt;br /&gt;
has the right to dispose of it.&lt;br /&gt;
I believe that if suitable action had been taken to bring employers and&lt;br /&gt;
employees together a settlement might have been reached long ago. However,&lt;br /&gt;
I cannot see why the Commonwealth Government should attempt to&lt;br /&gt;
override the State Industrial Court in opposition to the State Government,&lt;br /&gt;
, or why we should attempt to override the State emergency legislation."&lt;br /&gt;
UNEMPLOYMENT-FIGURES.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 4th July, 1946, the Minister for Post-war Reconstruction&lt;br /&gt;
( Mr. Dedman) said-&lt;br /&gt;
The total number of persons unemployed in Australia on 21st June,&lt;br /&gt;
1946, was 11,100, about 60 per cent. of whom were receiving unemployment &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;benefit. The other 40 per cent. were receiving a re-employment allowance&lt;br /&gt;
as ex-servicemen while awaiting employment in the type of work thrlv&lt;br /&gt;
desired." PRIMARY INDUSTRIES.&lt;br /&gt;
POULTRY FARMING-EGGS, CONTROL, CESSATION FIXED.&lt;br /&gt;
On 19th June, 1946, the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Scully) announced&lt;br /&gt;
that the control of the egg industry under National Security Act Regulations&lt;br /&gt;
would continue in operation until 31st December, 1946, when the Act expired.&lt;br /&gt;
It was previously proposed that control should cease on 30th June, 1946,&lt;br /&gt;
in view of the establishment of a central organization by the several State&lt;br /&gt;
Egg Marketing Boards known as Egg Boards of Australia Limited which&lt;br /&gt;
intended to take over control of the industry as from 1st July, 1946.&lt;br /&gt;
Circumstances precluded the company from commencing operations and he&lt;br /&gt;
had authorized continuance of Commonwealth control until 31st December.&lt;br /&gt;
1946, before which date the position regarding the organization should he&lt;br /&gt;
clarified. EXPORTS TO BRITAIN--EGGS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 19th June, 1946, Mr. Scully announced that exports to the British&lt;br /&gt;
Ministry of Food from Ist July to 31st December, 1946, would be 1,000,000&lt;br /&gt;
cases of eggs, equivalent to 30,000,000 dozen eggs as well as about 20,000,0C. 1&lt;br /&gt;
lb. of frozen egg pulp, equivalent to nearly 17,000,000 dozen eggs.&lt;br /&gt;
COTTON-BOUNTY.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1946, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Fraser) said that&lt;br /&gt;
the Raw Cotton Bounty Act would expire on 31st December, 1946, and the&lt;br /&gt;
Government had decided to introduce legislation to extend the operation&lt;br /&gt;
of the Act sc that producers would be guaranteed that the present net&lt;br /&gt;
return of 15d. per lb. of raw cotton above the grade known as strict good&lt;br /&gt;
ordinary" would be continued on cotton produced in Australia during&lt;br /&gt;
1947 and each year until 31st December, 1951. The guaranteed net returns&lt;br /&gt;
would be computed after taking into account the net return from by-products&lt;br /&gt;
of raw cotton. Raw cotton of '. strict good ordinary" or lower grades&lt;br /&gt;
would continue to receive bounty at half the appropriate rate as provided&lt;br /&gt;
under the Act. The bounty had been extended subject to'the Queensland&lt;br /&gt;
Government making every endeavour to implement undertakings given&lt;br /&gt;
during 1939-40 to improve the efficiency of cotton growing.&lt;br /&gt;
PARLIAMENT.&lt;br /&gt;
BROADCASTING-BILL INTRODUCED.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 19th June, 1946, the Postmaster-General ( Senator&lt;br /&gt;
Cameron) introduced the Parliamentary Proceedings Broadcasting Bill.&lt;br /&gt;
Senator Cameron said-&lt;br /&gt;
The broadcasting of the proceedings of the Commonwealth Parliament&lt;br /&gt;
has received the careful consideration of the Government, and it has decided&lt;br /&gt;
that arrangements be made for these broadcasts to be introduced during &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tihe present session. Investigations have demonstrated that it is not&lt;br /&gt;
practicable to ( establish a separate network of medium-wave stations to&lt;br /&gt;
broadcast the proceedings of Parliament. In any case, the establishment&lt;br /&gt;
of such a network would involve an expenditure in the neighbourhood of&lt;br /&gt;
' 500,000. The Goverunment considers that it would be preferable to commence&lt;br /&gt;
the service on some modified plan which would not cause so much disturbanice&lt;br /&gt;
to existing programme arrangements. The Government has reached&lt;br /&gt;
the conclusion that the service should be commenced on an experimental&lt;br /&gt;
basis, the broadcasts of parliamentary proceedings being confined at the&lt;br /&gt;
outset to the second national station in the capital city of each State and&lt;br /&gt;
in Newca: ttle. If, as expected, the innovation proves acceptable to the&lt;br /&gt;
public, it will 1) 0bnee cessary to determine from time to time the extent to&lt;br /&gt;
which the facilities it is intended to use at first should be expanded. Accordingly,&lt;br /&gt;
provision has been made in the bill for the employment of such of the&lt;br /&gt;
other national stations as may be prescribed. Consideration would, of&lt;br /&gt;
course, be given to the use of short-wave stations.&lt;br /&gt;
The Government holds the. view that control of the broadcasts should&lt;br /&gt;
lie exercised by Parliament itself through a joint parliamentary committee.&lt;br /&gt;
The bill accordingly provides for the appointment of a committee including&lt;br /&gt;
the President of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Representatives.&lt;br /&gt;
It will be appreciated that there are a number of details to be settled in connexion&lt;br /&gt;
with the apportionment of broadcasting time between both Houses&lt;br /&gt;
of the Parliament when they are sitting simultaneously, and in regard to&lt;br /&gt;
the rights of members, technical and programme arrangements. It is the&lt;br /&gt;
Government's desire that the joint committee should examine all these&lt;br /&gt;
questions and recommend to Parliament the general principles on which&lt;br /&gt;
the broadcasts should be undertaken. After the adoption of its recommendations&lt;br /&gt;
by both Houses, the joint committee will control the subsequent&lt;br /&gt;
arrangements. From tinm'' to time questions may arise which will require&lt;br /&gt;
prompt attention and it is desirable that the joint committee should have&lt;br /&gt;
authority to delegate, to a sub-committee, its powers to determine the days&lt;br /&gt;
on which, and the periods during which, the proceedings of either House&lt;br /&gt;
shall be broadcast.&lt;br /&gt;
" The Government accepts the view that the immunities and privileges&lt;br /&gt;
applying to debates within Parliament should be extended to the broadcasts&lt;br /&gt;
parliamentary proceedings.&lt;br /&gt;
The Bill embraces the foregoing conclusions and, in anticipation of&lt;br /&gt;
it being acceptable to Parliament, arrangements have been made, with the&lt;br /&gt;
concurrence of the President of the Senate and the Speaker of the House&lt;br /&gt;
of Representatives, for the erection of a control booth in each House and for&lt;br /&gt;
the installation of such equipment as is necessary to enable the broadcasts&lt;br /&gt;
to be undertaken. It should be practicable to commence the broadcasting&lt;br /&gt;
of parliamentary proceedings before the end of the present session, the actual&lt;br /&gt;
' late being determined'by the joint committee, which will be selected as&lt;br /&gt;
; oon as the measure becomes law." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Parliament.-On 20th June, 1946, Senator Cameron moved the&lt;br /&gt;
following amendment:-&lt;br /&gt;
One of the members of the committee shall be the President of the Senate, one&lt;br /&gt;
member shall be the Speaker of the Hou.' e of Representatives, and, of the other four&lt;br /&gt;
members of the committee, two shall be members of, and appointed by, the Senate&lt;br /&gt;
and two shall be members of, and appointed by, the House of Representatives.&lt;br /&gt;
[ The amendlment w~ is carried.]&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 4th July, 1946, the Minister for Information ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
Calwell) moved an amendment to the Parliamentary Proceedings Broadcasting&lt;br /&gt;
Bill to provide that the Joint Committee on the broadcasting of&lt;br /&gt;
parliamentary proceedings -hlould comprise nine members inst-:: r! of six.&lt;br /&gt;
[ The amendment was carried and, later, was carried in the Senate.]&lt;br /&gt;
[ The bill was passed.]&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 5th July, 1946, the Speaker ( Mr. Roscvear), chairman,&lt;br /&gt;
the President ( Senator Brown), Senators Arnold and Gib-, o, Messrs.&lt;br /&gt;
Corser, Fraser, Haylen, Holt and Sheehan were appointed members of thl&lt;br /&gt;
Joint Committee on the Broadcasting of Parliamentary Proceedings.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 5th July, 1946, the Joint Committee submitted the&lt;br /&gt;
following report:-&lt;br /&gt;
Days on which proceedings shall be broadcast: The proceedings of Parliament.&lt;br /&gt;
shall be broadcast on each day on which either House is sitting.&lt;br /&gt;
Period during which proceedings shall be broadcast: The broadcast shall commence&lt;br /&gt;
on each sitting day at the time fixed for the meeting of the House whose opening&lt;br /&gt;
proceedings are to be broadcast on that day as determined by the Joint Committee.&lt;br /&gt;
and shall cease when the adjournment is moved in the House which is being broadcast&lt;br /&gt;
at that time.&lt;br /&gt;
Allocation of broadcasting time between the Senate and tie House of Representatives:&lt;br /&gt;
The allocation of broadcasting time between the Senate and the House of Representatives&lt;br /&gt;
shall be in accordance with the views of the Joint Committee, or its sub-committee,&lt;br /&gt;
on the importance of the impending debate and the public interest attaching thereto.&lt;br /&gt;
The committee recognizes that in practice more time will be allotted to the House of&lt;br /&gt;
Representatives than to the Senate.&lt;br /&gt;
Re-broadcast of questions without notice and answers Within the limits of time&lt;br /&gt;
available, questions without notice and answers in each House shall be re-broadcast&lt;br /&gt;
between 7.20 p. m. and 7.55 p. m. on each sitting day.&lt;br /&gt;
Broadcast and re-broadcast through national stations: No broadcast or re.&lt;br /&gt;
broadcast of the proceedings of either House shall be made except through national&lt;br /&gt;
broadcasting stations unless the Joint Committee otherwise determines.&lt;br /&gt;
[ The report was adopted.]&lt;br /&gt;
PRIVILEGE-PARLIAMENTARY PAPERS.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.--On 4th July, 1946, the Acting Attorney-General&lt;br /&gt;
( Mr. Holloway) introduced the Parliamentary Papers Bill. Mr. Holloway&lt;br /&gt;
said-This bill proposes to give absolute protection against civil or criminal&lt;br /&gt;
proceedings, for example proceedings for libel, in respect of the publication&lt;br /&gt;
under the authority of a parliamentary committee of any document laid&lt;br /&gt;
before the committee or of any evidence given befo: re the committee.&lt;br /&gt;
The Parliamentary Papers Act, which the bill proposes to amend, provides,&lt;br /&gt;
amongst other things, that no action or proceedings, civil or criminal&lt;br /&gt;
shall lie against any person for publishing any document published under&lt;br /&gt;
the authority of the Senate or the House of Representatives. Tlhe act does&lt;br /&gt;
not apply to publication under the authority of a parliamentary committee &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but where the evidence given before a parliamentary committee is tabled&lt;br /&gt;
in either House of the Parliament and ordered by that House to be printed&lt;br /&gt;
the protection given by the act applies.&lt;br /&gt;
However, when evidence is tabled and ordered to be printed, a large&lt;br /&gt;
number of copies must be printed to meet the requirements of the circulation&lt;br /&gt;
list for parliamentary papers. For example, on the tabling of the report&lt;br /&gt;
of the Standing Committee on Broadcasting regarding proposed staff&lt;br /&gt;
regulations for the Australian Broadcasting Commission, the number of&lt;br /&gt;
copies printed was 660. It is considered that the expense of printing the&lt;br /&gt;
weidence before parliamentary committees as a parliamentary paper is not&lt;br /&gt;
always justified. As an instance, the Standing Committee on Broadcasting&lt;br /&gt;
considers that the number of copies of the evidence given before it which,&lt;br /&gt;
generally speaking, need be printed is about 40. I feel sure that where a&lt;br /&gt;
committee itself arranges the publication of evidence before it with the&lt;br /&gt;
object of saving public money, it should not be deprived of the protection&lt;br /&gt;
of the Parliamentary Papers Act. It may be that the publication is already&lt;br /&gt;
privileged either at common law or by virtue of section 49 of the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
Constitution, but it is considered desirable to put the matter beyond&lt;br /&gt;
doubt. The bill is designed to achieve this object and applies to documents&lt;br /&gt;
; nd evidene, published after 23rd September, 1943." [ The bill was passed.]&lt;br /&gt;
ENEMY ALIENS.&lt;br /&gt;
OVERSEAS INTERNEES-INQUIRY, MR. JUSTICE SIMPSON'S&lt;br /&gt;
REPORT.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 19th June, 1946, the Minister for Immigration&lt;br /&gt;
Calwell) said-&lt;br /&gt;
Mr. Justice Simpson was appointed by the Government to inquire&lt;br /&gt;
into the cases of a number of enemy aliens who were still being held in&lt;br /&gt;
internment. He was asked to report to the Government as to which&lt;br /&gt;
persons should be released to remain in residence in this country, and as&lt;br /&gt;
to which persons should be repatriated to their homelands. The Government&lt;br /&gt;
has decided to carry out Mr. Justice Simpson's recommendations in&lt;br /&gt;
their entirety. A number of perons are being held in internment pending&lt;br /&gt;
repatriation they will be repatriated as soon as shipping is available.&lt;br /&gt;
If shipping is not available before the expiration of the National Security&lt;br /&gt;
Act, special legislation will be enacted to enable me to give effect to&lt;br /&gt;
Mr. Justice Simpson's recommendations."&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
When the National Security Act ceases on 31st December, 1946, there&lt;br /&gt;
will be no power by which enemy aliens interned during the war and whose&lt;br /&gt;
repatriation has been recommended by a Supreme Court judge in the&lt;br /&gt;
interests of public safety and the defence of the Commonwealth can be&lt;br /&gt;
repatriated. Further, because of lack of shipping, it may not be possible&lt;br /&gt;
to give effect to the judge's recommendatious before the act expires.&lt;br /&gt;
S" Cabinet to-day decided that the Minister for Immigration ( Mr. Calwell)&lt;br /&gt;
prepare a bill to provide for the repatriation of aliens who were interned &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;during the war and after an inquiry by a judicial authority are deemed to&lt;br /&gt;
be a menace to the security of the Commonwealth the control of the movements&lt;br /&gt;
of aliens interned during the war and released while awaiting&lt;br /&gt;
repatriation following a judicial inquiry which deemed them to be a menace&lt;br /&gt;
to the security of the Commonwealth and the repatriation of aliens who,&lt;br /&gt;
after a judicial inquiry, are deemed to be a danger to the security of the&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth." NATIONAL UNIVERSITY.&lt;br /&gt;
BILL INTRODUCED.&lt;br /&gt;
In PI'rliaentl.--On 19th June, 1946, the Minister for Post-war Reconstruction&lt;br /&gt;
( Mr. Dedman) introduced the Australian National University&lt;br /&gt;
Bill. Mr. Dedman said--&lt;br /&gt;
The Government is anxious that the national university which this&lt;br /&gt;
bill seeks to establish should be established in such manner that it will bring&lt;br /&gt;
credit to Australia, advance the cause of learning and research in general,&lt;br /&gt;
and take its rightful place among the great universities of the world. For&lt;br /&gt;
this reason I will sympathetically consider any amendment, with th,.&lt;br /&gt;
object of helping the university achieve these ends.&lt;br /&gt;
" Australia has gained a justifiably high reputation in university&lt;br /&gt;
teaching and research, and the Government believes that the establishment&lt;br /&gt;
of an Australian national university at Canberra will bring still further&lt;br /&gt;
credit to our country, not only by the work done within its own walls by its&lt;br /&gt;
own staff and research students, but also by collaboration and co-operation&lt;br /&gt;
between its members and the research workers and teachers of the other&lt;br /&gt;
Australian universities. With the help and encouragement of other&lt;br /&gt;
universities, anid of all men and women'of good will, the national university&lt;br /&gt;
will soon be in a px: ition to take its share in solving many complex problems&lt;br /&gt;
which are the joint responsibility of all universities.&lt;br /&gt;
The establishment of a university is a matter of considerable complexity&lt;br /&gt;
and a very great responsibility. For this reason the Government&lt;br /&gt;
has not acted hastily. I have discussed the problems involved with the&lt;br /&gt;
Minister for the Interior ( Mr. Johnson), with other Ministers concerned.&lt;br /&gt;
with the Vice-Chancellors of the Universities of Sydney and Melbourne&lt;br /&gt;
and with groups of distinguished scientists who have been called together&lt;br /&gt;
by the Inter-Departmental Committee on Education to advise on the&lt;br /&gt;
general and detailed questions associated with this project. In addition.&lt;br /&gt;
the Government has had the help and advice of the Canberra University&lt;br /&gt;
College Council.&lt;br /&gt;
The essence of democratic government is that all national issues must&lt;br /&gt;
ultimately be decided by the people themselves. To me it is more than&lt;br /&gt;
ever important at tais stage in Australia's development that the Australian&lt;br /&gt;
people should have available everything they need to permit their decisions&lt;br /&gt;
to be made wisely and after a full understanding of the issues involved.&lt;br /&gt;
Both in Australia and in the world at large, innumerable problems await&lt;br /&gt;
solution if the future is to be made safe and the people placed in a position&lt;br /&gt;
to enjoy the fruits of the developments in science and in human relationships&lt;br /&gt;
during the last six years. The first thing that must be done is to &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ensure that these developments are studied in relation particularly to their&lt;br /&gt;
. Lpplication in Australia. Progress in physical science has culminated in&lt;br /&gt;
the harnessing of atomic energy and this has brought the world to its final&lt;br /&gt;
crossroads. Mishandled, these discoveries in the physical world can make&lt;br /&gt;
peace and prosperity impossible. Properly used' they may introduce an&lt;br /&gt;
era of happiness and prosperity unparalleled in world history. It is essential&lt;br /&gt;
that Australia, in common with the other nations of the world, should do&lt;br /&gt;
ieverything possible to foster that careful research which will allow us to&lt;br /&gt;
become the masters, not the servants, of our physical environment. In&lt;br /&gt;
medicine, too, the outstanding achievements of the war years await full and&lt;br /&gt;
proper application to the civil needs of our people. Once again this implies&lt;br /&gt;
patient research by all the talent at our disposal and demands the establishnient&lt;br /&gt;
of appropriate institutions at which this research may be conducted.&lt;br /&gt;
The Government feels that the university now proposed for Canberra is&lt;br /&gt;
nHe appropriate place in which this research may be carried out. On the&lt;br /&gt;
side of human relationships, our continued development, and a full under-&lt;br /&gt;
-tanding of our problems, requires that we encourage research into the&lt;br /&gt;
social sciences. Here, more than in any other field of learning, Australia&lt;br /&gt;
lhas an outstanding contribution to make to the world at large. In&lt;br /&gt;
economics, history, law, anthropology, and in all the related social sciences,&lt;br /&gt;
Australia i n a particularly advantageous position.&lt;br /&gt;
We lave also greatly increased responsibility to shoulder in relation&lt;br /&gt;
to other people, and particularly to those with whom we are associated&lt;br /&gt;
aI a Pacific power. The whole field of Pacific studies awaits fuller development&lt;br /&gt;
than it has previously received in Australia. Our relations with the&lt;br /&gt;
East, with the Americas, with the East Indies, New Zealand, New Guinea&lt;br /&gt;
, ad all the Pacific islands, must be carefully studied so that they may&lt;br /&gt;
l,' come friondly and fruitful if our future is to be safeguarded and if we&lt;br /&gt;
to make our full contri! bution in the councils of the nations. Here,&lt;br /&gt;
iur opportunities are unique. Our remoteness enables us to consider the&lt;br /&gt;
fundamental issues involved, free from the day to day fears and turmoil&lt;br /&gt;
tliht beset, many of the great Powers. For that reason we have a duty&lt;br /&gt;
to the world at large which we must recognize if we are to be accepted as&lt;br /&gt;
a world Power.&lt;br /&gt;
The Iill is very straightforward and needs little amplification. It&lt;br /&gt;
follows in broad outline the general plan of government which operates&lt;br /&gt;
successfully in other universities, both in Australia and overseas. It will&lt;br /&gt;
be noted that the functions of the university lay particular stress on postgraduate&lt;br /&gt;
research and the research schools of immediate importance to&lt;br /&gt;
Australia are set out, but nothing in the bill prevents the establishment&lt;br /&gt;
of other research schools that may appear essential to the governing body&lt;br /&gt;
f the university. It is recognized that facilities must be made available&lt;br /&gt;
in Canberra to meet the increasing needs for undergraduate studies anud&lt;br /&gt;
for special training for officers of government departments and provision&lt;br /&gt;
is made to enablb this to be done.&lt;br /&gt;
The governing authority of the university is to be council consisting&lt;br /&gt;
of not more than 30 members and to be composed partly of elected members&lt;br /&gt;
and partly of members appointed by the Govcrnor-General and by the &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parliament. The university must be free to administer its own affairs&lt;br /&gt;
without any pressure from outside, otherwise decisions on highly complex&lt;br /&gt;
technical matters may be taken which are not in the best interests of the&lt;br /&gt;
university, and which may prevent it from carrying out its work efficiently.&lt;br /&gt;
The appropriate safeguards against such outside interference are contained&lt;br /&gt;
in the bill which specifically refers all matters connected with the&lt;br /&gt;
government of the university to the council.&lt;br /&gt;
" I do not anticipate that the university will be in full operation for&lt;br /&gt;
some time, but it is essential that as much basic planning as possible be&lt;br /&gt;
completed so that the necessary plans can be laid for buildings and other&lt;br /&gt;
essential work. The acute shortage of labour and materials for building&lt;br /&gt;
will prevent an immediate start being made on any accommodation for the&lt;br /&gt;
university. I propose that the bill be amended to permit the appointment&lt;br /&gt;
of an interim council to carry out the work of the council until that body&lt;br /&gt;
can be properly constituted and appointed, and in particular to undertake&lt;br /&gt;
the preliminary work relating to the planning of the university.&lt;br /&gt;
The Government is concerned that the university should be able to&lt;br /&gt;
plan ahead, particularly cn its research side, and I propose to provide the&lt;br /&gt;
university with a grant which will be reviewed every five years rather than&lt;br /&gt;
to leave it dependent on the funds voted annually by Parliament. The&lt;br /&gt;
Government proposes to make available in the first five years, commencing&lt;br /&gt;
with the financial year 1951-52, the sum of &#339; 325,000 a year. The amount&lt;br /&gt;
will be reviewed every five years thereafter. In the period before July,&lt;br /&gt;
1951, such amount will be made available, to a maximum of &#339; 325,000 a&lt;br /&gt;
year, as is actually needed to meet running expenses. The Government&lt;br /&gt;
will provide sufficient funds to enable the university to start with buildings&lt;br /&gt;
worthy of the objects for which they are built and in keeping with the best&lt;br /&gt;
types of architecture in the Capital Territory. Accordingly the Government&lt;br /&gt;
has approved &#339; 872,500 for buildings for the university. This amount&lt;br /&gt;
will not be required immediately, nor will it be drawn from any one budget.&lt;br /&gt;
The vice-chancellor, as the administrative head of the university,&lt;br /&gt;
will be, in many ways, the key member of its staff. In the first instance,&lt;br /&gt;
it is proposed that the vice-chancellor be appointed by the Governor-&lt;br /&gt;
General for five years. All subsequent appointments to that office will&lt;br /&gt;
be made by the council. It is vital that the vice-chancellor be a man of&lt;br /&gt;
outstanding administrative ability, and, if possible, of high academic&lt;br /&gt;
standing. I believe that he must at all costs secure men of world reputation&lt;br /&gt;
to supervise the work of the various research schools." [ The bill was passed.]&lt;br /&gt;
COAL-MINING INDUSTRY.&lt;br /&gt;
CONTROL-COAL CLIFF COLLIERY.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 20th June, 1946, the Minister for Supply ( Senator&lt;br /&gt;
Ashley) said that losses in the operation of Coal Cliff colliery by the Commonwealtb&lt;br /&gt;
had been-&lt;br /&gt;
Year ended March, 1945, &#339; 28,350; year ended March, 1946, &#339; 27,652. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LITERARY CENSORSHIP BOARD.&lt;br /&gt;
MEMBERS RE-APPOINTED.&lt;br /&gt;
On 20th June, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) announced that&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. L. H. Allen ( chairman), Prof. J. F. M. Haydon and Mr. K. Binns had&lt;br /&gt;
been re-appointed members of the Literature Censorship Board for three&lt;br /&gt;
years from 25th June, 1946. Sir Robert Garran had been re-appointed&lt;br /&gt;
Appeal Censor for the same period from the same date.&lt;br /&gt;
DEFENCE.&lt;br /&gt;
POST-WAR-RIFLE CLUBS.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parlirmeni.-On 20th June, 1946, the Minister for the Army ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
Forde) said--&lt;br /&gt;
The Government has authorized the re-establishment of rifle clubs as&lt;br /&gt;
from 1st July, 1946. The departmental organization for the administration&lt;br /&gt;
of the rifle club movement will be on the lines in force before 1931, when&lt;br /&gt;
the rifle clubs were a civil movement under the Department of Defence.&lt;br /&gt;
POST-WAR-BRITISH COMMONWEALTH CONFERENCE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 27th June, 1946, the acting Minister for Defence ( Mr. Forde)&lt;br /&gt;
announced that Lieutenant-Generals S. F. Rowell, C. A. Clowes and F. H.&lt;br /&gt;
Berrvnan, and Brigadier R. King would attend a defence conference of the&lt;br /&gt;
commanders-in-chief of all British army commands at home and overseas&lt;br /&gt;
and of representatives of the Dominions in Britain in August, 1946.&lt;br /&gt;
WOOL.&lt;br /&gt;
MANUFACTURES-SUBSIDY.&lt;br /&gt;
On 20th June, 1946, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Fraser) announced&lt;br /&gt;
that subsidy would be paid to maintain existing prices of wool to Australian&lt;br /&gt;
manufacturers for utilization in goods for domestic consumption, when&lt;br /&gt;
auction sales recommenced after 30th June, 1946. The purpose of the&lt;br /&gt;
subsidy was to enable Australian manufacturers to compete with overseas&lt;br /&gt;
buyers in a manner that will avoid interference with normal auction purchases.&lt;br /&gt;
Subsidies would be paid to manufacturers to re-imburse any excess&lt;br /&gt;
paid in purchasing at prices for domestic consumption but not in excess&lt;br /&gt;
of the average market level for individual wool types at a series of auction&lt;br /&gt;
sales. That ensured that manufacturers would not bid extravagantly on&lt;br /&gt;
the assumption that the Conunmmonwealth Government would meet deficiencies&lt;br /&gt;
resulting from unlimited bidding.&lt;br /&gt;
WHEAT STABILIZATION SCHEME.&lt;br /&gt;
POST-WAR-BILL INTRODUCED.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 20th June, 1946, the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
Scully) introduced the Wheat Industry Stabilization Bill. Mr. Scully&lt;br /&gt;
said-Wheat has been a troubled industry for many years. For a decade&lt;br /&gt;
before the war, it was frequently in a depressed condition and constant&lt;br /&gt;
assistance from governments was. required. Prices were low and growers &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;could not obtain a reasonable living from their labour. Other wheatproducing&lt;br /&gt;
countries were in a similar plight, and wheat presented the&lt;br /&gt;
world's greatest agricultural problem. The need for stabilization in Australia&lt;br /&gt;
was recognized, but it is beyond the power of any Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
Iovernment to stabilize the industry. Joint action by all Australian&lt;br /&gt;
governments is necessary, because both States and Commonwealth are&lt;br /&gt;
vitally affected by matters concerning the wheat inditstry. Although the&lt;br /&gt;
prcblem is old, to date it has not been possible to get agreement on a plan,&lt;br /&gt;
and the method of operating it.&lt;br /&gt;
The bill is intended to give security to the wheat industry in Australia.&lt;br /&gt;
It provides growers with a guaranteed minimum price for wheat for five&lt;br /&gt;
years, and has the machinery to maintain minimum price guarantees as a&lt;br /&gt;
permanent feature. The effect will be to remove the feature which disturbed&lt;br /&gt;
the industry most in the past; that is, the impact of unduly low&lt;br /&gt;
prices. It will be replaced by a system under which wheat farmers will&lt;br /&gt;
know, for a period of years in advance, that they will receive a definite&lt;br /&gt;
price for their wheat. They can plan their farm programme with an assured&lt;br /&gt;
return, and with the knowldge that they will not be ruined by market&lt;br /&gt;
changes which cannot be foreseen or controlled. The stabilization proposals&lt;br /&gt;
represent the considered judgment of governments and growers, first, as to&lt;br /&gt;
the measures needed for tlh industry, and, second, as to the best way to&lt;br /&gt;
effect them. Co-operation with the States is an essential part of the plan.&lt;br /&gt;
The States control production, and production must be regulated according&lt;br /&gt;
to the markets available for our wheat. In marketing, Commonwealth and&lt;br /&gt;
States must use their constitutional powers in harmony if the plan is to be&lt;br /&gt;
effective; neither can provide effective marketing unaided. In the plan&lt;br /&gt;
now proposed. the States have shown their willingness to co-operate with&lt;br /&gt;
the Commonwealth. It has been discussed in detail with State Gove lnmn.-&lt;br /&gt;
its, and they have agreed to bring complementary legislation befdre&lt;br /&gt;
their parliaments. The Government has consulted wheat-growers' organizations.&lt;br /&gt;
The' plan was discussed with the Wheat Growers' Federation in&lt;br /&gt;
December, 1945, and growers' views on its details were then expounded&lt;br /&gt;
fully. The various points stressed received consideration and it has been&lt;br /&gt;
possible to meet them in full. The bill represents the greatest practicable&lt;br /&gt;
measure of co-operation between governments and growers to settle the&lt;br /&gt;
problem of the wheat industry.&lt;br /&gt;
The plan provides a miinimum guaranteed price for wheat for the&lt;br /&gt;
period 1945-46 to 1949-50. It provides for review during the currency&lt;br /&gt;
of the scheme, with a view to its extension beyond the five years. Growers&lt;br /&gt;
will contribute to ai stabilization fund, when prices are high, and the&lt;br /&gt;
contribution will be not more than 50 per cent. of the excess of the export&lt;br /&gt;
price above the guaranteed minimum price. The Commonwealth will&lt;br /&gt;
meet any deficiency in any one year should the stabilization fund become&lt;br /&gt;
exhausted. A central marketing organization will be responsible for the&lt;br /&gt;
marketing of the Australian wheat crop, and production will be regulated&lt;br /&gt;
in accordance with thl markets available. The guaranteed price for the&lt;br /&gt;
seasons 1945-46 to 19,19-50, is 5s. 2d. a bushel f. o. r. ports for f. a. q. bagged&lt;br /&gt;
wheat. This miinimum will apply to the whole of the marketed crops. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, a home-consumption price applies to wheat used locally for&lt;br /&gt;
flour. This will be extended to cover other wheat used locally. There is;&lt;br /&gt;
in addition, the very important point of the guarantee for export wheat.&lt;br /&gt;
Control over local wheat prices is always possible, but the grower will now&lt;br /&gt;
get protection against slumps which have been a regular feature of world&lt;br /&gt;
markets, and the Commonwealth will take a financial risk to give that&lt;br /&gt;
protection. It is intended that the guaranteed price will apply for five&lt;br /&gt;
seasons, but, . before the period is up, the plan will be reviewed, and a fresh&lt;br /&gt;
guarantee given for a further period. The intention is to have regular&lt;br /&gt;
reviews, and to maintain always a guaranteed price for some seasons ahead.&lt;br /&gt;
The first period has been fixed as a reasonable period of security and a&lt;br /&gt;
reasonable period for a fixed commitment. The guaranteed price is the&lt;br /&gt;
minimum return, and growers will get more when export prices are high.&lt;br /&gt;
They are given a definite floor price.&lt;br /&gt;
A contribution from growers is provided for. It is considered that,&lt;br /&gt;
in principle, a government guarantee, which is really a guarantee from the&lt;br /&gt;
taxpayer should be accompanied by contributions from growers when&lt;br /&gt;
prices are high. This principle is accepted by growers and a 50-50 contribution&lt;br /&gt;
is generally conceded to be fair. When prices are high, growers will&lt;br /&gt;
contribute up to 50 per cent. of the excess above the guaranteed price of&lt;br /&gt;
export wlheat. The money so subscribed will go into a stabilization fund,&lt;br /&gt;
and will be used to meet the guarantee when prices fall. The fund will&lt;br /&gt;
be a trust fund. There is no intention of building up an excessively large&lt;br /&gt;
fund, and, if prices remain higher than is now expected, the contribution&lt;br /&gt;
will be reduced below 50 per cent. The effect is that growers will make a&lt;br /&gt;
reasonable but not an excessive contribution, and the Commonwealth will&lt;br /&gt;
meet the guarantee if a run of low prices exhausts the fund. This means&lt;br /&gt;
that growers will share in the extra amounts from high price years, and are&lt;br /&gt;
assured in advance against a price below 5s. 21.&lt;br /&gt;
It is not proposed, that returns shall be permanently out of line with&lt;br /&gt;
the export price, nor that the industry will be continually subsidized. Twothirds&lt;br /&gt;
of our wheat goes on to the export market, and we must compete&lt;br /&gt;
with other countries for our markets. The plan gives time for adjustments&lt;br /&gt;
to meet changing world conditions, and it protects growers against a rapid&lt;br /&gt;
fall on the export market. It cannot relieve them of the need to meet&lt;br /&gt;
world competition in the export trade. It is hoped, however, that an&lt;br /&gt;
effective internatiolal agreement will protect . export markets in future.&lt;br /&gt;
For the next five years, come what may in the export field, growers are&lt;br /&gt;
guaranteed against the effect of a world slump. They will not receive in&lt;br /&gt;
any one of the five years less than 5s. 2d.&lt;br /&gt;
The difficulties of making a guarantee effective can hardly be overcome&lt;br /&gt;
without a central organization for marketing. A wheat board will be set&lt;br /&gt;
up to handle and sell the crops with the benefits of war-time experience&lt;br /&gt;
and of an efficient organization. The board will succeed the war-time Wheat&lt;br /&gt;
Board and carry on its -work. In its new set-up it will operate under joint&lt;br /&gt;
powers conferred by Commonwealth and States, and the statutory power&lt;br /&gt;
to operate will relate almost entirely to wheat covered by the State acts.&lt;br /&gt;
Regulation of production is a part of the plan in which action would&lt;br /&gt;
be impossible without full State co-operation. The long history of wheat &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;gluts and wheat shortages has shown how easy it is to go from one extreme&lt;br /&gt;
to the other. Wheat gluts build up fast, and the low prices which result&lt;br /&gt;
have had a disastrous effect in past years on wheat farmers here and overseas.&lt;br /&gt;
Over-production must be avoided in the future. We wish to produce all&lt;br /&gt;
the wheat we reasonably can, and to sell it at a price fair to growers and&lt;br /&gt;
consumers. We want to avoid temporary high-price expansion in the&lt;br /&gt;
industry which would leave it over-capitalized and unable to carry on when&lt;br /&gt;
prices recede. Deliberate regulation according to markets available is a&lt;br /&gt;
new departure, but it offers the best prospect for avoiding a return to the&lt;br /&gt;
disastrous see-saw from glut to scarcity. It may seem odd at present to&lt;br /&gt;
be thinking of regulating wheat production. Australia is now trying to&lt;br /&gt;
produce the maximum crop and to supply everything possible to meet overseas&lt;br /&gt;
needs. But we must prepare for whatever may come in the future,&lt;br /&gt;
and it is likely that, within a short time, a wheat glut may recur. If it&lt;br /&gt;
does, farmers will again be faced with depression, and precautions against&lt;br /&gt;
that must be taken now.&lt;br /&gt;
Normal pre-war basis of production can be maintained and it will be&lt;br /&gt;
practicable to include in the industry soldier settlers and farmers' sons.&lt;br /&gt;
I hope that conditions of world trade in the years to come will give an&lt;br /&gt;
outlet for all the wheat which Australia can produce. If so, there will be&lt;br /&gt;
room for expansion to the limit of economic productive capacity. It must,&lt;br /&gt;
however, be realized that farmers cannot go into the wheat industry one&lt;br /&gt;
season, and out of it the next. Once in it, they are committed to heavy&lt;br /&gt;
outlay and years of production. Boom years are a menace because of the&lt;br /&gt;
danger of high land prices and over-capitalized farms, leading to a financial&lt;br /&gt;
structure which is not able to meet low or medium price years. For that&lt;br /&gt;
reason, the production basis must be decided with the greatest care. The&lt;br /&gt;
plan is intended to make the wheat industry sound financially. Regublltion&lt;br /&gt;
Sof production-not restriction of production-has been recognized over&lt;br /&gt;
the years us one requisite for any plan. That is recognized not only by&lt;br /&gt;
governmnts but by the growers; and growers are willing to co-operate&lt;br /&gt;
in regulation of the industry to secure the wide benefits of stabilization.&lt;br /&gt;
Regulation of production was brought in as a war-time measure, and now&lt;br /&gt;
can readily be adapted to peace-time needs. It is a State function, and&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth and States will co-operate to secure uniformity in administration.&lt;br /&gt;
There aire two Commoniwealth bills, and complementary legislation&lt;br /&gt;
will be necessary in each State. It is considered the State legislation can&lt;br /&gt;
be covered by one act, and one object of the discussions was to secure&lt;br /&gt;
uniformity among the States. The Wheat Industry Stabilization Bill&lt;br /&gt;
provides the mechanism for carrying out the plan I have outlined, and for&lt;br /&gt;
co-operating with the States in all necessary matters. The Wheat Export&lt;br /&gt;
Charge Bill completes the work by providing for the charge which forms the&lt;br /&gt;
Urowers' contribution to the hill. Difficult problems will be met in administration.&lt;br /&gt;
I am confident that they will be overcome by the partnership of&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth and States.&lt;br /&gt;
The Wheat Charges Bill, to be introduced later, provides for a maximum&lt;br /&gt;
contribution of 50 per cent., or a lower rate if prescribed, of the difference&lt;br /&gt;
between the guaranteed price of 5s. 2d. and the average export price in &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;; any one year or such part of the export price as is prescribed. It is proposed&lt;br /&gt;
for the 1945--46 crop, that the contribution be 50 per cent. of the difference&lt;br /&gt;
between 5s. 2d. and 9s. 6d. bagged. The average export return isestimated&lt;br /&gt;
to be ] 0s. Growers will be paid from the pool on the following basis:-&lt;br /&gt;
2d. a bushel for domestically consumed wheat, and for export wheat&lt;br /&gt;
2d. a bushel plus 50 per cent. of the difference between 5s. 2d., the guaranteed&lt;br /&gt;
price, and 9s. 6d.-which is 2s. 2d. and a further 6d. on export&lt;br /&gt;
wheat, this being the difference between 10s. and 9s. 6d. It is estimated&lt;br /&gt;
that, for the whole of the wheat marketed local and export, the grower will&lt;br /&gt;
receive 6s. 7d. a bushel f. o. r. at ports bagged.&lt;br /&gt;
Summarized, the two bills provide-&lt;br /&gt;
The preservation over five years of a price of 5s. 2d. a bushel f. o. r. at ports. bagged&lt;br /&gt;
for all wheat consumed within Australia.&lt;br /&gt;
A guarantee by the Government of a minimum price for export of 5s. 2d. a bushel&lt;br /&gt;
f. o. r. at ports bagged.&lt;br /&gt;
When the export price exceeds the guaranteed price, growers to contribute to a&lt;br /&gt;
fund to an amount not exceeding 50 per cent. of the difference between the export price&lt;br /&gt;
and the guaranteed price of 5s. 2d.&lt;br /&gt;
When the export price falls below 5s. 2d., the fund will be called upon to provide&lt;br /&gt;
the amount necessary to bring the export price up to 5s. 2d.&lt;br /&gt;
If and when the fund is exhausted in any one year, the Government under its&lt;br /&gt;
guarantee will provide, out of general revenue, the funds necessary to bring export prices&lt;br /&gt;
up to 5s. 2d.&lt;br /&gt;
For the 1945-46 crop, the Government proposes that the grower will be paid on&lt;br /&gt;
export wheat 5s. 2d., plus 2s. 2d., plus the excess of export returns over 9s. 6d. Under&lt;br /&gt;
this arrangement, it is calculated that, for the whole of his sales, export and local, the&lt;br /&gt;
grower will receive 6s. 7d. a bushel f. o. r. at ports bagged.&lt;br /&gt;
The scheme, including the guarantee, is to operate for five years. During its&lt;br /&gt;
: urrency, however, reviews will be made with a view to continuing it under conditions&lt;br /&gt;
which may or may not be revised, beyond five years.&lt;br /&gt;
The plan is designed to provide for stabilized returns over a period of years. Funds&lt;br /&gt;
will be held on account of growers in years of high prices and paid out in years of low&lt;br /&gt;
prices. But the Government underwrites the scheme to the extent of guaranteeing&lt;br /&gt;
that, whatever be the rise or fall of the market over five years, the farmer will get a&lt;br /&gt;
return not less than 5s. 2d. a bushel f. o. r. bagged at ports. [ The bill was passed.]&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 108, p. 44; 110, p.&lt;br /&gt;
EXTERNAL COMMUNICATIONS.&lt;br /&gt;
FUTURE POLICY-TELECOMMUNICATIONS, BILL INTRODUCED.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 20th June, 1946, the Minister for Information&lt;br /&gt;
( Mr. Calwell) introduced the Overseas Telecommunications Bill. Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
Calwell said-&lt;br /&gt;
This bill deals with the transfer to national ownership of the external&lt;br /&gt;
telecommunication services now owned and operated by Amalgamated&lt;br /&gt;
Wireless ( Australasia) Limited and the establishment of a statutory&lt;br /&gt;
corporation to operate both radio and cable services linking Australia with&lt;br /&gt;
other countries. This bill is one of similar pieces of legislation which will&lt;br /&gt;
be enacted by the parliaments of all self-governing countries in the British&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth and Empire. The step being taken in Australia is part&lt;br /&gt;
of a unified plan. recommended by the British Commonwealth Telecominunications&lt;br /&gt;
Conference in July and August, 1945. The conference reached&lt;br /&gt;
the unanimous conclusion that, to secure the desired strengthening and &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;better ordering of the British Commonwealth telecommunications system,&lt;br /&gt;
a fundamental change in the present organization was necessary. The&lt;br /&gt;
conference recommended-&lt;br /&gt;
That the private shareholder interest in the ownership of overseas telecommunication&lt;br /&gt;
services of Britain, the Dominions and India should be replaced by public ownership.&lt;br /&gt;
That the government in each country should acquire the ownership of the telecom.&lt;br /&gt;
munication assets in its territories.&lt;br /&gt;
That the type of organization established in each country to own and operate the&lt;br /&gt;
external telecommunication services should as far as possible be uniform.&lt;br /&gt;
That a Commonwealth Telecommunication Board be established to replace the&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth Communications Council, with functions mainly advisory in character.&lt;br /&gt;
but extending to all the national organizations throughout the Empire instead of being&lt;br /&gt;
related only to the London organization as under present conditions.&lt;br /&gt;
The conference also worked out a system of pooling of net revenues.&lt;br /&gt;
in a central fund, from which out-payments for the maintenance of the&lt;br /&gt;
board and the maintenance of the submrine cables could be met, after&lt;br /&gt;
which the residues would be returned to the respective national bodies.&lt;br /&gt;
Legislation to give effect to the recommendations of the conference&lt;br /&gt;
has been introduced in the British House of Commons and provides for the&lt;br /&gt;
acquisition of the shares of Cable and Wireless Limited, apart from the&lt;br /&gt;
2,600,000 shares which it already owns, : nd the payment of compensation&lt;br /&gt;
to the shareholders. Another bill is to be introduced later for the establishment&lt;br /&gt;
of the Commonwealth Telecommunications Board and for the carrying&lt;br /&gt;
into effect of the full scheme recommended by the 1945 conference.&lt;br /&gt;
The bill before this House provides for the full implementation of the&lt;br /&gt;
recommendations of the conference and the ratification of an overall agreement&lt;br /&gt;
in the form set out in the first schedule to the bill. The bill provides&lt;br /&gt;
for the establishment in Australia of a government commission as a&lt;br /&gt;
corporate body, to acquire the ownership of and to maintain and operate&lt;br /&gt;
the overseas telecommunication services at present conducted by Amalgamated&lt;br /&gt;
Wireless ( Australasia) Limited and by Cable and Wireless Limited&lt;br /&gt;
in the -territories of the Commonwealth of Australia. The commission will&lt;br /&gt;
be called the Overseas Telecommunications Commission ( Australia).&lt;br /&gt;
Provision is made for the assessment of the compensation which will he&lt;br /&gt;
payable to Amalgamated Wireless ( Australasia) Limited. The bill provides&lt;br /&gt;
that the amount may be determined by agreement between the commission&lt;br /&gt;
and the company. In the event of agreement not being reached, the&lt;br /&gt;
amount may be determined by a compensation board. If either party is&lt;br /&gt;
dissatisfied with the amount of compensation determined by the board,&lt;br /&gt;
an appeal may be made to the High Court. The assets of Cable and Wireless&lt;br /&gt;
Limited to be taken over by the commission will be transferred by the&lt;br /&gt;
British Govermnent to the commission at an agreed price to be paid in cash&lt;br /&gt;
Employees of the two companies who have been exclusively employed&lt;br /&gt;
by them on telecommunications in Australia for three years or over, and&lt;br /&gt;
for whom suitable employment can be found by the commission, will become&lt;br /&gt;
entitled to appointment to positions in the service of the commission, with&lt;br /&gt;
preservation of their accrued pension, superannuation, furlough and other&lt;br /&gt;
rights. If it is not found possible to re-engage all the employees affected.&lt;br /&gt;
it is proposed to come to an arrangement with the companies so that the&lt;br /&gt;
employees affected will not be placed at a disadvantage. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commission will acquire, operate and maintain all the overseas&lt;br /&gt;
telecommunication services hitherto owned and operated in Australia by&lt;br /&gt;
Cable and Wireless Limited and Amalgamated Wireless ( Australasia)&lt;br /&gt;
Limited, including in the latter case the operation of coastal and island&lt;br /&gt;
radio stations which handle wireless traffic with ships at sea and similar&lt;br /&gt;
traffic exchanged within and between territories of the Commonwealth.&lt;br /&gt;
The national corporations throughout the Empire will undertake research&lt;br /&gt;
: tad developmental work to improve the efficiency of services. This work&lt;br /&gt;
will be co-ordinated by the Commonwealth Telecommunications Board in&lt;br /&gt;
London, and that board will also undertake research work on behalf of all&lt;br /&gt;
partner governments. It is contemplated that the commission shall, if&lt;br /&gt;
so desired by another national body, undertake to act as agent on agreed&lt;br /&gt;
terms in maintaining and operating overseas telecommunication services in&lt;br /&gt;
regional areas adjacent to Australia.&lt;br /&gt;
Power is conferred on the Miiister to approve of any contracts where&lt;br /&gt;
-upply, either directly or indirectly, of imported equipment or material&lt;br /&gt;
of a value exceeding &#339; 5,000 is involved. This provision will ensure that&lt;br /&gt;
lue consideration is given by the commission to the use of equipment manuf1ctured&lt;br /&gt;
in Australia before steps are taken to import material of any&lt;br /&gt;
ippreciable value from abroad. The powers conferred on the commission&lt;br /&gt;
io not detract in any way from those entrusted to the Minister administering&lt;br /&gt;
the Wireless Telegrapliy and the Post and Telegraph Acts.&lt;br /&gt;
Conditions under which advances will be made to the commission shall&lt;br /&gt;
be determined by the Treasurer. The form in which the commission will&lt;br /&gt;
keep its accounts will be subject to the approval of the Treasurer and to&lt;br /&gt;
inspection and audit by the Auditor-General. Annual reports and financial&lt;br /&gt;
statements of the commission, accompanied by a certificate of the Auditor-&lt;br /&gt;
(' cncral. will be submitted to Parliament.&lt;br /&gt;
The c-inmluission will arrange free handling of meteorological telegrams&lt;br /&gt;
exchanged with ships at sea and of similar messages exchanged between&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth meteorological offices and stations. The commission will&lt;br /&gt;
handle free on behalf of the Post Office other telegrams for transmission&lt;br /&gt;
within the Commonwealth in cases cf interruption to land-lines, in return&lt;br /&gt;
for which the Post Office will arrange free transmission of messages relating&lt;br /&gt;
to the commission's administrative affairs.&lt;br /&gt;
The duties and functions of the Commonwealth Telecommunications&lt;br /&gt;
Board are set out in detail in the overall agreement which becomes a part&lt;br /&gt;
of the bill. The costs of the board are to be met in agreed proportions&lt;br /&gt;
from the net revenues of the several national bodies.&lt;br /&gt;
In the overall agreement, a form of tripartite agreement is drawn up&lt;br /&gt;
for execution in due course by each partner government concerned, the&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth Telecommunications Board and the local national telecommunications&lt;br /&gt;
body. This tripartite agreement defines the relationship&lt;br /&gt;
which will exist between the several parties thereto and, in particular, to&lt;br /&gt;
mutual responsibilities of the local national body and the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
Telecommunications Board. It provides for the establishment of a central&lt;br /&gt;
fund into which the national bodies will pay annually their net revenues. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;" Of the subscribed capital in Amalgamated Wireless ( Australasia)&lt;br /&gt;
Limited, amounting to &#339; 985,518, the Government owns 500,001 fully paid&lt;br /&gt;
shares and private interests 485,517 shares. Under the agreements to which&lt;br /&gt;
I have referred the measure of control exercisable by the Government is&lt;br /&gt;
incommensurate with its majority shareholding. The agreements are so&lt;br /&gt;
greatly in favour of the company that, apart from approval or veto of'&lt;br /&gt;
tariffs and the granting or withholding of licences for new services and--&lt;br /&gt;
even this later right by the Government has been denied by the company-.&lt;br /&gt;
the Government has virtually little or no control at all over the policy of th,&lt;br /&gt;
company. Government representation on the Board of Directors is limited&lt;br /&gt;
to three out of a total of seven directors constituting the board. Effective&lt;br /&gt;
co-ordination and control of overseas telecommunication services in&lt;br /&gt;
Australia in the national interest is impracticable of realization so long as&lt;br /&gt;
two separate companies own and operate the two respective means of&lt;br /&gt;
overseas communication, cable and radio. The transfer of the services of'&lt;br /&gt;
both companies to the Government will enable their complete co-ordination&lt;br /&gt;
under a single operating authority, and will ultimately enable cheaper rates&lt;br /&gt;
to be offered to the users of the services through the avoidance of existing&lt;br /&gt;
duplication of effort and of overhead costs resulting from the conduct of&lt;br /&gt;
the respective services by two separate undertakings. The acquisition by&lt;br /&gt;
the Government of the telecommunication assets of Amalgamated Wireless&lt;br /&gt;
( Australasia) Limited will involve a reconstitution of the company to enable&lt;br /&gt;
it to continue as a manufacturing, commercial broadcasting and patentholding&lt;br /&gt;
sales and servicing organization. The Government proposes to&lt;br /&gt;
retain its proportionate shareholding in the reconstituted company, if the&lt;br /&gt;
private shareholders of Amalgamated Wireless ( Australasia) Limited so&lt;br /&gt;
desire. Provision for this would not be appropriate in this bill, and&lt;br /&gt;
suitable steps towards this end will be taken later, if necessary."&lt;br /&gt;
[ The bill was passed.]&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 93, p. 80; 105, p. 26; 108, p. 27.)&lt;br /&gt;
AIRMAIL TO NETHERLANDS EAST INDIES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 8th July, 1946, the Postmaster-General ( Senator Cameron)&lt;br /&gt;
announced that airmail facilities had been resumed between Australia&lt;br /&gt;
and the Netherlands East Indies.&lt;br /&gt;
REVIEW OF RENTS.&lt;br /&gt;
REGULATIONS-OPERATION REVIEWED.&lt;br /&gt;
On 22nd June, 1946, the Minister for Housing ( Mr. Lazzarini) said that,&lt;br /&gt;
because of National Security ( Landlord and Tenant) Regulations, there&lt;br /&gt;
had been an overall rental reduction of 14.4 per cent. in shared accommodation&lt;br /&gt;
cases determined since the deputy rent controllers commenced operations&lt;br /&gt;
in October, 1945. A summary of determinations of rents of shared &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;accommodation for the quarters ended 31.4t December, 1945, and 31st&lt;br /&gt;
March, 1946, was-Number of Deter-Rent Rtent Rent&lt;br /&gt;
mnatione iadc. Decreased. Unchanged. Increased.&lt;br /&gt;
Dec. Afar. Dec Mar Dec. War. Dec. Mar.&lt;br /&gt;
Qtr. Qtr. Qr. Qtr. Qtr. Qtr. Qtr. Qtr.&lt;br /&gt;
New South Wales 952 1,947 548 1,211 219 397 185 339&lt;br /&gt;
Victoria.. 612 1,560 -394 1,051 193 418 25 91&lt;br /&gt;
Queensland 366 416 274 242 56 113 36 61&lt;br /&gt;
Tasmania 42 61 17 26 24 33 1 2&lt;br /&gt;
Total 1,972 3,984 1,233 2,530 492 961 247 493&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier reference, please see No. 111, p. 13.)&lt;br /&gt;
WOOL AGREEMENT.&lt;br /&gt;
NEW AGREEMENT-JOINT ORGANIZATION, FIRST MEETING..&lt;br /&gt;
On 23rd June, 1.946, the Prime Miniister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
" The first meetings of the Dominion and British directors of United&lt;br /&gt;
Kingdom-Dominion Wool Disposals Limited have been held in London.&lt;br /&gt;
The company has been entrusted by the Governments of Britain, Australia,&lt;br /&gt;
New Zealand and South Africa with the double task of effecting orderl * y&lt;br /&gt;
disposal of accumulated war-time surpluses of wool and at the same tim' 4&lt;br /&gt;
maintaining anl appropriate degree of stability in prices.&lt;br /&gt;
It will attempt to achieve the first objective by offerinc, at auctionl&lt;br /&gt;
its stocks of wool alongside current clips in accordance with supply and&lt;br /&gt;
demand in the world's markets and to achieve the second objective by&lt;br /&gt;
regulation of offerings and by means of reserve ' prices at which it will be&lt;br /&gt;
prepared to buy in growers' wool at auction. It will, at all times, endeavour&lt;br /&gt;
to act impartially towards tbe interests of the various parts affected or&lt;br /&gt;
likely to be affected by its decisions and the company makes the following&lt;br /&gt;
preliminary announcement:&lt;br /&gt;
His Majesty's Governments in Britain, Australia, New Zealand&lt;br /&gt;
and South Africa have considered the recommendation made by tho&lt;br /&gt;
Joint Organization pursuant to the terms of paragraph 6 of the Wool&lt;br /&gt;
Disposals Plan and have decided that the initial general level of&lt;br /&gt;
reserve prices for DoiioDs' Wools sold in the Dominions shall be&lt;br /&gt;
the same as tbe present average selling price, ex store, in the&lt;br /&gt;
Dominion concerned. It is the intention that this inlitial level shall,&lt;br /&gt;
in the absence of circumstances at present quite unforeseen, be&lt;br /&gt;
maintained throughout the wool year 1946-47.&lt;br /&gt;
Individual reserve prices for the wool year 1946-47, apart fronm&lt;br /&gt;
exceptional cases, will not be changed throughout the year.&lt;br /&gt;
The sale of wool at fixed prices b or on behalf of, the Joint&lt;br /&gt;
Organization will cease on 30th June, 1946.&lt;br /&gt;
Orders agaiinst which allocation of wool has no~ t been made, oil&lt;br /&gt;
or before 30th June, 1946, will be cancelled. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sales by auction will commence in Australia at the beginning of&lt;br /&gt;
September, in South Africa at the beginning of September, in New&lt;br /&gt;
Zealand of crutchings and of old wool at the beginning of September&lt;br /&gt;
and of new wool in November, and in Britain in September. The&lt;br /&gt;
precise dates on which auctions will commence and details of the&lt;br /&gt;
selling programme will he announced later.&lt;br /&gt;
Details in broad technical descriptions of the stock estimated to be&lt;br /&gt;
held by the organization at 30th June, 1946, will be announced as soon as&lt;br /&gt;
possible." On 27th June, 1946, the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Scully) announced&lt;br /&gt;
that the Wool ( Contributory Charge) Assessment Act and the Wool&lt;br /&gt;
( Contributory Charge) Act, assented to on 11th October, 1945, as an&lt;br /&gt;
essential part of the plan for the stabilized marketing of accumulated stocks&lt;br /&gt;
of wool in conjunction with current clips, had been proclaimed to operate&lt;br /&gt;
as from 1st July, 1946.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 27th June, 1946, Mr. Scully said-&lt;br /&gt;
The agreement between the Governments of Britain; Australia, New&lt;br /&gt;
Zealand and South Africa for the disposal of accumulated stocks of wool&lt;br /&gt;
and of oncoming clips provided for decisions by the four Governments,&lt;br /&gt;
of a reserve price for the season, below which sales would not be made, and&lt;br /&gt;
for a contributory charge which would be struck in each country to meet&lt;br /&gt;
the industry's share of the cost of administration. The general reserve&lt;br /&gt;
price agreed upon is that price at which wool is at present being sold&lt;br /&gt;
ex store. For Australia, this is, on average, 18. l1 ( Aust.) a lb. The&lt;br /&gt;
contributory charge decided upon by the Comuonwealth Government is&lt;br /&gt;
per cent. of the value of the wool, which works out at .91d. ( Aust.) a lb.&lt;br /&gt;
average. The price of 18.15d. a lb., less the cnurributory charge of .91l., gives&lt;br /&gt;
a net average return of 17.24d. and this is 1.79d. ( Aust.) more than&lt;br /&gt;
the average price of 15.45d. ( Aust.) over the whole clip payable by Britain&lt;br /&gt;
under the war-time agreement. This must be considered very satisfactory&lt;br /&gt;
to growers, because it gives to them, in effect, an overall minimum&lt;br /&gt;
guaranteed return substantially greater than that received by them under&lt;br /&gt;
the war-time contract." WAR ARCHIVES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 25th June, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
In 1942, the then Prime Minister ( the late Mr. Curtin) formed a War&lt;br /&gt;
Archives Committee under the chairmanship of Dr. C. E. W. Bean, who&lt;br /&gt;
was historian of World War to investigate measures for the preservation&lt;br /&gt;
of Australian records and documents relating to World War II.&lt;br /&gt;
I have now approved of the scope of the committee being broadened&lt;br /&gt;
so that its functions include the preservation of all Conunonwealth records&lt;br /&gt;
and not only records relating to the war. The committee will be known&lt;br /&gt;
as the Commonwealth Archives Committee. Its functions will be to study&lt;br /&gt;
archival principles and practices and to submit recommendations for the&lt;br /&gt;
establishment, when circunistances permit, of a permanent archival system &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;23&lt;br /&gt;
for the Commonwealth. Pending the establishment of such system, it will&lt;br /&gt;
advise the Government on general questions of collection and preservation.&lt;br /&gt;
of records, for the collection or preservation of which adequate steps are&lt;br /&gt;
not being taken by a Commonwealth authority, and will formulate proposals&lt;br /&gt;
for the preservation of records and documents or Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
departments, and lay down broad principles to be observed by Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
departments and provisional archival authorities. The members of&lt;br /&gt;
the committee will be---&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Bean ( chairman), Messrs. H. S. Temby ( Prime Minister's Department).&lt;br /&gt;
P. Hasluck ( Department of External Affairs), J. G. B. Castieau ( Attorney-General's&lt;br /&gt;
Department), K. Binns ( Commonwealth Librarian), LL-Colonel J. L. Treloar ( Director.&lt;br /&gt;
Australian War Memorial), Mr. A. W. Bazley ( Assistant Director, Historical Records,&lt;br /&gt;
Australian War Memorial), and a representative of the Department of the Interior.&lt;br /&gt;
TEXTILE TRADE.&lt;br /&gt;
WOOLLEN TEXTILES--EXPORTS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 26th June, 19416, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Fraser) said&lt;br /&gt;
that export of woollen cloths related to all woollen and worsteds and&lt;br /&gt;
included shipments to Unrra as well as commercial exports. Of the&lt;br /&gt;
3,000,000 square yards exported during the current trade year, about&lt;br /&gt;
2,000,000 square yards of woollen piece goods went to Unrra, and a large&lt;br /&gt;
quantity of it was stock the trade was glad to dispose of as it was unsaleable&lt;br /&gt;
in Australia. The remaining 1,000,000 square yards of commercial exports&lt;br /&gt;
of woollen and worsted piece goods represented only 4 per cent. of the&lt;br /&gt;
total production of woollens and worsteds and included all types of woollen&lt;br /&gt;
cloth. Suitings exported represented only a small proportion as the&lt;br /&gt;
Governmeut -had established strict quotas for worsted exports. Apart&lt;br /&gt;
from a small quota to New Zealand, the only exports of worsteds were on&lt;br /&gt;
a token basis to maintain overseas markets.&lt;br /&gt;
BUDGET, 1945-46.&lt;br /&gt;
APPROPRIATION BILL-EXCESS REVENUE.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 26th June, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley)&lt;br /&gt;
introduced the Appropriation Bill. Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
The purpose of this bill is to obtain parliamentary appropriation for&lt;br /&gt;
the expenditure of an additional &#339; 20,000,000 of revenue for war purposes.&lt;br /&gt;
When the budget was presented in September, 1945, I estimated that total&lt;br /&gt;
revenue would be &#339; 374,000,000. The. budget was framed to provide an&lt;br /&gt;
appropriation from revenue for non-war items aggregating &#339; 166,000,000.&lt;br /&gt;
The balance of &#339; 208,000,000 was appropriated for war purposes.&lt;br /&gt;
It is now anticipated that some revenue items will exceed the estimate.&lt;br /&gt;
With the end of the war and the relaxation of controls, there has been a&lt;br /&gt;
marked buoyancy in customs and excise revenue, and indications are that&lt;br /&gt;
the estimate will he exceeded by &#339; 7,000,000. Increased sales of civilian&lt;br /&gt;
goods, mainly due to demobilization of the forces, may result in an increase&lt;br /&gt;
of sales tax revenue of &#339; 5,000,000. Income tax may yield an increased&lt;br /&gt;
amount of &#339; 5,000,000. Estate duty and s: ome other items of revenue will&lt;br /&gt;
show small increases. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is anticipated that non-war expenditure will be approximately the&lt;br /&gt;
same as the budget estimate. An accurate forecast of the total revenue&lt;br /&gt;
for 1945-16 is difficult, but the improvement will be from &#339; 15,000,000 to&lt;br /&gt;
&#339; 20,000,000. To permit this increase of revenue to be utilized to meet&lt;br /&gt;
war expenditure, it is necessary to provide an additional appropriation&lt;br /&gt;
of &#339; 20,000,000. The budget provided for total war expenditure of&lt;br /&gt;
&#339; 360,000,000. Owing mainly to the acceleration of demcbilization, this&lt;br /&gt;
estimate will be exceeded. The appropriation of &#339; 20,000,000 will enable&lt;br /&gt;
the actual improvement of revenue to be applied to war expenditure, thus&lt;br /&gt;
reducing the amount chargeable to loan." [ The bill was passed.]&lt;br /&gt;
IMPORTS.&lt;br /&gt;
CIGARETTE PAPERS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 26th June, 1946, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Fraser) announced&lt;br /&gt;
that, in view of the shortage of cigarette papers in Australia, licences would&lt;br /&gt;
be issued for the importation of reasonable quantities of cigarette papers.&lt;br /&gt;
BANKING CONTROL.&lt;br /&gt;
LEGISLATION-COMMONWEALTH BANK ACT, INDUSTRIAL&lt;br /&gt;
DEPARTMENT.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 26th June, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley)&lt;br /&gt;
said that to 20th March, 1946, applications to the Industrial Loan Department&lt;br /&gt;
of the Commonwealth Bank totalled 964. of which 782 had been dealt&lt;br /&gt;
with. Applications totalling 501 and involving &#339; 78, T738 had been granted.&lt;br /&gt;
ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE.&lt;br /&gt;
AWARDS FOR GALLANTRY.&lt;br /&gt;
On 26th June, 1943, the Governor-General announc.-d the filluwing&lt;br /&gt;
awards:-Commander of the Military Division of the Order of the British Empiire&lt;br /&gt;
Commodores A. M. Charlesworth, A. L. Walter., ( lcoupcaptain&lt;br /&gt;
A. M. Murdoch.&lt;br /&gt;
Distingished Service Order.-Group-captain D. W. Kingwell.&lt;br /&gt;
Oficer of the Military Division of the Order of the British Empire&lt;br /&gt;
Group Captains N. M. Heath, A. D. Charlton, Wing Commanders A. W.&lt;br /&gt;
Raymond, M. H. Meyers.&lt;br /&gt;
Member of the Military Dirision of the Order of the British EmPire&lt;br /&gt;
-Flight Lieutenants R. F. Parker, 0. C. Ripley.&lt;br /&gt;
Military Cross.--Flight Lieutenant N. M. Kater, Pilot Officer R. Stuart.&lt;br /&gt;
Br to the Distinguished Flying Cross.-Squadron Leaders B. E. Brown,&lt;br /&gt;
J. R. Kinninmont, N. T. Quinn, Flight Lieutenant F. R. Schaaf.&lt;br /&gt;
Distinguished Flying Cross.--Wing Commanders J. O. F. Burton,&lt;br /&gt;
C. H. C. Thompson, Squadron Leaders B. Todd, B. B. Watson, A. R. Emslie,&lt;br /&gt;
Flight Lieutenants G. S. Hodges, J. L. Macalister, A. G. Stuart, A. F. Tutt, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. P. Walters, J. Bell, J. G. B. Caimbeil, R. W. Crawlvord, P. Cuirtis,&lt;br /&gt;
E. E. Garside, B. Ciffin, D. H. Kellyv, W. J. Madigan. W. E. Miller, R.&lt;br /&gt;
McD. Muirhead, V. A. Ruile, E. L. Sly, A. B. Taylor, A. E. Thomson,&lt;br /&gt;
W. JTW. ilkinson, Ekving Officers J. C. Meacleier, 1. A. Pedersein, J. A. 1' rettv.&lt;br /&gt;
Air Force Oro.-Wing ConimandcrEl. V. Reao, Flight I~ e'utendlnts S. J.&lt;br /&gt;
Raie. Sladle, F. r1B. all, F. C. Chaney, W. R. Mlills, Flvinga Officers W.&lt;br /&gt;
Bridges, R. JTC. ar~ or, F. Weir.&lt;br /&gt;
British Empire Medil-Fight Sergeant R. C. Blut. Lleading Aircraft-,&lt;br /&gt;
mian C. H. Couper.&lt;br /&gt;
Onl 3rd July, 1946. the Goverinor-Genieial announced the award of tht;&lt;br /&gt;
British Empire Modal to Sergeant M. T. Goode.&lt;br /&gt;
RECONSTRUCTION.&lt;br /&gt;
SOLDIERS' SETTLEMENT-RE VIEW OF OPERATIONS.&lt;br /&gt;
Onl 26thT June, 1946, the Minister for Post-war Reconstruction ( Mr. Dedman)&lt;br /&gt;
said that statistics of progress in war service land settlement since the&lt;br /&gt;
Comm-onwealth Act xvtis assented to onl 11th October, 1945, to 18th Junie.&lt;br /&gt;
1946, were-Arems leferrd back IUn der ( Jou-Submisiozi&lt;br /&gt;
Approved, to State. sideratio ii. Withdrawn.&lt;br /&gt;
Acres. Acres. Acres. Acres.&lt;br /&gt;
New South Wales Western&lt;br /&gt;
Land Leases 329,799&lt;br /&gt;
New South Wales 302,167 115,584 46,458 24,267&lt;br /&gt;
New South Wales Group Settle.-&lt;br /&gt;
ment 803&lt;br /&gt;
Victoria 63,940 5,160&lt;br /&gt;
Queensland 414,991 1,313,194 230,281&lt;br /&gt;
South Australia 64,189 54,350 83,255&lt;br /&gt;
Western Australia 90,072 334 76,599&lt;br /&gt;
Tasmania 134,516 23,016&lt;br /&gt;
Total 1,400,477 10648 4,73 24,267&lt;br /&gt;
Onl 26th June, 1946, Mr. Dedman said that rural loans mnade for wa r&lt;br /&gt;
service land settlement to 31st May, 1946, , vere-&lt;br /&gt;
New South Wales, 668 applications, &#339; 461,334 Victoria, 100, &#339; 66,219 Queensland,&lt;br /&gt;
47, &#339; 26,332 South Australia, 75, &#339; 55,074 Western Australia, 444, &#339; E365,510;&lt;br /&gt;
Tasmania, 26, &#339; 18,451 total, 1,360, &#339; 992,920.&lt;br /&gt;
GOVERNMENT'S PLAN-NATIONAL WORKS COUNCIL, LOCAL&lt;br /&gt;
GOVERNMENT AREAS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 1st July, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
SThe question has beeni asked whether the Commnonwealth Government&lt;br /&gt;
would give financial assistance to local authorities to implement their plans&lt;br /&gt;
for local works, improvemlents and facilities, or arrange For the granting&lt;br /&gt;
of interest free loans to such bodies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;26&lt;br /&gt;
It must be remembered that these local authorities are self-governing&lt;br /&gt;
bodies, responsible to the electors, and that powers exist under State law&lt;br /&gt;
for them to raise loans, as well as obtain revenue by the levying of rates.&lt;br /&gt;
As to concessional interest rates, I think it would be difficult to justify the&lt;br /&gt;
selection of one class of borrowing for favoured treatment in this respect.&lt;br /&gt;
Moreover, a concession to one class of borrowers presents the problem of&lt;br /&gt;
adjusting upwards the rates to other borrowers if a net loss in interest&lt;br /&gt;
receipts from all advances--involving an additional charge on the Budget--&lt;br /&gt;
is to be avoided.&lt;br /&gt;
The Commonwealth Government is aware of the problems associated&lt;br /&gt;
with the financing of public work programmes and has actively pursued a&lt;br /&gt;
policy which will provide the most favorable terms over the widest field&lt;br /&gt;
of prospective borrowers. I refer particularly to the fact that borrowings&lt;br /&gt;
by governments, and semi-and local government authorities, may now be&lt;br /&gt;
negotiated on more favorable terms than ever before and this is directly&lt;br /&gt;
. ttributable to the policy of low interest rates by the Commonwealth.&lt;br /&gt;
It is essential to the continued success of financial policy, that all&lt;br /&gt;
. pproaches to the market for loan funds should be properly co-ordinated.&lt;br /&gt;
This is particularly important during the next few years, when it will be&lt;br /&gt;
necessary to introduce the public works requirements of Commonwealth,&lt;br /&gt;
State and local government bodies in an ordered way so as to avoid undue&lt;br /&gt;
, competition for available building and works facilities. Similarly, it is&lt;br /&gt;
-sscntial that financial needs be co-ordinated and related to available money.&lt;br /&gt;
The fact that the Commonwealth, foreseeing these potential needs,&lt;br /&gt;
: onvened the National Works Council, and was instrumental in having a&lt;br /&gt;
long-term public works programme planned by the States, must not be&lt;br /&gt;
interpreted as an indication that the Commonwealth Government desires to&lt;br /&gt;
usurp the sovereign responsibilities of the States in the field of local government,&lt;br /&gt;
nor that it is prepared to support a financial arrangement which&lt;br /&gt;
would give strong preference to local government bodies in respect of public&lt;br /&gt;
works finance which could not be extended to other Commonwealth and&lt;br /&gt;
State financial requirements for public works and buildings programmes.&lt;br /&gt;
At its first meeting in January, 1944, the National Works Council&lt;br /&gt;
agreed to. the preparation of a programme of public works in three classifications&lt;br /&gt;
of urgency and amounting in all to roughly &#339; 200,000,000 as a reservoir&lt;br /&gt;
of worhs to facilitate the stabilization of the early post-war economic&lt;br /&gt;
condition. It was resolved that the programme for each State should be&lt;br /&gt;
endorsed by that State Government and that the administering authority&lt;br /&gt;
of the programme should indicate its agreement to accept the financial&lt;br /&gt;
responsibility entailed. Among the items included in the States' programmes&lt;br /&gt;
would be works planned by local government authorities and&lt;br /&gt;
authorized by the State Government concerned as sufficiently urgent to be&lt;br /&gt;
included in its programme. At the second meeting of the National Works&lt;br /&gt;
Council in August, 1944, progress was reviewed and it was again emphasized&lt;br /&gt;
that the responsibility for the financing of the works programmes planned&lt;br /&gt;
rested on the States. Local government authorities should, therefore,&lt;br /&gt;
submit their loan proposals to their State Governments." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;27&lt;br /&gt;
UNITED NATIONS FOOD AND AGRICULTURE ORGANIZATIONAUSTRALIAN&lt;br /&gt;
BODY.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1946, Mr. Chifley said---&lt;br /&gt;
The Fcod and Agriculture Organization is now becoming effectively&lt;br /&gt;
established as an integral part of the new international machinery of the&lt;br /&gt;
United Nations. The first conference, to which Australia sent a delegation,&lt;br /&gt;
was held in 1945. Following the conference, steps have been taken to build&lt;br /&gt;
up a permanent secretariat to carry out its functions.&lt;br /&gt;
In 1944, Full Cabinet approved of an inter-departmental committee&lt;br /&gt;
being established, comprising representatives of the Departments of the&lt;br /&gt;
Treasury, External Affairs, Post-war Reconstruction, Commerce and Agriculture,&lt;br /&gt;
and Health, to consider matters associated with the subject as&lt;br /&gt;
they arose and to report to the Minister for External Affairs. A request&lt;br /&gt;
has now been received from the Director-General of the Food and Agriculture&lt;br /&gt;
Organization that an Australian committee be set up to provide a&lt;br /&gt;
liaison between the appropria: e agencies in Australia and the secretariat&lt;br /&gt;
of the organization.&lt;br /&gt;
" Cabinet decided to-day that the Inter-departmental Committee be&lt;br /&gt;
S replaced by an Australian Food and Agriculture Organization Committee&lt;br /&gt;
to be set up in conformity with the request of the Director-General of F. A. O.,&lt;br /&gt;
comprising representatives of the Departments of the Treasury, External&lt;br /&gt;
S Affairs, Commerce and Agriculture, Information, Interior, Health, and of&lt;br /&gt;
the Bureau of Agricultural Economics ( now with the Department of Post-&lt;br /&gt;
S war Reconstruction), the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research,&lt;br /&gt;
the Commonwealth Statistician, and the Forestry and Timber Bureau.&lt;br /&gt;
The Australian F. A. O. Committee has the following duties and responsibilities&lt;br /&gt;
To advise the Government on policy questions in regard to F. A. O.&lt;br /&gt;
To collect information and statistics required by the F. A. O. secretariat from&lt;br /&gt;
Australia and to approve such matter before despatch.&lt;br /&gt;
To disseminate information provided by F. A. O.&lt;br /&gt;
To bring to the notice of appropriate authorities any action required on their part&lt;br /&gt;
S to carry out the purposes of F. A. O.&lt;br /&gt;
To prepare the draft brief for Australian representatives attending conferences and&lt;br /&gt;
other meetings of the F. A. O.&lt;br /&gt;
To furnish a quarterly progress report to Cabinet and to report at other times as&lt;br /&gt;
circumstances require.&lt;br /&gt;
To arrange suitable publicity for F. A. O. activities through the Department of&lt;br /&gt;
Information.&lt;br /&gt;
S To co-operate with State authorities through the Department of Commerce and&lt;br /&gt;
Agriculture and the Australian Agricultural Council.&lt;br /&gt;
WORLD ORGANIZATION--ATOMIC ENERGY.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 3rd July, 1946, Mr. Chifley said--&lt;br /&gt;
On the general subject of the control of atomic energy and the materials&lt;br /&gt;
used in the manufacture of atomic bombs, a conference has been sitting for&lt;br /&gt;
some time. The Minister for External Affairs ( Dr. Evatt) is representing&lt;br /&gt;
Australia. I cannot say what final decisions are likely to be reached, but&lt;br /&gt;
the general view has been expressed by this Government, and has been&lt;br /&gt;
submitted to the conference, that the control of atomic energy should be&lt;br /&gt;
placed under the United Nations. Having regard to the dreadful possibilities&lt;br /&gt;
of the use of uranium and other ingredients in the production of &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;atomic bombs, and to the future peace of the world, our belief is that this&lt;br /&gt;
new discovery should be developed to produce industrial power and not&lt;br /&gt;
hombs for war purposes. Dr. Evatt is making this clear at the conference."&lt;br /&gt;
SECONDARY INDUSTRIES COMMISSION-PLYWOOD INDUSTRY&lt;br /&gt;
PANEL.&lt;br /&gt;
On 3rd July, 1946, Mr. Dedman announced the formation of a Plywood&lt;br /&gt;
Industry Advisory Panel to function within the Secondary Industries&lt;br /&gt;
Division of his department comprising-&lt;br /&gt;
Mr. I. H. Boas, chairman, the secretary of the Department of Forests, Papua-New&lt;br /&gt;
Guinea ( Mr. J. B. McAdam), Messrs. J. F. Brett and C. R. Paterson ( Australian Plywood&lt;br /&gt;
Board), Mr. C. Mitchell ( Associated Country Saw Millers of New South Wales), the&lt;br /&gt;
secretary of the Furnishing Trad-es Union ( Mr. O. Schreiber), the secretary of the&lt;br /&gt;
Timber Workers' Union ( Mr. J. A. Weir), and Mr. A. H. Crane ( Forestry Division,&lt;br /&gt;
Queensland Department of Lands).&lt;br /&gt;
The panel would report on--&lt;br /&gt;
The pro-war and post-war requirements of plywood by types to determine the degree&lt;br /&gt;
of permanency of any increased demand.&lt;br /&gt;
The present day relation between established demand and. available supplies&lt;br /&gt;
expressed in terms of local production capacity, plus importation potential.&lt;br /&gt;
The location and availability of logs with particular reference to unexploited home&lt;br /&gt;
: and adjacent island stands of timber.&lt;br /&gt;
Action to secure an adequate supply of logs for the plywood industry to meet&lt;br /&gt;
current and expected demands.&lt;br /&gt;
WHEAT POOLS PAYMENTS.&lt;br /&gt;
No. 8 WHEAT POOL-THIRD ADVANCE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 26th June, 1946, the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Scully) announced&lt;br /&gt;
; a third advance in No. 8 pool of 9d. a bushel bulk quota wheat and Is. lid.&lt;br /&gt;
a bushel for non-quota wheat, less freight in each case. An extra Id. would&lt;br /&gt;
be paid on bagged wheat. The advance brought payments of the pool to&lt;br /&gt;
4s. llAd. a bushel, less freight bagged basis.&lt;br /&gt;
TARIFF.&lt;br /&gt;
EXPORTS PROHIBITED.&lt;br /&gt;
On 27th Jtune, 1946, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Fraser) announced&lt;br /&gt;
that exportation of pig lead, scrap lead and manufactures of lead had been&lt;br /&gt;
prohibited. On 3rd July, 1946, Senator Fraser announced that exportation of&lt;br /&gt;
tobacco, cigars and cigarettes had been prohibited.&lt;br /&gt;
ROYAL AUSTRALIAN NAVY.&lt;br /&gt;
AWARDS FOR GALLANTRY.&lt;br /&gt;
On 27th June, 1946, the Governor-General announced the award of the&lt;br /&gt;
Distinguished Service Cross to Lieutenant G. J. B. Crabb. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PETROL SUPPLIES.&lt;br /&gt;
RATIONING SYSTEM-. ADJUSTMENT.&lt;br /&gt;
On 27th June, 1946, the Minister for Supply ( Senator Ashley) announced&lt;br /&gt;
that the adjustment promised in respect of petrol consumers in classes&lt;br /&gt;
3 to 7, whose licences covered both private and business running, would be&lt;br /&gt;
effected by making available an additional four gallons of motor spirit&lt;br /&gt;
monthly as from the August issue uniformly to each consumer in those&lt;br /&gt;
groups, thus making the actual ration available the gillonage shown on the.&lt;br /&gt;
face of ench consumer's licence, plus four.&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier reference, please see No. 115, p. 18.)&lt;br /&gt;
AUSTRALIAN WAR EFFORT AND CAPACITY.&lt;br /&gt;
CONTROL OF TINPLATE--RE-INSTITUTED.&lt;br /&gt;
On 27th June, 1946, the Minister for Supply ( Senator Ashley) announced&lt;br /&gt;
that as from 1st July, 1946, control of the end use of tinplate, which had&lt;br /&gt;
been relaxed in October, 1945, would be re-instituted. Action had been&lt;br /&gt;
necessary because of serious cut-hacks in allocation:; of tinplate from the&lt;br /&gt;
United States and because substantial supplies of tinplate were not yet&lt;br /&gt;
coming forward from Britain. The Government was taking steps to meet&lt;br /&gt;
the position and had despatched a mission to Britain and the United States&lt;br /&gt;
to ensure that Australia's needs were fully known.&lt;br /&gt;
PHILIPPINES.&lt;br /&gt;
INDEPENDENCE-AUSTRALIAN REPRESENTATION.&lt;br /&gt;
On 27th June, 1946, the acting Minister for External Affairs ( Mr. Makin)&lt;br /&gt;
announced that Australia would be represented by Commodore J. A. Collins&lt;br /&gt;
and the Australian Consul-General in the Philippines ( Mr. H. A. Peterson)&lt;br /&gt;
; at the ceremonies attending the proclamation of Philippine independence&lt;br /&gt;
at Manilla on 4th July, 1946.&lt;br /&gt;
MORTGAGE BANK.&lt;br /&gt;
OPERATIONS TO JUNE, 1946.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parlianment.-On 28th June, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley)&lt;br /&gt;
said that to 25th June, 1946, applications for lcans to the Mortgage Bank&lt;br /&gt;
Department of the Commonwealth Bank totalled 2,535 of which 1,398 had&lt;br /&gt;
been approved, involving &#339; 2,924,105. TAXATION.&lt;br /&gt;
COMPARISONS WITH OTHER COUNTRIES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 28th June, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chilley) said that staterients&lt;br /&gt;
comparing the level of taxation in Australia with that of other&lt;br /&gt;
countries were misleading, unless qualified by a proper understanding of&lt;br /&gt;
the relative values of the several currencies and other relevant factors,&lt;br /&gt;
including the level of indirect taxation, such as customs and excise duties,&lt;br /&gt;
the level of social services expenditure, the standard of living in each&lt;br /&gt;
: ountry and whether the exchange rates were free or pegged. I &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tables of tax payable in sterling countries as compared with tax payable&lt;br /&gt;
in non-sterling countries should be treated with great caution before&lt;br /&gt;
drawing any conclusions from them. In the following table, setting out the&lt;br /&gt;
tax payable on selected incomes in Australia, New Zealand and Britain,&lt;br /&gt;
in each case the tax payable had been expressed in the currency of the&lt;br /&gt;
country concerned. The amounts shown in the statement included the&lt;br /&gt;
following levies&lt;br /&gt;
Australia-social services contribution. New Zealan!--social security&lt;br /&gt;
charge, Britain-national insurance at 4s. 10d. a week.&lt;br /&gt;
Income. Australia. New Zealand. I; ritaln.&lt;br /&gt;
150 9. 19 16&lt;br /&gt;
200 15 25&lt;br /&gt;
250 30 40 38&lt;br /&gt;
300 46 54&lt;br /&gt;
350 04 70&lt;br /&gt;
400 82 85&lt;br /&gt;
500 118 117 134&lt;br /&gt;
600 155 152 173&lt;br /&gt;
800 23 225 252&lt;br /&gt;
1,000 312 305 331&lt;br /&gt;
1,250 422 415 432&lt;br /&gt;
1,500 547 534 544&lt;br /&gt;
2,000 45 805 769&lt;br /&gt;
3,000 1,557 1,472 1,332&lt;br /&gt;
4,000 2,341 2,304 1,957&lt;br /&gt;
5,000 3,157 3,204 2,632&lt;br /&gt;
EXTERNAL TERRITORIES.&lt;br /&gt;
CIVIL ADMINISTRATION-FULL RESTORATION.&lt;br /&gt;
On 28th June, 1946, the Minister for External Territories ( Mr. Ward)&lt;br /&gt;
announced that the transfer of administrative control of the Rabaul and&lt;br /&gt;
Kokopo sub-districts of New Britain from the Australian Military Forces&lt;br /&gt;
to the Provisional Administration of the Territory of Papua-New Guinea&lt;br /&gt;
had been effected on 24th June, 1946. Restoration of civil administration&lt;br /&gt;
to the whole of the territories was now complete.&lt;br /&gt;
WHEAT STABILIZATION SCHEME.&lt;br /&gt;
POST-WAR-PRODUCTION COSTS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 1st July, 1946, the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Scully) said that h;,&lt;br /&gt;
had told the Australian Wheat-growers' Federation that day that he would&lt;br /&gt;
recommend to Cabinet that a commission of inquiry be set up to ascertain&lt;br /&gt;
the cost of producing wheat in Australia. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;311&lt;br /&gt;
AUSTRALIAN BROADCASTING COMMISSION.&lt;br /&gt;
REVENUE FROM LICENCES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
In June, 1945, Cabinet approved of the continuation of a special payment&lt;br /&gt;
to the Australian Broadcasting Commission of such additional amount&lt;br /&gt;
; Is is equivalent to Is. a full licence fee and 6d. a half licence fee for a period&lt;br /&gt;
of twelve months on the basis of licences in force on 30th June, 1945. This&lt;br /&gt;
was a further continuation of an arrangement approved in May, 1944.&lt;br /&gt;
Cabinet to-day decided to continue still further this special payment&lt;br /&gt;
tor a further v.: ar, pending a report on the subject by the Parliamentary&lt;br /&gt;
Standing Committee on Broadcasting."&lt;br /&gt;
SOCIAL SECURITY.&lt;br /&gt;
TUBERCULOSIS PATIENTS-COMMONWEALTH GRANT.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
The Tuberculosis Act, passed by Parliament in October, 1945, came&lt;br /&gt;
into operation on 1st January, 1946, and provided for Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
grants for diagnostic facilities, after-care facilities, payment for patients in&lt;br /&gt;
State hospitals and special allowances to a sufferer or his or her dependants.&lt;br /&gt;
In regard to special allowances, the then Minister for Health ( Senator Fraser)&lt;br /&gt;
and I were directed by Cabinet to discuss with the State Ministers for Health&lt;br /&gt;
the question of the States distributing, on behalf of the Commonwealth,&lt;br /&gt;
the grant to be used as a special tubercul,) sis allowance.&lt;br /&gt;
To provide for policy and administrative questions arising from the&lt;br /&gt;
Act, Cabilnet to-dav decided that the Act be amended to provide that an&lt;br /&gt;
amount of &#339; 250,000 a year may be payable to States, the allocation to each&lt;br /&gt;
State to be determined by the Minister, on condition that the States distribute&lt;br /&gt;
the grant to or in respect of sufferers from tuberculosis or their&lt;br /&gt;
dependants in necessitous circumstances to achieve the object of encouraging&lt;br /&gt;
sufferers to cease work and take treatment; to assist in preventing the&lt;br /&gt;
spread of the disese and to promote the better treatment of the disease;&lt;br /&gt;
and that payments received by individuals in accordance with the proposed&lt;br /&gt;
new section shall not be regarded as income for the purposes of the Invalid&lt;br /&gt;
and Old-age Pensions Act and of the Unemployment and Sickness Benefits&lt;br /&gt;
Act. This will ensure that the tuberculosis special allowances are-excluded&lt;br /&gt;
from the means tests imposed in these two Acts, thus making the allowances&lt;br /&gt;
additional to any benefit the sufferer may be eligible to receive direct&lt;br /&gt;
from the Commonweilth by waY of sickness benefit or invalid pension."'&lt;br /&gt;
AUSTRALIAN BROADCASTING ACT.&lt;br /&gt;
VENEREAL DISEASE, SEX TALKS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 3rd July, 1946, the Postmaster-General ( Senator Cameron) announced&lt;br /&gt;
that the Parliamentary Broadcasting Committee had recommended that&lt;br /&gt;
broadcast talks on venereal disease and sex matters should net be permitted.&lt;br /&gt;
The Government had adopted the recommendation and broadcasting stations&lt;br /&gt;
had been requested to refrain forthwith from broadcasting such talks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;32&lt;br /&gt;
PRICES.&lt;br /&gt;
U. S. REVOCATION-EFFECT ON AUSTRALIA.&lt;br /&gt;
On 3rd July, 1946, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Fraser) said that&lt;br /&gt;
the effect on Australian prices of the abandonment of price control in the&lt;br /&gt;
United States would depend on the. extent and direction of the inflationary&lt;br /&gt;
forces in America. It was not known whether American exports would be&lt;br /&gt;
affected or whether any increase in price would be significant. In any&lt;br /&gt;
case, it would be some months before goods purchased at currnat or future&lt;br /&gt;
prices would be landing in Australia and there was no present indication&lt;br /&gt;
that the local retail price level would be affected. It was difficult to make&lt;br /&gt;
any forecasts but Australia would watch developments in the United States&lt;br /&gt;
with great interest both from the point of view of the lesson to be learned&lt;br /&gt;
from the experiment, and the effects on the Australian economy.&lt;br /&gt;
SERVICE PAY RATES.&lt;br /&gt;
DEFERRED PAY-GOVERNMENT LIABILITY.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 3rd July, 1946, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley)&lt;br /&gt;
said-Total expenditure on deferred pay for the financial year 1944-45 was&lt;br /&gt;
&#339; 9,674,273. To 30th May, 1946, expenditure was &#339; 67,711,892."&lt;br /&gt;
MEAT AGREEMENT.&lt;br /&gt;
EXPORTS-CONTROL, BILL INTRODUCED.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.-On 3rd July, 1946, the Minister for Commerce ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
Scully) introduced the Meat Export Control Bill. Mr. Scully said-&lt;br /&gt;
The purpose of this bill, to amend the Meat Export Control Act, is to&lt;br /&gt;
provide for the reconstitution of the Australian Meat Board, and to grant&lt;br /&gt;
to the board additional powers necessary to enable it to carry out work in&lt;br /&gt;
relation to the long-term purchase agreement covering ncat for export,&lt;br /&gt;
entered into between the Commonw,. ealth Go-vernment and the British&lt;br /&gt;
Government. The Australian Meat Board will consist of twelve members, including&lt;br /&gt;
a Commonwealth Government representative, who will be appointed by the&lt;br /&gt;
Governor-General. He will be employed full-time on the business of the&lt;br /&gt;
board and will be chairman. Of the remaining eleven members, seven&lt;br /&gt;
members, constituting a clear majority of the board, will be representative&lt;br /&gt;
of producer interests. Producer members, comprising four representatives&lt;br /&gt;
of the lamb and mutton producers, two of the beef producers, and one of'&lt;br /&gt;
the pig producers, must be bona fide producers, and must be persons&lt;br /&gt;
nominated by producer organizations constituted on a Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
basis. Members appointed to represent the meat exporting companies arc&lt;br /&gt;
to be appointed after consultation with representative organizations of&lt;br /&gt;
meat exporters. The member appointed to represent the employees will&lt;br /&gt;
be appointed after co:, ulltation with the Federal Council of the Meat&lt;br /&gt;
Industry Employees Union. The member appointed to represent the&lt;br /&gt;
publicly-owned abattoirs and freezing works will be appointed by th'e&lt;br /&gt;
Governor-General. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J'I&lt;br /&gt;
The bill gives the person presiding at a meeting tile right to dissent&lt;br /&gt;
from any decision of the board. This right is necessary because of the&lt;br /&gt;
Conmmn: nwealth Government's financial interest in the operations of thet&lt;br /&gt;
board. It is essential that the chairman shall have the right to bring to&lt;br /&gt;
thef Minister's notice immediately any resolutior which lie considers may&lt;br /&gt;
involve the Commonwealth Government in any way on a point of principle&lt;br /&gt;
or, on question of financial losses or gains.&lt;br /&gt;
So that all sections of the industry may be in a position to present&lt;br /&gt;
their views on matters affecting the ilndustry, provision has been made for&lt;br /&gt;
th' settini. g-up of State conmmittees. It will be competent for any duly&lt;br /&gt;
constituted State organization representing a section of the meat industry&lt;br /&gt;
to: ; ppl\ fcr representation on the State committee.&lt;br /&gt;
SAs the ainiistration of the long-term purchase agreement for meat&lt;br /&gt;
between the Commonwealth Government and the British Government will&lt;br /&gt;
li, a function of the board after the expiration of the ANatioil Security Act,&lt;br /&gt;
provision has been malde for the powers of the board to be extended to&lt;br /&gt;
includ the following&lt;br /&gt;
To purchase on behalf of the Conimonwealth Government any meat, meat product,&lt;br /&gt;
or edible offal.&lt;br /&gt;
To sell on behalf of the Commonwealth Government any meat, meat product, or&lt;br /&gt;
edible offal.&lt;br /&gt;
To manage and control as necessary, the handling, storage aifd shipment of any&lt;br /&gt;
meat, meat product, or edible offal.&lt;br /&gt;
Subject to the approval of the Commonwealth Government, to obtain advances&lt;br /&gt;
from the Commonwealth Bank under Commonwealth Government guarantee, for use&lt;br /&gt;
in the purchase of meat for export and the payment of expenses incurred in connexion&lt;br /&gt;
therewith. Attention is directed to the provision, of. special interest to producers,&lt;br /&gt;
that. the colnitions attaching to the issue by the board of an export licence&lt;br /&gt;
liav bieen extended to n ake it obligatory on the licensee, where the prodlucer-&lt;br /&gt;
wnier of such stock so requests, to treat stock on account of the&lt;br /&gt;
o) wn'r n weigh t and grade basis." [ The bill ats ipssed.]&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliament.--On 3rd July, 1946, Mr. Scully introduced the Meat&lt;br /&gt;
Industry Control Bill. Mr. Scully said&lt;br /&gt;
The purpose of this bill. which is supplementary to the Meat Export&lt;br /&gt;
Control Bill, is to transfer to the Australian Meat Board the powers arnd&lt;br /&gt;
functions at present exercised by the Controller of Meat Supplies and the&lt;br /&gt;
Meat Canning Committee under National Security Act regulations. It will&lt;br /&gt;
b) e appreciated that the transfer is to be temporary, and that, with the&lt;br /&gt;
expiration of the National Security Act, this act will cease to have the force&lt;br /&gt;
of law. Notwithstanding that, the interests of the Commonwealth Government&lt;br /&gt;
and of the meat industry, insofar as they relate to actions taken 1v&lt;br /&gt;
the Controller of Meat Supplies and the Meat Canning Committee ander&lt;br /&gt;
Nationa. l Secu-i ity Act regulations, must be protected. The bill provides&lt;br /&gt;
that these rights and obligatilns shall be assumed by the Australian Meat&lt;br /&gt;
Board. Since the rationing of meat and the control of meat prices n. re&lt;br /&gt;
nmatters which, for the time being ; t least, are closely linked with the&lt;br /&gt;
4420.--2 * i &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;general control of the meat industry, provision has been made for the temporary&lt;br /&gt;
appointment to the Australian Meat Board of additional memhers,&lt;br /&gt;
one to represent the Commonwealth Prices Commissioner, and one the&lt;br /&gt;
Director of Rationing. These members will automatically cease to hold&lt;br /&gt;
office upon the expiration of the National Scc rity Act."&lt;br /&gt;
[ The bill was passed.]&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 83, p. 37; No. 109, p. 8.)&lt;br /&gt;
NATIONALITY.&lt;br /&gt;
NATURALIZATION-NEW GUINEA.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parliamnent.-On 4th July, 1946, the Minister for Immigration ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
Calwell) introduced the Nationality Bill. Mr. Calwell said-&lt;br /&gt;
Under existing nationality law, an essential requirement for the grant&lt;br /&gt;
of a certificate of naturalization is that an applicant shall have resided for&lt;br /&gt;
a prescribed period within the British dominions. The Territory of New&lt;br /&gt;
Guinea does not form a part of the Briti., h dominions for the purposes of&lt;br /&gt;
nationality law, and residence in the territory cannot be counted as&lt;br /&gt;
residence for the grant of naturalization. This means that the only way&lt;br /&gt;
open at present to a person living in the territory to acquire British nationality,&lt;br /&gt;
which will be recognized in Australia, or other parts of the Empire,&lt;br /&gt;
is to abandon his domicile there and take up residence in Australia or some&lt;br /&gt;
other part of the British Commonwealth. The purpose of this bill is to&lt;br /&gt;
enable a resident of the territory to qualify for naturalization as a British&lt;br /&gt;
subject while maintaining his residence in the territory.&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth Crown Law authorities have expressed the opinion&lt;br /&gt;
that it is nQt possible to grant to residents of New Guinea naturalization&lt;br /&gt;
which would be effective throughout the British dominions. The Government&lt;br /&gt;
has decided that the next best should be given to residents of the&lt;br /&gt;
territory; that is, that they shall be accorded the privilege of qualifying&lt;br /&gt;
for the grant of British nationality which will have effect in the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
and its territories. The hill makes that provision.&lt;br /&gt;
It is not the Government's intention that this shall be the final word&lt;br /&gt;
on the subject. It is proposed to hold a conference of representatives of&lt;br /&gt;
Britain and the Dominions in the near future to discuss certain nationality&lt;br /&gt;
questions. It is intended to raise at that conference the matter of making&lt;br /&gt;
provision that residence in New Guinea shall he regarded as a qualification&lt;br /&gt;
for the grant of a certificate of naturalization which will be effective, not&lt;br /&gt;
only in Australia and its territories, hut also throughout the whole of the&lt;br /&gt;
British Commonwealth.' [ Th7e bill wlr pased.]&lt;br /&gt;
JUDICIARY.&lt;br /&gt;
ARBITRATION C. OURT-PENSION RIGHTS.&lt;br /&gt;
In Ptli,, went.-On 4th July, 194i, the Minister for Labour ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
Hollow iv) introduced the Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration&lt;br /&gt;
Bill. Mr. Holloway said&lt;br /&gt;
The object of this hill is to provide that, where a judge of the Common-l&lt;br /&gt;
weallth Arbitration Court has, before his appointment, served in any judicil&lt;br /&gt;
dflir, und.' r a State, his service umnder the State. up to a period of ten yeo,' rs, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;shall be deemed to be part of his service as a judge of the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
Arbitration Court for the purpose of calculating his pension rights. Under&lt;br /&gt;
the act in its present form, account may be taken of prior service in a&lt;br /&gt;
judicial office under the Commonwealth for the purposes of pension rights,&lt;br /&gt;
hlt no such provision is made in respect of prior service in a judicial office&lt;br /&gt;
under a State.&lt;br /&gt;
In other legislation, for example, the BaInkraptry Act, a limited period&lt;br /&gt;
of prior service in a judicial office under a State may be taken into account&lt;br /&gt;
for the purposes of pension. The idea is to establish a permanent basis&lt;br /&gt;
for settling matters of this kind. Recently, several new judges have been&lt;br /&gt;
appointed, and most ce them have served in a judicial capacity in a State."&lt;br /&gt;
[ The bill was passed.]&lt;br /&gt;
PATENTS.&lt;br /&gt;
BILL INTRODUCED.&lt;br /&gt;
In Pirliamein't.-On 4th July, 1946. the Acting Attorney-General ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
IIllowa.) introduced the Patents Bill. MJr. Holloway said-&lt;br /&gt;
The principal object of the bill is to remove certain disadvantages&lt;br /&gt;
which have occurred by. reason of the deltayv at present existing in the&lt;br /&gt;
examination work of the Patent Office. That delay has ibeen brought about&lt;br /&gt;
in plart , y the fact that a large nmber of exaniiners of patent. s--representing&lt;br /&gt;
over 60 per cent. of the stal'f-were released during the war fromn&lt;br /&gt;
the Patent Office for service in the forces and in other departments. The&lt;br /&gt;
de! ay has also been partly brought about by reason of an abnormal and&lt;br /&gt;
entirely unpredictable increase of the number of applications for patents.&lt;br /&gt;
This increase appears to be largely due to the great industrial development&lt;br /&gt;
which has taken place in Australia in recent years. Many overseas manufacturers&lt;br /&gt;
discovered during the war that the Australian market was worth-&lt;br /&gt;
\ vhile. and that they cannot obtain royalties for the use of their inventions&lt;br /&gt;
in Australia unless they patent them here. Tn 1939, the nunmb" r of applications&lt;br /&gt;
for patents was 5,700; last year it was 7,300; and it is expected&lt;br /&gt;
that. this year the iiumbier will exceed 10,000.&lt;br /&gt;
Every effort is being made to obtain the services of additional&lt;br /&gt;
examinrs of patents. It takes at least three years to train an examiner&lt;br /&gt;
full-in his work, and some considerable time will elapse before any substantial&lt;br /&gt;
reduction is made of the arrears of examination work in the Patent&lt;br /&gt;
Office. Anv serious delay in the examination of patent applications has a&lt;br /&gt;
dlerimental effect on inventors, and -m industrial development.&lt;br /&gt;
This bill proposes to amend, the law so as to provide for the publication&lt;br /&gt;
complete specifications forthwith after lodgment at the Patent Office&lt;br /&gt;
anld for a patentee whose invention has been used after publication to be&lt;br /&gt;
entitled to damages for infringement committed from the date of publication&lt;br /&gt;
forthwith after the lodgment instead of from the date of publication consequent&lt;br /&gt;
upon acceptance. Damages are recoverable only if a patent is&lt;br /&gt;
ultimnately sealed on the application and only in respect of valid claims.&lt;br /&gt;
As a corollary to the provisions referred to, the bill gives protection to&lt;br /&gt;
persons who may be threatened with infringement actions by applicants&lt;br /&gt;
4420.--&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;on the basis of questionable or iivali I claims, and prohibits the miking of&lt;br /&gt;
falso representations that articles are patented or the subject of ienlinr&lt;br /&gt;
applications. SThe bill proposes to imake periai. neit a; practice aidopte! durig the&lt;br /&gt;
war under ntional Security Act Regulations of not examiniung a pr, ov isiotial&lt;br /&gt;
specification until the complete specificetionll has len lodged. lI -aaiy&lt;br /&gt;
cases, applications are acconipanied I* v provisional specifications onvl and&lt;br /&gt;
lapse hb reason of the ailure oif the ipplicant to lodge a collnplt ; Is-cification.&lt;br /&gt;
The ti: e spent in exannliin provisional specifications 1whih0 via; v&lt;br /&gt;
lapse will he sa\ l ed Ylir eason of this allnendlinenit." [ The bill iwmci I"' ssd&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier reference, please see No. 96, p. 47.)&lt;br /&gt;
SERVICE PAY RATES.&lt;br /&gt;
REP'ATRIA TION-MElD-E) ICAL CARE, COMMITTEE APPOJNTEU.&lt;br /&gt;
In Parlinvient.-On 5th July, 1946, thile Minister for Repatriaition ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
Frost) said that the Repatriation Coniissin, with his coienrr-no", h1o&lt;br /&gt;
oppointed the following coillillitte':&lt;br /&gt;
Colonel E. J. Parks, chaiiman, Major-Geueral S. R. Burston, Air Vi., e-Marshal&lt;br /&gt;
S. V. Hurley, Colonel K. Smith, and Captain C. Wheeler, secretary.&lt;br /&gt;
Its terms of referetce were-&lt;br /&gt;
To examine the existing metlical set-up of the Repatriation ( onnnission throughout&lt;br /&gt;
Australia; to consilder fully all facts antd factors affecting proper medical care anti&lt;br /&gt;
treatment of all mruembers of the Forces in the future suffering physically or mentally&lt;br /&gt;
as a result of their war service, and as a result of its investigations and deliberations&lt;br /&gt;
to advise as to the future policy, organization and administration of tilhe medical&lt;br /&gt;
services of the Repatriation Commission with a view to ensuring the best and most&lt;br /&gt;
efficient medical services and also to ensure, as far as possible, that ex-servicomen in&lt;br /&gt;
tilhe medical care of the Repatriation Commission have the ben-fit of thile Iatest arv. nce,&lt;br /&gt;
in medicine, surgery and medical rehabilitation.&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier reference, please see No. 94. p. 3.)&lt;br /&gt;
DENMARK.&lt;br /&gt;
EXCHANGE OF KINISTERS-DANISH lMINTISTER.&lt;br /&gt;
OiL . th JUIlv. 1946, the Acting Miiiister for External Affairs ( 2Mr. Makin)&lt;br /&gt;
, nniouncedl that , i.' reeiuent has been reached on the exchange of diplomatic&lt;br /&gt;
miissionls ibetween Australia and Denmark. The first Danish Minister to&lt;br /&gt;
Ausrtralia ( Mr. C. lRottholi) would soon arrive in Australia. rThe Danish&lt;br /&gt;
bGovernm'ent Ilhal Iee informnel that it might not hie possile to appoint ii&lt;br /&gt;
Australint Miinist er innediatel. BRITAIN.&lt;br /&gt;
PROPOSED VISIT BY MR. ATTLEE--POSTPONED.&lt;br /&gt;
On 6th Jub-. 1946 the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said--&lt;br /&gt;
SThe B3ritishl Prime Minister and Mrs. Attlee have been looking for1ward&lt;br /&gt;
to visiting Australia and New Zealand at the invitation of their governments.&lt;br /&gt;
It was announced in April, 1946, that Mr. Attlee planued to leave Britain&lt;br /&gt;
in the last week of July, 1946, ibut that his plans were liable to revijion if&lt;br /&gt;
there should bie any public matters, requiring his personal attention, which&lt;br /&gt;
necessitated his presence in Britain in the period concerned. He has now&lt;br /&gt;
regretfully reached the conclusion that the decision recently announced to &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;summnioii the Peace Coaference at Paris onil 29th July, 1946, added to the&lt;br /&gt;
other pressing problems which confront the British Government at present,&lt;br /&gt;
render it impossible for hin to be absent froulnt Britain dluring the period&lt;br /&gt;
proposed for thile visit to Australia. and New Zealand. He has, accordingly,&lt;br /&gt;
informed mec that lie keenly regrets that. lie is obliged to cancel the arrangenernts&lt;br /&gt;
! L postponie the visit.&lt;br /&gt;
Both Mr. and Mrs. Attlee are acutely lisappointed at the loss of this&lt;br /&gt;
opportunity to see Australia and New Zealand, to meet their governments&lt;br /&gt;
and people and to express, on behalf of the people of Britain, the appreciation&lt;br /&gt;
of Britain of the minagnificent contribution made hY both the fighting&lt;br /&gt;
iten andl women and the civilians of each of the two Dominions ill the war.&lt;br /&gt;
They greatly hope that they imar have an ollpportunitY to visit Allstralia&lt;br /&gt;
;: nd New Zealand at a later ilatj'." HOUSING.&lt;br /&gt;
WAR WORKERS--REGULATIONS, REVOCATION.&lt;br /&gt;
On th J1ly, 1916, the Minister for Holusing ( Mr. Lazzaritti) anioiouced&lt;br /&gt;
the repeal of National Security ( Housing and Accommodation) Regulations,&lt;br /&gt;
which, during the war, had enabled essential workers, such as those engaged&lt;br /&gt;
in munitions, flax, food production andl certain others in prescribed ailreas,&lt;br /&gt;
to secure available o , inagn d accnoiodatiov.&lt;br /&gt;
AMERICA.&lt;br /&gt;
AMBASSADOR-UNITED STATES AND AUSTRALIAN&lt;br /&gt;
APPOINTMENTS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 9th July, 1946. the Prime Miniiter ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
SFollowing dibcussionts between the lMinister for External Affairs ( Dr.&lt;br /&gt;
Evatt), the President of the United States ( Mr. Truman) andrl the Acting&lt;br /&gt;
Secretary of State ( Mr. Dean Acheson), formal arrangements have now&lt;br /&gt;
been completed betten the Australian and LniIod States Governments&lt;br /&gt;
for the raising of the rank of their legations at Canluberra and Washington&lt;br /&gt;
to embassies. and of the office of Minister to that of Ambas ador. This&lt;br /&gt;
step is the natural consequence of the iicrea. ingly closer and cordial relations&lt;br /&gt;
betweenll Australia and the Unitel States and reflects the added importance&lt;br /&gt;
of the Pacific area in the eves of both goverimients. The move also serves&lt;br /&gt;
as a recoanition of th. e major contribution made by Australia to victory&lt;br /&gt;
in World War II., and of the important part which she continues to play&lt;br /&gt;
in regari to the pireservation of security inii the Pacific.&lt;br /&gt;
President Truman proposes to submit to the Senate the noillinatio&lt;br /&gt;
of Mr. Robert Butler of St. Paul, Minnesota, as first United States&lt;br /&gt;
Ambassador to Australia. Mr. Butler served in World War I. and is&lt;br /&gt;
to-day one of America's leading constructional engineers. He is also&lt;br /&gt;
actively connected with the governing bodies of various educational&lt;br /&gt;
establishments. The Minister for the Nave ( Mr. Makin) will, in dlue course, be&lt;br /&gt;
accrclited as the first Australian Anmb! ssador to the Uniit,, d States.'" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AUSTRALIAN MILITARY FORCES.&lt;br /&gt;
AWARDS FOR GALLANTRY.&lt;br /&gt;
Ou 10th July, 1946, the Governor-General announced the award of the&lt;br /&gt;
George Medal to Corporal Diti.&lt;br /&gt;
FIGHTING FORCES.&lt;br /&gt;
EDUCATIONAL SERVICES-PSYCHIATRIC CASES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 26th June, 1946, the Minister for Post-war Reconstruction ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
Dedman) announced that consideration had been given to the care of&lt;br /&gt;
persons discharged from the Forces who, although not eligible for repatria-j&lt;br /&gt;
tion benefits, had psychiatric disability and required treatment and satisfactory&lt;br /&gt;
re-establishment. Arrangements had been made for a committee&lt;br /&gt;
representative of the Ministry of Post-war Reconstruction, the Repatriation&lt;br /&gt;
Commission, the Department of Social Services, the Treasury and . the&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Labour to carry out detailed planning. The Australian&lt;br /&gt;
Red Cross Society had been invited to take part ith a view to it assuming&lt;br /&gt;
a full and official part in the development of the planning. Establishment&lt;br /&gt;
of a psychiatric out-patients' service in each State was an essential of the&lt;br /&gt;
plan, together with further development by the Department of Social&lt;br /&gt;
Services of its rehabilitation centres in State capitals. f r1&lt;br /&gt;
By Authority: L. F. JOHNSTON, Commonwealth Government Printer, Canberra. &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>