<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3</transcript-id>
    <title>Digest of Decisions and Announcements and Important Speeches No 10  - Period 1st December 1941 to 16th December 1941</title>
    <prime-minister>Curtin, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19411007 - 19450705</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/12/1941</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000003_3.pdf</document>
    <subjects />
    <content>&lt;p&gt;COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT.&lt;br /&gt;DIGESTOF DECISIONS&lt;br /&gt;AND ANNOUNCEMENTS&lt;br /&gt;IMPORTANT SPEECHES&lt;br /&gt;THE PRIME MINISTER&lt;br /&gt;( THE HON. JOHN CURTIN).&lt;br /&gt;No.&lt;br /&gt;IIFRIO) D) --slsr DE-CEIMBER. 1f41. To 16TH I) CEMJ3Efl, 1) 41.&lt;br /&gt;By Anthoritr.&lt;br /&gt;L F. JornSToN, COmmonwealth Government Printer. Canbem.&lt;br /&gt;( Printed in Australia.)&lt;br /&gt;b7U. _ I I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AUSTRALIAN MILITARY FORCES.&lt;br /&gt;STRATEGIC ROAD CONSTRUCTION.&lt;br /&gt;On 1st Decemiber, 1941, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Forde)&lt;br /&gt;said-" The important strategic route joining Western. Queenstnd and&lt;br /&gt;the North-South road is rapidly nearing completion. The road will be&lt;br /&gt;trafficable for at least nine months of the year, hut if seasons are&lt;br /&gt;favorable, it will he traversible for the whole twelve months."&lt;br /&gt;On 5th December, 1941, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) said-&lt;br /&gt;" War Cabinet to-day gave consideration to the question of the&lt;br /&gt;construction of roads of strategic and operational impoirtance. It was&lt;br /&gt;decided to proceed with all-weather strategic roads as follows:&lt;br /&gt;Northern Command ( Queensland), &#339; 616,000; Eastern Command ( New&lt;br /&gt;South Wales), &#339; 15,000; Western Goummand ( Western Australia),&lt;br /&gt;&#339; 17,000. Cabinet's decision will be * referred to the Co-ordinator-&lt;br /&gt;General of. Works ( Sir Harry Brown), who will confer with the States&lt;br /&gt;and submit proposals for the apportionment of the financial -responsibility&lt;br /&gt;between the Commonwealth and States, while the States'&lt;br /&gt;construction authorities will be consulted-regarding construction&lt;br /&gt;details." ( For earlier references, please see No. 8, page 22.)&lt;br /&gt;GLEADALL BOMB.&lt;br /&gt;On 6th December, 1941, Mr. Forde said -he had interested himself&lt;br /&gt;in a number of new bombs invented by Staff-Sergeant L. R. Gleadall,&lt;br /&gt;of Brisbane. Demonstrations had been c arried out that day. He said&lt;br /&gt;the inventions obviously possessed great merit and would fulfil the need&lt;br /&gt;for weapons which sections of fighting forces had been seeking. He was&lt;br /&gt;anxious that they be tested as soon as possible with a view to putting&lt;br /&gt;them into production. NO EXPORT OF RIFLES.&lt;br /&gt;On 10th December, 1941, Mr. Forde said-&lt;br /&gt;I " No rifles have been exported to other countries since I have been&lt;br /&gt;Minister for the Army-exc-ept to the Australian Imperial Force.&lt;br /&gt;Now, all the rifles that are beiug turned out are being used by our&lt;br /&gt;troops."&lt;br /&gt;MILITIA TRANSFERS TO AUSTRALIAN IMPERIAL FORCE.&lt;br /&gt;On 12th December, 1941, Mr. Forde referred to criticism of the&lt;br /&gt;decision to. retain in the Australian Military Forces, men who were&lt;br /&gt;desirous of enlisting for overseas service. He said that, by the calling-up&lt;br /&gt;of all units for full-time duty, the training of men who were already&lt;br /&gt;in Militia units would be carried on without a break and eventually&lt;br /&gt;they would be trained as portions of formed units. Their training&lt;br /&gt;would not be disrupted, and there would be but a deferment of the&lt;br /&gt;processes of medical examination, enlistment, and transfer to the&lt;br /&gt;Australian Imperial * Force recruit training depots, all of whida&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;normally occupied considerable time and expenditure. Men who had&lt;br /&gt;notified their desire to serve overseas were being placed on special lists&lt;br /&gt;which would be held by units, and the men would be shown as having&lt;br /&gt;been posted to the Australian Imperial Force reserve. When the&lt;br /&gt;occasion warranted, the men could be readily transferred to Australian&lt;br /&gt;Imperial Force reinforcements. The action taken was based on a&lt;br /&gt;recommnendation by the Government's military advisers in view of the&lt;br /&gt;gravity of the international situation, and was deemed to be in the&lt;br /&gt;best interests of the defence of the country, which overruled all personal&lt;br /&gt;considerations. UNIVERSITY STUDENTS.&lt;br /&gt;On 13th December, 1941, the Minister for War Organization of&lt;br /&gt;Industry ( Mr. Dedman) said that the Government's aim was to ensure&lt;br /&gt;that universities trained students in the tasks most urgently needed.&lt;br /&gt;Those completing courses essential to the war effort would not be subject&lt;br /&gt;to military service, bitt those doing unessential courses would be called&lt;br /&gt;up. ( For earlier references, please see No. 5, page 24.)&lt;br /&gt;CHRISTMAS DINNER.&lt;br /&gt;On 13th December, 1941, Mr. Forde announced that a special&lt;br /&gt;Christmas dinner would be provided for Australian troops who were&lt;br /&gt;in camps, forts or garrisons on that day. A substantial increase had&lt;br /&gt;been approved in the messing allowance for troops on Christmas Day&lt;br /&gt;so that arrangements could be made for the special meal. Hospital&lt;br /&gt;cases and convalescent men in Australia, the Middle East and Malaya&lt;br /&gt;would receive an individual Red Cross Christmas parcel.&lt;br /&gt;SEASONAL WORKERS.&lt;br /&gt;On 13th December, 1941, Mr. Forde said that men who had been&lt;br /&gt;granted leave fromn military training for harvest operations and those&lt;br /&gt;whose training ' had previously been deferred for essential work in&lt;br /&gt;connexion with timber, flax, textile and the colliery industries, would be&lt;br /&gt;rendering the utmost service to the war effort by remaining at their&lt;br /&gt;civilian occupations until, and unless, called for.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 2, page 8.)&lt;br /&gt;USE OF MILITIA OVERSEAS.&lt;br /&gt;On 15th December, 1941, Mr. Forde said-&lt;br /&gt;" The Government has no intention of sending members of the&lt;br /&gt;Australian Militia Forces to any points outside Australia except to&lt;br /&gt;Commonwealth territories or terriitories under the control of the&lt;br /&gt;Commonwealth Government. There is no necessity to do so. Members&lt;br /&gt;of the Militia Forces are enlisted for the'defence of Australia.&lt;br /&gt;Australian Imperial Force men are recruited for overseas* service.&lt;br /&gt;Members of the Militia Forces will be trained ' and used exclusively&lt;br /&gt;for the defence of Australia and its territories. They cannot he used&lt;br /&gt;for any other purpose except by an amendment of the Australian&lt;br /&gt;Defence Act-which the Government does not intend to make, because&lt;br /&gt;there is no necessity."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EXEMPTIONS FROM SERVICE.&lt;br /&gt;On 16th December, 1941, Mr. Forde said-&lt;br /&gt;A review was recently made of those exemiptions granted to Class&lt;br /&gt;I military trainees ( single men up to 35) employed in industries not&lt;br /&gt;directly associated with the war effort. In the past very, few men in&lt;br /&gt;certain trades have been called up but now that it has been decided&lt;br /&gt;to place the Militia on a war footing, it follows that m-ore skilled&lt;br /&gt;tradesmen will be called upon. That is unavoidable if efficiency in&lt;br /&gt;the Army is to be brought to its highest level. The review has been&lt;br /&gt;necessary because many units requiring tradesmen have been maintained&lt;br /&gt;previously in cadre form, but are now being brought to full strength.&lt;br /&gt;The list of reserved occupations order is still, and will continue to be,&lt;br /&gt;rigidly applied and instructions have been issued that not only men&lt;br /&gt;entitled to exemptions, but those whose training had been deferred&lt;br /&gt;by order of the Adjutant-General, to enable production of urgently&lt;br /&gt;required materials and equipment, will not be called up unless required&lt;br /&gt;to serve in their usual capacity in the forces. It is possible that many&lt;br /&gt;itien who have just been called up in Class 1 have gone over to war&lt;br /&gt;industries since they registered, and had been called up on particulars&lt;br /&gt;p~ rev'iously furnished. If it were known that they were in war&lt;br /&gt;industries they should not have becn called up. 1 emphasized that every&lt;br /&gt;mnan wvhosqe age or condition, regardless of his occupation, brought hint&lt;br /&gt;within Class 2 or Class;. 3 as defined by the proclamation of December 11,&lt;br /&gt;1941. is required to register." SEASIDE AREAS.&lt;br /&gt;On 15th December, 1941, Mr. Forde said that in any areas where&lt;br /&gt;there were forts or military establishments, strict regulations, guards&lt;br /&gt;and fences would prevent the public entering these places and he had&lt;br /&gt;no dloubt that residents would closely observe any blackout, lighting&lt;br /&gt;restriction or other necessary restrictions.&lt;br /&gt;PRISONERS OF WAR.&lt;br /&gt;RED CROSS FACILITIES.&lt;br /&gt;On 2nd Decenmber, 1941, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Forde)&lt;br /&gt;vannounced that he had authorized a contribittion of &#339; 750 to be.&lt;br /&gt;dcspatehed through the Australian Red Cross to the British Red Cross&lt;br /&gt;to provide further educational and recreational facilities for&lt;br /&gt;A ustralian prisoners in enemy countries.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 1, page 23; No. 5, page 13.)&lt;br /&gt;APPLES AND PEARS.&lt;br /&gt;ACQUISITION PLAN ADOPTED.&lt;br /&gt;On 3rd December, 1941, the Minister assisting the Minister for-&lt;br /&gt;Commerce ( Senator Fraser) said-&lt;br /&gt;" The Government has decided to acquire the apple and pear crop&lt;br /&gt;af the coming season and dispose of it on behalf of the growers. At the.&lt;br /&gt;8276-2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;seame time, the Government has decided upon certain reforms both in&lt;br /&gt;the scheme itself and in its administration. The Government was&lt;br /&gt;greatly influenced by the unanimous report of the Joint Parliamentary&lt;br /&gt;Committee which investigaited the industry, and the best means of&lt;br /&gt;supporting it during the war. The Government has been impressed by&lt;br /&gt;the fact that, although the committee found faults in both -the scheme&lt;br /&gt;and its administration, nevertheless the committee recommended continuance&lt;br /&gt;of acquisition as the best form of government intervention.&lt;br /&gt;Therefore, in spite of all difficulties and disadvantages, the Government&lt;br /&gt;has decided upon a scheme of acquisition. The Government expects&lt;br /&gt;that next year's plans will operate with much more satisfaction to&lt;br /&gt;Australia than the schemes of either of the previous years. Unless the&lt;br /&gt;Government finds reasons of governmental importance to the contrary&lt;br /&gt;at Lany time, it will adopt as a general guide--and will require the&lt;br /&gt;Marketing Board to adopt as a guide-the report and recommendations&lt;br /&gt;of the committee.&lt;br /&gt;" The ' Government earnestly hopes that, whilst affording reasonable&lt;br /&gt;compensation to producers for their fruit, the scheme -will also prove&lt;br /&gt;more beneficial to consumers. Every effort will be made to see that&lt;br /&gt;there is a wider and more efficient distribution of fruit. It is proposed&lt;br /&gt;that acquisition will commence on 1st January, 1942. In the meantime,&lt;br /&gt;details of the new plan will be worked out and necessary instructions&lt;br /&gt;given to the Maeteting Board in regard to its operation."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 9, page 9.)&lt;br /&gt;INDUSTRIAL MATTERS.&lt;br /&gt;DILUTION OF LABOUR REGULATIONS.&lt;br /&gt;On 3rd December, 1941, the Minister for Labour ( Mr. Ward)&lt;br /&gt;announced that an amendment bad been made to the National Security&lt;br /&gt;( Engineering Trades Dilution) Regulations to provide for the payment&lt;br /&gt;of full tradesmen's rates to all engineering trades apprentices in their&lt;br /&gt;fifth year of service. Under an amendment to these regulations made in&lt;br /&gt;October, 1941, it was provided that full tradesmen's rates should be&lt;br /&gt;paid to fifth-year apprentices of employers who were employing added&lt;br /&gt;engineering tradesmen. It was found in practice that the effect of&lt;br /&gt;this provision was to discourage employers from employing added&lt;br /&gt;tradesmen, as the employment of even one added tradesman would 1&lt;br /&gt;involve them in the payment of full tradesmen's rates to all their fifthrear:.&lt;br /&gt;apprentices. This was having an adverse effect on the placement&lt;br /&gt;of trainees turned out under the Commonwealth Technical Training&lt;br /&gt;Scheme. Under the regulations as now amended, all employers of&lt;br /&gt;fifth-year engineering apprentices will be placed on the same basis,&lt;br /&gt;and there will be no financial inducement to employeirs to refrain from&lt;br /&gt;co-operating in the engineering trades dilution scheme.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 2, page 14; No. 3, page 11; No.&lt;br /&gt;page 17; No. 6, page 9.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;COAL-MINING INDUSTRY.&lt;br /&gt;REGULATIONS ALTERED.&lt;br /&gt;On 3rd December, 1941, the Minister for Labour ( Mr. Ward)&lt;br /&gt;said-" I tender my thanks to the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) andi the&lt;br /&gt;Attorney-General ( Dr. Evatt) for their valuable assistance in giving&lt;br /&gt;effect to plans for improving the industrial arbitration system.-The&lt;br /&gt;Government has had under consideration for some time amendments&lt;br /&gt;to the National Security ( Coal Mining Industry Employment) Regulations&lt;br /&gt;to provide for more expeditious handling of disputes as they&lt;br /&gt;arise in order to ensure that production in this very important war&lt;br /&gt;industry shall be continuous. Many stoppages have occurred and much&lt;br /&gt;dissatisfaction has manifested itself due to delays in hearing matters&lt;br /&gt;and arriving at decisions. Experience showed that amendments of the&lt;br /&gt;existing regulations were necessary and as a result of conferences&lt;br /&gt;between Mr. Curtin, Dr. Evatt and myself, amendments were to-day&lt;br /&gt;approved to give effect to the following:-&lt;br /&gt;Extension of the powers of Local Reference Boards to enable&lt;br /&gt;them to settle any disputes as to local matters, that is, matters which&lt;br /&gt;specially affect employees in the locality in which a Board is established.&lt;br /&gt;The present power of a Local Reference Board extends only to&lt;br /&gt;settlement lby conciliation. Thc proposed provision will enable the&lt;br /&gt;Local Reference Board to hear and determine such matters. Matters&lt;br /&gt;which are not local shall be dealt with by the Central Reference Board.&lt;br /&gt;Provision is also made to provide for the appointment of a Conciliation&lt;br /&gt;Commissioner to be Acting Chairman of the Central Reference&lt;br /&gt;Board during the illness, or absence from any other cause, of the&lt;br /&gt;Chairman, providing that a Judge of the Arbitration Court is not&lt;br /&gt;available for appointment as Acting Chairman."&lt;br /&gt;REGULATIONS AMENDED&lt;br /&gt;On 16th December, 1941, the Attorney-General ( Dr. Evatt) said-&lt;br /&gt;" The Minister for Labour ( Mr. Ward) has discovered that, in a&lt;br /&gt;niumber of cases, the proceedings of Local Reference Boards under the&lt;br /&gt;National Security ( Coal-mining Industry Employment) Regulations&lt;br /&gt;have been delayed. Those regulations were recently amended to prevent&lt;br /&gt;appeals from decisions of Local Reference Boards, except where the&lt;br /&gt;board was exceeding its jurisdiction by dealing with a matter of'&lt;br /&gt;general import in the industry. At the same time, provision was made&lt;br /&gt;in the regulations to compel the chairman of the Local Reference Board&lt;br /&gt;to hold up the hearing and to refer to the Central Reference Board, at&lt;br /&gt;the instance of any member of the board; representative of employers;&lt;br /&gt;representative of employees, any question as to whether a matter was&lt;br /&gt;one of local or general application.&lt;br /&gt;" In Mr. Ward's view, this power to compel has been exercised far&lt;br /&gt;too frequently and, in the future, it is proposed that it will he in the&lt;br /&gt;( liscret-nn of the chairman of a Local Reference Board as to whether&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;any such question should be referred to the Central Referene Board,&lt;br /&gt;which will then have power to determine whether it or the Local&lt;br /&gt;Reference Board should deal with the matter. During the present&lt;br /&gt;period of crisis, Mr. Ward will take every step necessary to prevent&lt;br /&gt;industrial tribunals from being delayed in the hearing and determination&lt;br /&gt;of industrial disputes. Mr. Ward considers that the amendment&lt;br /&gt;which has been made to the regulations to make the power of chairmen&lt;br /&gt;of Local Reference Boards discretionary only, will be a factor in&lt;br /&gt;preventing delay.&lt;br /&gt;A further amendment has been made to the National Security&lt;br /&gt;( Industrial Peace) Regulations to ensure that the settlement of the&lt;br /&gt;recent dispute in the coal-mining industry with respect to annual leave,&lt;br /&gt;which was given by the Conciliation Commissioner ( Mr. D. B.&lt;br /&gt;Morrison), would not be disturbed. The amending regulation will give&lt;br /&gt;to Mr. Morrison's decision the same effect as if it had been an award of&lt;br /&gt;the Central Reference Board and his decision will not, therefore, be&lt;br /&gt;liable tobe upset by the Commonwealth Arbitration Court."*&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 1, page 14; No. 2, page 14; No. 7,&lt;br /&gt;page 18; No. 8, pages 14-15.)&lt;br /&gt;ACQUISITION OF STOCKS.&lt;br /&gt;On 12th December, 1941, the Minister for Supply ( Mr. Beasley)&lt;br /&gt;announced regulations for the compulsory acquisition of all coal stocks&lt;br /&gt;in New South Wales, and for the fixing of prices of coal throughout&lt;br /&gt;Australia as from 15th December, 194-1. The Coal -Commissioner will&lt;br /&gt;have power to-&lt;br /&gt;Terminate all existing contracts for the supply of coal to&lt;br /&gt;other States.&lt;br /&gt;Acquire by compulsion all coal at New South Wales pits&lt;br /&gt;for export to other States.&lt;br /&gt;Fix all future prices for the purchase and resale of coal.&lt;br /&gt;Limit rates of profit from all coal-mines or group of mines.&lt;br /&gt;Insist that colliery waggons be made available for the&lt;br /&gt;carriage of coal from any pit, even if it is not the pit&lt;br /&gt;of the owner of the colliery waggons.&lt;br /&gt;Fix prices for coal for consumption within New South&lt;br /&gt;Wales.&lt;br /&gt;Grade all coal into classes such as gas and tail coal, and,&lt;br /&gt;supply interstate buyers with coal of special quality&lt;br /&gt;instead of coal from certain mines.&lt;br /&gt;Pay for all coal compulsorily acquired at the average&lt;br /&gt;colliery prices ruling on 1st December, 1940, plus any&lt;br /&gt;authorized increases granted by the Prices Commissioner.&lt;br /&gt;Compel collieries to render accounts of interstate sales&lt;br /&gt;each month, so that prices can be adjusted where&lt;br /&gt;necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;COMMISSION APPOINTED.&lt;br /&gt;On 12th December, 1941, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) said-&lt;br /&gt;The Government has approved of the formation of the Coal&lt;br /&gt;Commission to control the supply, production, distribution and all other&lt;br /&gt;matters affecting coal. Members of the commission will be: Mr.&lt;br /&gt;Norman Mighell ( chairman), Mr. T. Armstrong ( representing the&lt;br /&gt;owners) and Mr. B. Cunningham ( representing the miners).&lt;br /&gt;" Arrangements have been made for the commission to survey the&lt;br /&gt;existing regulations with a view to recommending such alterations&lt;br /&gt;which it considers necessary to enable it to carry out effectively in the&lt;br /&gt;broadest sense the functions assigned to it. The matter will receive&lt;br /&gt;of the caotmetmoIinss ion is such maass rtdob induce conl fideonccree from hatltle sptuarties. ugn&lt;br /&gt;have received assurances of support and co-operation from the miners,&lt;br /&gt;and I look forward to the maximum Output and best use of coal to&lt;br /&gt;play its part in the maximum war effort."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 5, page&lt;br /&gt;ENEMY ALIENS.&lt;br /&gt;EDUCATION OF INTERNED -CHILDREN.&lt;br /&gt;On 3rd December, 1941, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Forde)&lt;br /&gt;said-The education of children of overseas internees who have been&lt;br /&gt;permitted to accompany their parents into internment is proceeding.&lt;br /&gt;Kindergarten and dining huts, equipped with diet kitchens for young&lt;br /&gt;children, and a school building for elder children, are at present in&lt;br /&gt;course of construction and will be used by children recently arrived iu&lt;br /&gt;Australia. Adult internees are also encouraged to participate in&lt;br /&gt;educational activities and some hundreds are studying a wide range&lt;br /&gt;of subjects. Over 250 have prepared themselves for the University of&lt;br /&gt;Melbourne Leaving Certificate examination. All expenses in connexion&lt;br /&gt;with overseas internees and their children are borne by the Governments&lt;br /&gt;originally responsible for their internament."&lt;br /&gt;PROPERTY REGULATIONS AMENDED.&lt;br /&gt;F On 3rd December, 1941, the Treasurer ( Mr. ' Chifley) said that a&lt;br /&gt;new Regulation under the National Security ( Enemy Property)&lt;br /&gt;Regulations had been gazetted to provide that no alteration to the&lt;br /&gt;memorandum or articles of association of an Australian company, in&lt;br /&gt;which more than 20 per cent. of the shares were held by enemy subject&lt;br /&gt;shareholders, shall become effective until approved by the Controller&lt;br /&gt;of Enemy Property. The Regulation was designed principally to protect&lt;br /&gt;the interests of shareholders in Australian companies where such&lt;br /&gt;shareholders were the subjects of a friendly or Allied power whose&lt;br /&gt;country was in enemy hands. All occupied countries were deemed to be&lt;br /&gt;" tenemy territory for purposes of the National Security ( Enemy&lt;br /&gt;Property) Regulations and technically, residents therein were enemy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;subjects It was felt, however, that the interests of these people in&lt;br /&gt;Australian companies, where such interests were sufficient to affect a&lt;br /&gt;company's policy, should not be prejudiced because of their inability.&lt;br /&gt;owing to war conditions, to exercise their rights in the normal manner.&lt;br /&gt;The new Regulation safeguarded those rights.&lt;br /&gt;LAND TRANSFER REGULATIONS.&lt;br /&gt;On 16th December, 1941, the Attorney-General ( Dr. Evatt)&lt;br /&gt;announced that by an amendment of the National Security ( Land&lt;br /&gt;Transfer) Regulations former subjects of Finland, Hungary, Rumania&lt;br /&gt;and Japan, who were naturalized British subjects, were regarded as&lt;br /&gt;naturalized persons of enemy origin. The sale of land to such persons,&lt;br /&gt;and other land transactions with such persons, was prohibited exceptf&lt;br /&gt;with the prior consent of the Attorney-General. Subjects of the&lt;br /&gt;countries mentioned who were not naturalized were enemy aliens and&lt;br /&gt;the sale of land to them,. and other land transactions with them,&lt;br /&gt;was absolutely prohibited. TRANSPORT.&lt;br /&gt;REGULATIONS MADE.&lt;br /&gt;On 3rd December, 1941, the Minister for Transport ( Mr. Lawson)&lt;br /&gt;gazetted regulations providing for the control of rail transport by the&lt;br /&gt;Commonwealth to ensure the best possible use of the facilities in&lt;br /&gt;emergency. A committee, to be known as the War Railways Committee.&lt;br /&gt;will be formed to advise and assist the Minister in the administration&lt;br /&gt;of the regulations. It will consist of the chief executive officers of the&lt;br /&gt;Commonwealth and State railways systems. The chairman will be&lt;br /&gt;appointed by the Minister. The regulations provide the necessary&lt;br /&gt;power to conduct the essential services for defence and civil purposes&lt;br /&gt;without restriction.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 4, page 14; No. 5, page 12.)&lt;br /&gt;VOLUNTEER DEFENCE CORPS.&lt;br /&gt;EQUIPMENT ISTRIBUTION.&lt;br /&gt;On 3rd December, 1941, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Forde) I&lt;br /&gt;said-"' Sufficient mortars have been distributed among the various centres&lt;br /&gt;in which the Volunteer Defence -Corps is operating to ensure a full&lt;br /&gt;issue. The rate of rifle issue is being maintained at the highest&lt;br /&gt;possible; level. Any increase will depend largely on the numbers&lt;br /&gt;obtained -by impressment. A growing factory output will ensure&lt;br /&gt;supplies of light machine guns. Sub-machine guns will also be distributed.&lt;br /&gt;Approximately 11,000 uniforms have been distributed and&lt;br /&gt;more are being issued as rapidly as possible; production is rising and&lt;br /&gt;a full issue is not far distant."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 6, page 23.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FULL-TIME DUTY PERSONNEL.&lt;br /&gt;On 5th December, 1941, the Prime Minister. ( Mr. Curtin) said-&lt;br /&gt;Approval was given by War Cabinet to-day to the employment of&lt;br /&gt;full-time duty personnel with the Volunteer Defence Corps. It was&lt;br /&gt;decided that, for the proper administration of the corps, full-time duty&lt;br /&gt;personnel should be employed, totalling 29 captains, 73 lieutenants and&lt;br /&gt;175 warrant and non-commissioned officers. The work of organization&lt;br /&gt;and administration has been carried out voluntarily, and in their spare&lt;br /&gt;time, * by members but, with the increased volume of work now to be&lt;br /&gt;handled and the vital part the corps may be called upon to play in&lt;br /&gt;Autralia's defence, it is no longer possible to depend on purely&lt;br /&gt;vla ry services. The appointment of full-time duty personnel will&lt;br /&gt;permit of the proper issue of, and accounting for, uniforms, equipment&lt;br /&gt;and training stores and will assist commanding officers in the training&lt;br /&gt;of units and the keeping of records and compilation of data required in&lt;br /&gt;connexion with the employment of the corps on mobilization."&lt;br /&gt;CALL-UP FOR SERVICE.&lt;br /&gt;On 13th December, 1941, Mr. Forde said-&lt;br /&gt;" Portions of the Volunteer Defence Corps will be called up for&lt;br /&gt;coast-watching and for defence of aerodromes. They will receive the&lt;br /&gt;same rates of pay as the Militia Forces. Arrangements are in progress&lt;br /&gt;for the calling-tip of these men. They will be drawn as far as possible&lt;br /&gt;from the areas in which their services will be used."&lt;br /&gt;FAR EASTERN POSITION.&lt;br /&gt;WAR CABINET MEETING.&lt;br /&gt;On 4th December, 1941, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) said-&lt;br /&gt;" War Cabinet, in consultation with the Chiefs of Staff, reviewed&lt;br /&gt;the preparedness of the Navy, Army and Air Force for any emergency.&lt;br /&gt;The precautionary steps that have been taken to meet any contingency&lt;br /&gt;that may arise were examined and . authority given for further&lt;br /&gt;essential measures, if and when, they should become necessary."&lt;br /&gt;AUSTRALIAN WAR EFFORT AND CAPACITY.&lt;br /&gt;APPOINTM1ENTS MADE.&lt;br /&gt;On 15th Decembet, 1941, the Minister for War Organization of&lt;br /&gt;Industry ( Mr. Dedman) announced further appointments of his&lt;br /&gt;department, Professor Ronald Walker of the University; of Hobart to be&lt;br /&gt;Chief Economic Adviser to the Department, the Chief Inspector, Personnel,&lt;br /&gt;Postmaster-General's Department ( Mr. G. T. Chippindall) to&lt;br /&gt;be Deputy-Director, Department of War Organization of -Industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;APPOINTMENT OF SCIENTISTS.&lt;br /&gt;On 11th December, 1941, Mr. Dedman said that two scientists were&lt;br /&gt;to be selected, having regard to their knowledge of industry and science,&lt;br /&gt;to spend about three months studying the position relative to the&lt;br /&gt;utilization of the scientific resources of the country in the war effort,&lt;br /&gt;by consultation with a few leaders in charge of war activities. These&lt;br /&gt;men would then submit to the Prime Minister proposals for making&lt;br /&gt;fuller use of such scientific help as was available in the country, and&lt;br /&gt;was unused. AIR RAID PRECAUTIONS.&lt;br /&gt;RESPIRATORS FOR CIVIL POPULATION.&lt;br /&gt;On 5th December, 1941, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) said-&lt;br /&gt;War Cabinet to-day discussed the matter of provision of respirators&lt;br /&gt;for use by the civil population of Australia in the event of gas&lt;br /&gt;attacks. It was decided to place an order in the United Kingdom for&lt;br /&gt;the supply of 1,000,000 respirator containers and that the Australian&lt;br /&gt;Department of Munitions commence, at the earliest possible date, the&lt;br /&gt;manufacture of the face-pieces for these containers at the rate of&lt;br /&gt;40,000 a week. Arrangements will be mnade by the Department of Home&lt;br /&gt;Security for the storage of containers and face-pieces and their assembly&lt;br /&gt;snd issue when required. The Department of Munitions will collsborate&lt;br /&gt;on the technical side of these matters and War Cabinet will later&lt;br /&gt;deal with the question of local production of the complete units. It&lt;br /&gt;is estimated that the provision of 1,000,000 units will cost &#339; 300,000."'&lt;br /&gt;COMPENSATION FOR VOLUNTEERS.&lt;br /&gt;On 16th December, 1941, the Minister for Home Security ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;Lazzarini) announced National Security ( Civil Defence Volunteers'&lt;br /&gt;Compensation) Regulations providing a scheme of compensation and/ or&lt;br /&gt;pension for Civil Defence Volunteers who were members of civil&lt;br /&gt;defence organizations approved by the Minister, who would administer&lt;br /&gt;the regulations. Members who sustained personal injuries in the course&lt;br /&gt;of training would beneifit under the scheme and allowances for&lt;br /&gt;dependants were provided. All claims would be handled by the&lt;br /&gt;Repatriation Commission. BULK OIL INSTALLATIONS.&lt;br /&gt;On 17th December, 1941, Mr. Lazzarini announced National&lt;br /&gt;Security ( Protection of Bulk Oil Installations) Regulations to vest in&lt;br /&gt;the Minister authority to require owners of bulk oil installations to&lt;br /&gt;take protective measures in connexion with those installations and to&lt;br /&gt;furnish reports in relstion to protective measures. Provision was made&lt;br /&gt;for the constitution of a Bulk Oil Protection Advisory Committee.&lt;br /&gt;Before the erection of any bulk oil installations was commenced, the&lt;br /&gt;consent in writing of the Minister shall be obtained.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 6, page 4; No. 7, page&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE.&lt;br /&gt;QANTAS EMPIRE AIRWAYS.&lt;br /&gt;On 5th December, 1941, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) said-&lt;br /&gt;" War Cabinet to-day agreed to a request by Qantas Empire Airways&lt;br /&gt;Limited for the return of one flying boat, of those chartered by&lt;br /&gt;the Royal Australian Air Force from the company, as soon as the&lt;br /&gt;Chief of the Air Farce Staff can arrange for the return. The machine&lt;br /&gt;will be requisitioned, if required in an emergency, during the two&lt;br /&gt;months of the period of return that has been approved."&lt;br /&gt;WOMEN DOCTORS APPROVED.&lt;br /&gt;On 5th December, 1941, Mr. Curtin said-&lt;br /&gt;" War Cabinet to-day gave approval to the employment in the&lt;br /&gt;Royal Australian Air Force medical service of women doctors, not&lt;br /&gt;exceeding a total of eight. They will be paid the rates of pay and&lt;br /&gt;allowances applicable to male doctors holding the corresponding rank.&lt;br /&gt;The duties of the new appointees will include clinical pathology at&lt;br /&gt;hospitals and general work at stations where members of the Women's&lt;br /&gt;Auxiliary Australian Air Force are accommodated. Cabinet's decision&lt;br /&gt;was prompted by the difficulty being experienced in meeting the medical&lt;br /&gt;officer requirements of the services."&lt;br /&gt;LEAVE CANCELLED.&lt;br /&gt;OA 5th December, 1941, the Minister for Air ( Mr. Drakeford) said&lt;br /&gt;that leave for Royal Australian Air Force personnel at Darwin had&lt;br /&gt;been cancelled for the present. This action had been taken some time&lt;br /&gt;ago when the Far Eastern position began to deteriorate.&lt;br /&gt;AIR-ARMY GO-OPERATION.&lt;br /&gt;On 10th December, 1941, the Minister for Air ( Mr. Drakeford)&lt;br /&gt;I said that the school of army co-operation, providing a basis for closer&lt;br /&gt;collaboration between the Air Force and the Army, to be established in&lt;br /&gt;Canberra early in the new year, would be under the control of Wing-&lt;br /&gt;Commander S. de B. Griffiths, Commanding Officer, Royal Australian&lt;br /&gt;Air Force Station, Canberra, pending the arrival in Australia of a&lt;br /&gt;Royal Air Force air-army co-operation expert. Squad ron-Leader G. J.&lt;br /&gt;Quinan, commander of an Australian army co-operation squadron,&lt;br /&gt;would assist the chief instructor. Army instructors would be Major&lt;br /&gt;H. M. Ervine-Andrews, the first V. C. winner of the present war, and&lt;br /&gt;Major T. F. Howeison, of the Australian Armoured Division. A comprehensive&lt;br /&gt;syllabus had been arranged by Air-Commodore F. M. Bladin,&lt;br /&gt;Air Officer Commanding Royal Australian Air Force Operational&lt;br /&gt;Area, and Colonel E. L. Vowles, Acting Director of Military Training.&lt;br /&gt;( Far earlier references, please see No. 1, page 15; No. 6, page 23; No. 7,&lt;br /&gt;pages 11-12.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWARDS FOR GALLANTRY.&lt;br /&gt;On l3th December, 1941, Mr. Drakeford received advice that&lt;br /&gt;Squadron-Leader C. Rawlinson had been awarded a bar to his Distinguished&lt;br /&gt;Flying Gross, and Flight-Lieutenant D. A. Coke and Flying-&lt;br /&gt;Officer F. Fischer had won the Distinguished Flying Cross for outstanding&lt;br /&gt;bravery in the Libyan campaign.&lt;br /&gt;On 17th December, 1941, Mr. Drakeford said-&lt;br /&gt;" Flight-Lieutenant C. R. Caldwel], who is serving in a Royal&lt;br /&gt;Australian Air Force squadron operating in Libya, has been simultaneously&lt;br /&gt;awarded the Distinguished Flying Cross and bar for outstanding&lt;br /&gt;bravery. MOVEMENTS OF PERSONNEL.&lt;br /&gt;On 15th December, 1941, Mr. Drakeford said the Government did&lt;br /&gt;not intend to disclose, at this stage, its intentions regarding the future&lt;br /&gt;of the Royal Australian Air Force personnel serving outside the&lt;br /&gt;Pacific as to do* so would be gratuitously to supply the enemy with&lt;br /&gt;valuable operational information.&lt;br /&gt;REINFORCEMENTS IN MALAYA.&lt;br /&gt;On 15th December, 1941, Mr. Drakeford said-&lt;br /&gt;Everything possible is being done-to maintain and, if necessary,&lt;br /&gt;reinforce our air strength in the Malayan battle zone. Any action&lt;br /&gt;taken by the Government to supply reinforcements for sectors outside&lt;br /&gt;the sphere of Australian operations is, and will continue to be, consistent&lt;br /&gt;with the protection of vital homie points from which our fighting forces&lt;br /&gt;receive their supplies of war materials and from which flow the commodities&lt;br /&gt;essential to the life of the community."&lt;br /&gt;IMPORTS.&lt;br /&gt;RESTRICTIONS ON STERLING GOODS.&lt;br /&gt;On 6th Decemb * er, 1941, the Minister for Trade and Customs&lt;br /&gt;( Senator Keane) announced the introduction, as from 8th December,&lt;br /&gt;1941, of restrictions on the importation of a wide range of goods from&lt;br /&gt;the United Kingdom and all other countries of the sterling area except&lt;br /&gt;New Zealand and British and French Pacific Islands. Mainly the&lt;br /&gt;goods are regarded as being unnece . ssary during wartime. In the case&lt;br /&gt;of raw cotton and. tobacco leaf it has been found necessary to apply&lt;br /&gt;the import licensing principles to all sterling areas.&lt;br /&gt;HIS HIGHNESS THE RAJAH OF SARAWAK.&lt;br /&gt;Ohi 10th December, 1941, the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr.&lt;br /&gt;Evatt) announced that His Highness the Rajah of Sarawak ( Sir&lt;br /&gt;Charles Vyner Brooke,, had arrived at Brisbane that day.&lt;br /&gt;He had been requested by His Highness that the visit should be&lt;br /&gt;regarded entirely as a private one. In that circumstance, no undue&lt;br /&gt;publicity should be given to the visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AIRCRAFT PRODUCTION.&lt;br /&gt;AUSTRALIAN DESIGNED RIVETING GUN.&lt;br /&gt;On 10th December, 1941, the Minister for Air ( Mr. Drakeford)&lt;br /&gt;said that Flight-Sergeant E. A. Lee, of Royal Australian Air Force&lt;br /&gt;Head-quarters, had designed a new and improved type of automatic&lt;br /&gt;riveting gun used in the construction of metal aeroplanes and _ parts&lt;br /&gt;which was being produced by Royal Australian Air Force trainees at&lt;br /&gt;No. 1 Engineering School, Ascot Vale ( Victoria). The Lee riveting&lt;br /&gt;gun was more efficient, easier to handle and much faster in operation&lt;br /&gt;than the imported Chobert gun, and could be made at a fraction of the&lt;br /&gt;cost. It was estimated that the Australian gun could be manufactured&lt;br /&gt;by the Royal Australian Air Force for a few shillings, compared with&lt;br /&gt;approximately &#339; 4 if produced privately, and &#339; 50 if imported.&lt;br /&gt;AUSTRALIAN-MADE BOMB RACKS.&lt;br /&gt;On 13th December, 1941, Mr. Drakeford announced that universal&lt;br /&gt;bomb racks, capable of holding all types of bombs used by Royal&lt;br /&gt;Australian Air Force machines, were now being manufactured in&lt;br /&gt;Australia. The Pacific conflict would make it increasingly difficult to&lt;br /&gt;import bomb racks from Britain.&lt;br /&gt;MUNITIONS PRODUCTION.&lt;br /&gt;CHECK ON ENLISTMENTS.&lt;br /&gt;On 11th December, 1941, the Minister for Munitions ( Mr. Makin)&lt;br /&gt;said that conferences -had recently been held between the Prime Minister&lt;br /&gt;( Mr. Curtin), the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Forde) and representatives&lt;br /&gt;of the Amalgamated Engineering Union to establish a more&lt;br /&gt;satisfactory basis for the employment of technicians in munitions&lt;br /&gt;factories, having regard to the essential requirements of the Army. A&lt;br /&gt;review of this question, which was at present proceeding, would check&lt;br /&gt;any wastage or inefficiency in the allotment of skilled workers to the&lt;br /&gt;services. WAR CABINET.&lt;br /&gt;On 11th December, 1941, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) said-&lt;br /&gt;I have to-day appointed the Minister for War Organization of&lt;br /&gt;Industry ( Mr. Dedman) to be a member of the War Cabinet."&lt;br /&gt;TEXTILE TRADE.&lt;br /&gt;COTTON GOODS " FROZEN&lt;br /&gt;On 11th December, 1941, the Minister for Supply ( Mr. Beasley)&lt;br /&gt;said that because of excessive buying recently, existing stocks of engine&lt;br /&gt;cotton cleaning waste, cotton cloths, stockinette and sundry cleaning&lt;br /&gt;cloths had been frozen from that day. Future sales would be&lt;br /&gt;prohibited to people holding more than one month's supply based on&lt;br /&gt;1940 usage. People with less may buy up to 1 ton or 14 days 1940&lt;br /&gt;usage, whichever was the lesser.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 4, page 9.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VOCATIONAL TRAI NI NG.&lt;br /&gt;REPORT TO CABINET.&lt;br /&gt;On 12th December, 1941, the Minister for Repatriation ( Mr. Frost)&lt;br /&gt;said that the Cabinet sub-committee, comprising the Minister for&lt;br /&gt;Health and Social Services ( Mr. Holloway), the Minister for Labour&lt;br /&gt;( Mr. Ward) and the Minister for Repatriation ( Mr. Frost), recently&lt;br /&gt;appointed to consider proposals regarding general repatriation benefits&lt;br /&gt;for members of the forces would report to Cabinet shortly. Questions&lt;br /&gt;referred for consideration were preference for returned soldiers and&lt;br /&gt;vocational training for those members eligible under the present&lt;br /&gt;Repatriation Act. In view of the changed Pacific situation, the further&lt;br /&gt;question arose as to the scope of the act. At present it provided,&lt;br /&gt;so far as general benefits were concerned, for those ' who enlisted for&lt;br /&gt;service abroad, but events might lead to an amendment of the act to&lt;br /&gt;cover members of the Australian Military Forces enlisted, or called up,&lt;br /&gt;for home defence only.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 2, page 10; No. 6, page 6.)&lt;br /&gt;DEPARTMENT OF INFORMATION.&lt;br /&gt;RUMORS DISCOUNTED.&lt;br /&gt;On 12th December, 1941, the Minister for Information ( Senator&lt;br /&gt;Ashley) appealed to the public to take no notice of rumors and to regard&lt;br /&gt;only official statements as authoritative. These would be issued as early&lt;br /&gt;as possible, and as frequently as was thought necessary. The Government's&lt;br /&gt;considered policy was promptly to release news which affected&lt;br /&gt;the operations of the forces whether it was good or bad.&lt;br /&gt;RELATIONS WITH AMERICA.&lt;br /&gt;DEMAND FOR AUSTRALIAN NEWS.&lt;br /&gt;On 12th December, 1941, the Minister for Information ( Senator&lt;br /&gt;Ashley) said that one of the results of the new Pacific situation was the&lt;br /&gt;tremendous increase of American interest in Australia. The Department&lt;br /&gt;of Information was doing everything possible to meet this new&lt;br /&gt;demand for news and information from Australia. In particular, the&lt;br /&gt;broadcasting division was transmitting on short-wave each evening to&lt;br /&gt;America a ten-minute news bulletin.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 3, page 13.)&lt;br /&gt;PRICES.&lt;br /&gt;FIRM DECLARED&lt;br /&gt;On 12th December, 1941, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Keane)&lt;br /&gt;said that all services performed by the Parisian Laundry Proprietary&lt;br /&gt;Limited, 118-120 Oxford-street, Woollahra ( New South Wales), had&lt;br /&gt;been brought under strict price control by a declaration. Action had&lt;br /&gt;been taken because the firm increased the prices charged on a large&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;section of its business after it had been advised by the New South&lt;br /&gt;Wales Deputy Prices Commissioner that it would be necessary to make&lt;br /&gt;application and justify any increases before putting them into effect.&lt;br /&gt;All firms should realize that instructions from Deputy Prices Commissioners&lt;br /&gt;should be strictly followed or immediate steps be taken by&lt;br /&gt;the trader concerned to discuss any difficulties with the Deputy Prices&lt;br /&gt;Commissioner. ( For earlier references, please see No. 6, page 14; No. 7, pages 21-22; No. 9,&lt;br /&gt;page 3.)&lt;br /&gt;SOCIAL SECURITY.&lt;br /&gt;PENSIONERS IN EMPLOYMENT.&lt;br /&gt;On 12th December, 1941, the Minister for Social Services ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;Holloway) said-&lt;br /&gt;Any old-age penlsioner who enters employment should immediately&lt;br /&gt;inform the Deputy Commissioner of Pensions at the capital city in&lt;br /&gt;which he resides. By so doing, overpayments of pensions may be prevented&lt;br /&gt;and the difficulties invariably attendant upon refunds will be&lt;br /&gt;obviated. If the work proved beyond the pensioner's capacity or ceases&lt;br /&gt;for any other reason, no difficulties will be raised in restoring pension&lt;br /&gt;payments from an appropriate date."&lt;br /&gt;BARLEY POOL.&lt;br /&gt;1941-42 CROP FIRST ADVANCE.&lt;br /&gt;On 15th December, 1941, the Minister for Commerce ( Mr. Scully)&lt;br /&gt;said that the Government ' had approved of advances totalling about&lt;br /&gt;&#339; 1,000,000 to barley-growers as the first advance to be made on barley&lt;br /&gt;of the 1941-42 crop. The money would be made available by the&lt;br /&gt;Commonwealth Bank, which would also provide &#339;. 700,000 for expenses&lt;br /&gt;incurred iii the administration of the pool. All advances were less&lt;br /&gt;an average freight of 34d. a bushel. The Australian Barley Fool Board&lt;br /&gt;was conferring with the Commronwealth Bank regarding machinery&lt;br /&gt;measures necessary for payment. It was anticipated that these&lt;br /&gt;arrangements would be completed to enable payment to be made&lt;br /&gt;towards the end of this month. Production this year had been a record&lt;br /&gt;and, in view of the serious limitation of export, it was estimated that a&lt;br /&gt;substantial loss would result from this year's pool.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 4, page 13.)&lt;br /&gt;OWEN SUB-MACHINE GUN.&lt;br /&gt;NUMBER MANUFACTURED.&lt;br /&gt;On 16th December, 1941, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Forde)&lt;br /&gt;said-A substantial number of Owen guns have already been manufactured.&lt;br /&gt;I have received a photograph showing a long line of these&lt;br /&gt;new sub-machine guns."&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 8, page 13.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WAR WITH FINLAND, HUNGARY, RUMANIA.&lt;br /&gt;PROCLAMATION.&lt;br /&gt;Commonwealth of By Es Excellency the G-overnor-4leneral&lt;br /&gt;Australia to wit, in and-over the Commonwealth of&lt;br /&gt;Gowaia Australia.&lt;br /&gt;Governor-General.&lt;br /&gt;jALEXANDER GORE A. RKWRIGILT, BA-RON G-OWRIE, the&lt;br /&gt;Governor-General aforesaid, acting with the advice of the Federal&lt;br /&gt;Executive Council and in the exercise of all powers me thereunto&lt;br /&gt;enabling, do hereby declare and proclaim that a state of war with the&lt;br /&gt;Republic of Finland, the Kingdom of Hungary and the Kingdom of&lt;br /&gt;Rumania exists and-has existed in the Commonwealth of Australia and&lt;br /&gt;its Territories as from the eighth day of December, One thousand nine&lt;br /&gt;hundred and forty-one at five o'clock in the a-fternoon reckoned&lt;br /&gt;according to the standard time in the Australian -Capital Territory:&lt;br /&gt;OF ALL WHICH His Majesty's loving subjects and all others&lt;br /&gt;whom these Presents may concern are hereby required to take notice&lt;br /&gt;and to govern themselves accordingly.&lt;br /&gt;Given under my Hand and the Seal of the Commonwealth of&lt;br /&gt;Australia this eighth day of December in the year of our&lt;br /&gt;Lord One thousand nine hundred and forty-one and in the&lt;br /&gt;fifth year of His Majesty's reign.&lt;br /&gt;By His Excellency's Command, JOEHN OURTIN Prime Minister.&lt;br /&gt;GOD SAVE THlE KING!&lt;br /&gt;WAR WITH JAPAN.&lt;br /&gt;PRIME MINISTER'S STATEMENT.&lt;br /&gt;( On 7th December, 1941, Japan attacked United States territory.)&lt;br /&gt;On 8th December, 1941, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) said-&lt;br /&gt;" The thread by which peace was hanging has -been snapped,&lt;br /&gt;notwithstanding all the discussions and negotiations which the~&lt;br /&gt;democracies persisted with in the hope that peace would be maintained.&lt;br /&gt;Japan has gonc -to war and it is necessary to point out that, prior tc&lt;br /&gt;formal declaration of war, Japan wantonly assailed British and United&lt;br /&gt;States interests and places.&lt;br /&gt;For weeks past, peace in the Pacific has been hanging by a thread.&lt;br /&gt;The question was: Would Japan snap the thread? For no other&lt;br /&gt;country which could have made war in the Pacific desired war. Since&lt;br /&gt;February of. this year the problem of the Pacific has been one of&lt;br /&gt;constant anxiety to the Government of Australia and to the governments&lt;br /&gt;of the democracies.&lt;br /&gt;Hit without warning brings its own retaliation. Men and women&lt;br /&gt;of Australia: The stern truth is that Japan commenced. a war in the&lt;br /&gt;Pacific in which our security and our vital int-. ests are at stake. I ask&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the people of Australia to give the best that they can in the service of&lt;br /&gt;this country. The fighting forces are a t battle stations. Every otheir&lt;br /&gt;man and woman should be at some place of usefulness.&lt;br /&gt;" The Australian Government has taken immediate steps this&lt;br /&gt;morning, according to plan, to do everything necessary. for the defence&lt;br /&gt;of Australian, British and United States interests. Thb Service&lt;br /&gt;Ministers and the Service Chiefs have acted promptly, as have other&lt;br /&gt;departments connected with internal Security. No time was lost&lt;br /&gt;from the moment, early this morning when the news was received, in&lt;br /&gt;taking all necessary measures.&lt;br /&gt;This is the gravest hour of our history. We have a heavy&lt;br /&gt;responsibility. I ask every Australian, man -and woman, to go about&lt;br /&gt;their allotted task with full vigor and courage."~&lt;br /&gt;PROCLAMATION.&lt;br /&gt;Commonwealth of By This Excellency the Governor-General&lt;br /&gt;Australia to wit. in and-over the Commonwealth of&lt;br /&gt;Gowuni Australia.&lt;br /&gt;Governor-General.&lt;br /&gt;IALEXANDER GORE ARKWRIGHT, BARON GOWRIE, the&lt;br /&gt;SGovernor-General aforesaid, acting with the advice of the Federal&lt;br /&gt;Executive Council and in the exercise of all poweirs me thereunto&lt;br /&gt;enabling, do hereby decla-re and proclaim that a state of war with the&lt;br /&gt;Japanese Empire exists and has existed in the -Commonwealth of&lt;br /&gt;Australia . and its Territories as from the eighth day of December, One&lt;br /&gt;thousand nine hundred and forty-one at five o'clock in the afternoon&lt;br /&gt;reckoned -according to the standard time in the Australian Capital&lt;br /&gt;Territory: OF ALL WHICH His Majesty's loving subjects and all others&lt;br /&gt;whom these P-resents may concern are hereby required to take notice&lt;br /&gt;and to govern themselves accordingly.&lt;br /&gt;Given under my Hand and the Seal -of the Commonwealth of&lt;br /&gt;Australia this ninth day of December in the year of Our&lt;br /&gt;Lord One thousand nine hundred -and forty-one and in the&lt;br /&gt;-fifth year of His Majesty's reign.&lt;br /&gt;By His Excellency's Command, JOHN OCURTIN Prime Minister.&lt;br /&gt;GOD SAVE THE KNI&lt;br /&gt;NATIONAL BROADCAST BY PRIME MINISTER.&lt;br /&gt;On 8th December, 1941, in a national broadcast, Mr. Curtin said:&lt;br /&gt;Men and women of Australia,,&lt;br /&gt;We are at war with Japan. That has happened because, in the&lt;br /&gt;first instance, Japanese naval and air forces launched an unprovoked&lt;br /&gt;attack on British and United States territory; because our vital&lt;br /&gt;interests are imperilled and because the rights of free people in the&lt;br /&gt;whole Pacific are assailed. As a result, the Australian Government&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this afternoon took the necessary steps which will mean that a&lt;br /&gt;state of war exists between Australia and Japan. To-morrow, in&lt;br /&gt;common with the United Kingdom, the United States and the Netherlands&lt;br /&gt;East Indies Governments, the Australian Government will&lt;br /&gt;formally and solemnly declare the state of war it has striven so sincerely&lt;br /&gt;and strenuously to avoid.&lt;br /&gt;Throughout the whole affair, and despite discouragement, the&lt;br /&gt;Australian Government and its representatives abroad struggled hard&lt;br /&gt;to prevent a breakdown of discussions. Australia encouraged the&lt;br /&gt;United States to retain the diplomatic initiative on behalf of the&lt;br /&gt;democratic Powers. We did not want war in the Pacific. The&lt;br /&gt;Australian Government has repeatedly made it clear-as have the&lt;br /&gt;Governments of the United Kingdom, the United States and the&lt;br /&gt;Netherlands East Indies-that if war came to the Pacific it. would be&lt;br /&gt;of Japan's making. Japan has now made war.&lt;br /&gt;" I point out that the hands of the democracies are clean. The&lt;br /&gt;discussions and negotiations which have taken place between Japan&lt;br /&gt;and the democracies were not merely empty bandying of words on&lt;br /&gt;the democracies' part. Since last February it has been the constant&lt;br /&gt;aim and endeavour of the democracies to keep peace in the Pacific.&lt;br /&gt;It has been a problem fraught with grave difficulties but, in the&lt;br /&gt;view of the democracies, it was a problem that was capable of being&lt;br /&gt;overcome. Accordingly, the best brains of the democracies were&lt;br /&gt;brought to bear on the problem. It will stand on record that the&lt;br /&gt;President of the United States himself, the American Secretary of&lt;br /&gt;State ( Mr. Cordell Hull), the British and the Dominion Governments&lt;br /&gt;worked untiringly and unceasingly. Yet, when the President of the&lt;br /&gt;United States had decided to communicate direct to the Japanese&lt;br /&gt;Emperor a personal appeal for Imperial intervention on the side&lt;br /&gt;of peace, the war Government of Japan struck. That war Government,&lt;br /&gt;set on aggression and lusting for power in the . same fashion&lt;br /&gt;as its Axis partners, anticipated thie undoubted weight of the&lt;br /&gt;President's plea and shattered the century-old friendship between&lt;br /&gt;the two countries.&lt;br /&gt;For the first time in the history of the Pacific, armed conflict&lt;br /&gt;stalks abroad. No other country but Japan desired war in the&lt;br /&gt;Pacific. The guilt for plunging this hemisphere into actual warfare is,&lt;br /&gt;therefore, upon Japan. The recapitulation of events I have given you&lt;br /&gt;is necessary so that we in Australia may correctly assess the issues&lt;br /&gt;involved. The stern truth is that war has been forced upon us, not&lt;br /&gt;because of stubborn resistance on the part of the democracies to every&lt;br /&gt;demand that Japan made, but because Japan chose the method of&lt;br /&gt;armed might to settle differences which every other country involved&lt;br /&gt;was ready and willing to settle by negotiation and arbitration. Japan,&lt;br /&gt;by so doing, chose the Hitler method. While its diplomatic representatives&lt;br /&gt;were actually at the White House; while all the democratic&lt;br /&gt;Powers regarded the conversations as continuing; Japan ignored the&lt;br /&gt;convention of a formal declaration of war and struck like an assassasin&lt;br /&gt;in the night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For, as the dawn broke this morning, at places as far apart as&lt;br /&gt;Honolulu, Nauru, Ocean Island, Guam, Singapore' and British Malaya,&lt;br /&gt;guns from Japanese warships; bombs from Japanese aircraft; shots&lt;br /&gt;from Japanese military forces struck death to United States citizens&lt;br /&gt;and members of its defence forces; to the peaceful subjects of Great&lt;br /&gt;Britain and to her men on ships and on the land. The Pacific Ocean&lt;br /&gt;was reddened with the blood of Japanese victims. These wanton&lt;br /&gt;killings will be followed by attacks on the Netherlands East Indies;&lt;br /&gt;on the Commonwealth of Australia; on the Dominion of New Zealand;&lt;br /&gt;if Japan can get its brutal way.&lt;br /&gt;Australia, therefore, being a nation that believes in a way of&lt;br /&gt;life whichb has freedom and liberty as its corner stones goes to the&lt;br /&gt;battle stations in defence of the free way of living. Our course is&lt;br /&gt;clear, our cause is just-as has been the case ever since September,&lt;br /&gt;1939, when we stood in the path of IHitlerism and declared that we&lt;br /&gt;would stand out to the end against ruthless an ' d wanton aggression.&lt;br /&gt;I say, then, to the people of Australia: Give of your best in the&lt;br /&gt;service of the nation. There is a place and part for all of us. Each&lt;br /&gt;must take his or her place in the service of the nation, for the nation&lt;br /&gt;itself is in peril. This is our darkest hour. Let that be fully realized.&lt;br /&gt;Our efforts in the -past two years must be as nothing compared with&lt;br /&gt;the efforts we must now put forward.&lt;br /&gt;" I can give you the assurance that the Australian Government is&lt;br /&gt;fully prepared. It has ' been in readiness for whatever eventuality, and&lt;br /&gt;last Friday the initial steps were taken and fully car. ried out. From&lt;br /&gt;early this morning the Service Ministers of the Cabinet and the Chiefs&lt;br /&gt;of the fighting Services have done everything that has to -be done by&lt;br /&gt;them. The War Cabinet met and put into effect the plan devised for&lt;br /&gt;our protection. This afternoon, the full Cabinet met and I am able&lt;br /&gt;to announce to you prompt decisions on a : wide variety of mattersall&lt;br /&gt;of them vital to the new war organization that confronts us.&lt;br /&gt;All leave for members of the fighting Forces has been cancelled.&lt;br /&gt;An extension of the present partial mobilization of Navy, Army and&lt;br /&gt;Air Forces is being prepared. The Minister for Home Security will,&lt;br /&gt;to-morrow, confer with Army authorities on air' raid precautions.&lt;br /&gt;Regulations will be issued to prohibit the consumption of petrol for&lt;br /&gt;purposes of pleasure. A conference will. be held ' by the Minister for&lt;br /&gt;Supply, with oil companies on ' the storage of fuel and the security of&lt;br /&gt;that storage. Arrangements will be made for all work on services that&lt;br /&gt;are essential nationally to be continued on public holidays in future,&lt;br /&gt;while, in this connexion, all transport services will be concentrated&lt;br /&gt;upon necessary purposes. The Minister for Labour will leave for&lt;br /&gt;Darwin immediately to organize the labour supply there. An&lt;br /&gt;examination will . be made to ascertain what retail establishments&lt;br /&gt;should continue to trade after 6 p. m.-so, as to conserve light, coal,&lt;br /&gt;transport services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;" These are some of the things decided upon quickly, but in no&lt;br /&gt;atmosphere of panic. There are other things that the Government&lt;br /&gt;has done. These, by their nature, are secret. But, in total, what has&lt;br /&gt;been done to-day adds up to complete provision for the safety of the&lt;br /&gt;nation. " Tb-morrow, the War Cabinet will meet again, as will the Australian&lt;br /&gt;War -Council, when the Leader of the Opposition and his&lt;br /&gt;colleagues will -be fully appraised of every phase of the position. The&lt;br /&gt;Parliament of the -Commonwealth will assemble on Tuesday of next&lt;br /&gt;week. " One thing remains, and on it depends our very lives. That thing&lt;br /&gt;is the co-operation, the strength, and the will-power of you, the people.&lt;br /&gt;Without it we are, indeed, lost. Men and women of Australia: The&lt;br /&gt;call is to you, for your courage; your physical and mental ability; your&lt;br /&gt;inflexible determination that we, as a nation of free people, shall&lt;br /&gt;survive. My appeal to you is in the name of Australia, for Australia&lt;br /&gt;is the stake in this conflict. The thread of peace has snapped-only&lt;br /&gt;the valour of our fighting Forces, hacked by the very uttermost of&lt;br /&gt;which we are capable in factory and workshop, can knit that thread&lt;br /&gt;again into security'. -Let there be no idle hand. The road of service&lt;br /&gt;is ahead. Let us all tread it firmly, victoriously.&lt;br /&gt;We here, in this spacious land where, for more than 150 years,&lt;br /&gt;peace and security have prevailed, are now called upon to meet the&lt;br /&gt;external aggressor. -The enemy presses from without. I have said&lt;br /&gt;that our forces! are at their battle stations. They are not alone. lIt&lt;br /&gt;is true that Japan is not alone. But, as I speak to you to-night, the&lt;br /&gt;United States; Great Britain and her colonies and dominions, which&lt;br /&gt;include the Commonwealth of Australia -and the Dominion of New&lt;br /&gt;Zealand; the great federation of Russian republics; the Netherlands&lt;br /&gt;East Indies and. China, are associated in the common cause of prcserving&lt;br /&gt;for free men and free women not only their inheritance, but&lt;br /&gt;every hope they have of decency and dignity and liberty.&lt;br /&gt;We Australians have imperishable traditions. We shall maintain&lt;br /&gt;them. We shall vindicate them. We shall hold this country and&lt;br /&gt;keep it as a citadel for the British-speaking race and as a place where&lt;br /&gt;civilization will-persist.&lt;br /&gt;" Men and women of Australia: It is my duty to sound a toosin t&lt;br /&gt;I proclaim a call unto you. I do it in the words of Swinhurne--&lt;br /&gt;"' Come -forth, be born and live,.&lt;br /&gt;Thou that hast help to give,&lt;br /&gt;And light to mnake man's day of manhood fair,&lt;br /&gt;With flight outfiying the sphered sun,&lt;br /&gt;Hasten thine hour&lt;br /&gt;And halt not till thy work ' be done.'"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;STATE OF WAR.&lt;br /&gt;On 9th December, 1941, the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr.&lt;br /&gt;Evatt) said-&lt;br /&gt;" Instructions have been sent to the Charge d'Affaires ( Mr. Officer),&lt;br /&gt;Australian Legation, Tokio, to inform the Imperial Japanese Government&lt;br /&gt;that a state of war exists and has existed between His Majesty's&lt;br /&gt;Government in the Commonwealth of Australia and the Imperial&lt;br /&gt;Japanese Government, as from 5 o'clock in the afternoon, 8th December,&lt;br /&gt;1941. I have also received a formal call this afternoon from the&lt;br /&gt;Japanese Minister to Australia ( Mr. Kawal) and have submitted to&lt;br /&gt;him a communication which related the notification which has been&lt;br /&gt;sent to the Imperial Japanese Government."&lt;br /&gt;MESSAGE TO THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.&lt;br /&gt;On 12th December, 1941, the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr.&lt;br /&gt;Evatt), in communicating formally to the United States Government&lt;br /&gt;the declaration of war by the Commonwealth of Australia against&lt;br /&gt;Japan, conveyed the following message to President Roosevelt on&lt;br /&gt;behalf of the Prime Minister ( Mr. Curtin) and the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;Government. I desire to express our profound appreciation of the initiative,&lt;br /&gt;courage and patience displayed by the President and Secretary of State&lt;br /&gt;in their endeavours to prevent war in the Pacific and in their objective&lt;br /&gt;of outlawing force as on instrument of national policy.&lt;br /&gt;" For the time being the attempt to maintain Pacific peace oii a&lt;br /&gt;basis of law and justice has been checked by the sudden and treacherous&lt;br /&gt;attack of the Japanese forces while diplomiatic negotiations were&lt;br /&gt;actually proceeding. The Commonwealth is hionoured to be associated&lt;br /&gt;with the United States in resisting the aggressors until they are finally&lt;br /&gt;overthrown and until the principles for which the President has so&lt;br /&gt;frequently declared are established, not only in the Pacific, but everywhere&lt;br /&gt;in the world."&lt;br /&gt;In reply, President Roosevelt sent the following message to Dr.&lt;br /&gt;Evstt, to be conveyed to Mr. Cumtin:&lt;br /&gt;" Please send my best wishes to the Government and the people of&lt;br /&gt;Australia. We did our utmost to keep the peace in the Pacific but&lt;br /&gt;our enemies had decided on aggression beforehand. This is now a&lt;br /&gt;world war in the true secse. We are in it wvith you and you will not&lt;br /&gt;find uts wanting. I need not tell the Australians to keep a stout heart.&lt;br /&gt;I know that you will. We will win."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PARLIAMENT APPROVES.&lt;br /&gt;On 16th December, 1941, the House of Representatives, on the&lt;br /&gt;motion of Mr. Curtin, and the Senate, on the motion of the Minister&lt;br /&gt;for the Interior ( Senator Collings), approved the following resolution&lt;br /&gt;unanimously. " That this House approves of the action of His Majesty's Government&lt;br /&gt;in the Commonwealth in ha * g advised the issue of proclamations&lt;br /&gt;declaring the existence of a state f~ war with Japan, Finland, Hungary&lt;br /&gt;and Rumania. Further, this Ho se hereby pledges itself to take every&lt;br /&gt;step deemed necessary to defend this Commonwealth and its territories,&lt;br /&gt;to carry on hostilities in association -with our allies, and to achieve&lt;br /&gt;final victory over our enemies."~&lt;br /&gt;WHEAT POOLS PAYMENTS.&lt;br /&gt;1941-42 CROP FIRST ADVANCE.&lt;br /&gt;On 15th December, 1941, the Minister for Commerce Scully)&lt;br /&gt;said that the Government had approved of the first advance on wheat&lt;br /&gt;of the 1941-42 crop at the rate of 3s. a bushel, less freight, for bagged&lt;br /&gt;wheat, and 2s. 10d. a bushel, less freight, for bulk wheat. This would&lt;br /&gt;involve &#339; 21,000,000. The Government had arranged with the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;Bank for the provision of the necessary funds. The Australian&lt;br /&gt;Wheat Board was conferring with the Commonwealth Bank regarding&lt;br /&gt;the machinery measures necessary for payment and it was anticipated&lt;br /&gt;that these arrangements would he completed to enable payment to be&lt;br /&gt;made towards the end of this month. About 142,000,000 bushels would&lt;br /&gt;be acquired this season, of which 80,000,000 bushels would be bulk&lt;br /&gt;and 62,000,000 bushels bagged. The crop was the first to feel the&lt;br /&gt;real impact of war. Market prospects were not good, the only certain&lt;br /&gt;outlet during the next twelve months being that for 32,000,000 bushels&lt;br /&gt;which would be required in Australia. Because it appeared that a&lt;br /&gt;second advance from sales would not be justified for a considerable&lt;br /&gt;period the Government had fixed the initial advance at the utmost that&lt;br /&gt;could be paid.&lt;br /&gt;( For earlier references, please see No. 3, page 11; No. 4, page 13, No. 6, page&lt;br /&gt;By Author~ ty L F. JOHNSTON. Corrnion wenlIth GovernMent Printer. Cunberr&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>