<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8</transcript-id>
    <title>DIGEST OF DECISIONS AND ANNOUNCEMENTS AND IMPORTANT SPEECHES BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RIGHT HON. J. B. CHIFLEY - 128</title>
    <prime-minister>Chifley, Ben</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19450713 - 19491219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/06/1947</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000008_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects />
    <content>&lt;p&gt;
I No. 128.&lt;br /&gt;
JUNE, 11947, TO 31sT JULY, 11) 47.&lt;br /&gt;
By Authority:&lt;br /&gt;
L F. JOHNSTOCNo. mmonwealth Government Printer. Canbam,&lt;br /&gt;
( Printed in Australia.)&lt;br /&gt;
3009. COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT"&lt;br /&gt;
DIGEST OF DECISIONS&lt;br /&gt;
AND ANNOUNCEMENTS AND&lt;br /&gt;
IMPORTANT SPEECHES&lt;br /&gt;
BY&lt;br /&gt;
THE PRIME MINISTER&lt;br /&gt;
( THE RIGHT HON. J. B. CHIFLEY).&lt;br /&gt;
.1 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ROYAL-AUSTRALIAN NAVY.&lt;br /&gt;
VISIT OF BRITISH CARRIER SQUADRON.&lt;br /&gt;
On 5th June, 1947, the Minister for the Navy ( Mr. Riordan)&lt;br /&gt;
announced that exercises in which two aircraft carriers and two&lt;br /&gt;
destroyers of the British Pacific Fleet and ships of the Australian and&lt;br /&gt;
New Zealand squadrons would take part, would be carried out off the&lt;br /&gt;
Australian coast in July, 1947. The British carriers were H. M. S.&lt;br /&gt;
Theseus and H. M. S. Glory, accompanied by the destroyers Contest and&lt;br /&gt;
Cockade. Theseus would visit Melbourne from 11th July to 20th July.&lt;br /&gt;
Glory would visit Adelaide from 4th July to 9th July. The carriers and&lt;br /&gt;
destroyers would stay in Sydney from 24th July to 6th August, and&lt;br /&gt;
would then go to Brisbane where they would remain from 8th August&lt;br /&gt;
to 18th August. JUDICIARY.&lt;br /&gt;
ARBITRATION COURT-APPOINTMENT OF CHIEF JUDGE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 9th June, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
Mr. Justice H. B. Piper has, owing to ill health, resigned his office&lt;br /&gt;
as Chief Judge of the Commonwealth Arbitration Court as from 16th&lt;br /&gt;
June, 1947, and Mr. Justice E. A. Drake-Brockman is being appointed&lt;br /&gt;
Chief Judge in his stead." INDUSTRIAL.&lt;br /&gt;
PRIME MINISTER MEETS AUSTRALASIAN COUNCIL&lt;br /&gt;
OF TRADES UNIONS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 20th June, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifly) said-&lt;br /&gt;
I met the president ( Mr. P. J. Clarey, and the secretary&lt;br /&gt;
( Mr. A. Monk) of the Australasian Council of Trades Unions to-day.&lt;br /&gt;
They conveyed to me a resolution of the council supporting the&lt;br /&gt;
continuance of Empire preference.&lt;br /&gt;
The officers put to me certain aspects of the 40 hours week and also&lt;br /&gt;
discussed National Security ( Economic Organization) Regulations&lt;br /&gt;
covering wage-pegging.&lt;br /&gt;
The decision of the Council regarding the explediting of food for&lt;br /&gt;
Britain was conveyed to me.&lt;br /&gt;
The officers informed me that the council was opposed to any proposed&lt;br /&gt;
ban on the construction of . the guided projectile range but asked&lt;br /&gt;
that further investigations be made to ensure the welfare of aborigines&lt;br /&gt;
and their land. War and defence were touched on by the officers who&lt;br /&gt;
asked that the Commonwealth Government should use its influence&lt;br /&gt;
at the United Nations in support of a policy of progressive disarnianment&lt;br /&gt;
' and control of atomic bombs.&lt;br /&gt;
The continuance of price control and the position arising in Victoria&lt;br /&gt;
and other States because of the attitude of the Legislative Councils&lt;br /&gt;
was mentioned to me and an intimation given that the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
Government should take measures to assure control of prices and rents.&lt;br /&gt;
" I gave the deputation my views on all the subjects and added that&lt;br /&gt;
their representations would be considered by Cabinet." J &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS-CONFERENCE, AUGUST, 1947.&lt;br /&gt;
On 15th July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
The conference of representatives of the Associated Chambers of&lt;br /&gt;
Manufactures and the Australasian Council of Trades Unions will be&lt;br /&gt;
held on 2nd August and 3rd August, 1947."&lt;br /&gt;
INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS-AUSTRALIAN LABOUR PARTY&lt;br /&gt;
COMMITTEE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 16th July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
At the request of the general secretary of the Australian Labour&lt;br /&gt;
Party ( Mr. P. J. Kennelly, I have agreed to meet the Industrial&lt;br /&gt;
Committee of the Australian Labour Party on 5th August, 1947."&lt;br /&gt;
( The Industrial Committee of the Australian Labour Party comprises:&lt;br /&gt;
Messrs, A. S.-McAlpine ( New South Wales), P. J. Kennelly, M. L. C. ( Victoria),&lt;br /&gt;
S. J. Bryan ( Queensland). and E. Brooker. M. L. A. ( Tasnmnia).)&lt;br /&gt;
INCOME TAX.&lt;br /&gt;
HOARD OF REVIEW.&lt;br /&gt;
On 9th June, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
Cabinet decided to-day that a second Board of Review be established&lt;br /&gt;
under the Income Tax Assessment Act by appointing the present&lt;br /&gt;
War-time ( Company) Tax Board of Referees as the board. The existing&lt;br /&gt;
board of review will be given the powers of the War-time ( Company)&lt;br /&gt;
Tax Board of Referees. For the time being the present board&lt;br /&gt;
will determine cases arising in New South Wales and Queensland, and&lt;br /&gt;
the second board will determine cases arising in the other four States.&lt;br /&gt;
The functions of the Board of Review, although primarily associated&lt;br /&gt;
with income tax, have been extended to matters arising out of sales&lt;br /&gt;
tax, pay-roll tax, . war-time ( company) tax, entertainments tax and&lt;br /&gt;
estate and gift duties.&lt;br /&gt;
At a later date, the second board will be reconstituted with a permanent&lt;br /&gt;
chairman and two permanent members."&lt;br /&gt;
Personnel of the present Board of Review: Messrs. It. E . Gibson ( chairman).&lt;br /&gt;
Hannan, E. F. Hamilton.&lt;br /&gt;
Personnel of War-tinme ( Company) Tax Hoard of H-tefrfccince: Messrs. II.&lt;br /&gt;
MIcGee ( chairman). John Spence, A. Barton.&lt;br /&gt;
ASSESSMENT BILL, 1947-INSTALMENT SCALES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 13th June, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
" Regulations under the Income Tax Assessment Act and the Social&lt;br /&gt;
Services Contribution Assessment Act have been gazetted to-day.&lt;br /&gt;
These regulations prescribe reduced scales of instalment deductions&lt;br /&gt;
to be made by employers from the weekly salary or wages paid to&lt;br /&gt;
employees on and after the 1st July, 1947. The reduced scales give&lt;br /&gt;
effect to the reductions in income tax and social services contribution&lt;br /&gt;
rcnntly paced by Parliament. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As in the past, one scale has been printed by the Taxation Dleparl.-&lt;br /&gt;
ment to cover instalments for both income tax and social services contributions.&lt;br /&gt;
Copies of this scale will be available to employers before&lt;br /&gt;
1st July, 1947.&lt;br /&gt;
Some variation has been made in the form of the printed scale to&lt;br /&gt;
be used. In cases of employees with dependants, the scale at present in&lt;br /&gt;
operation provides for instalments according to the number and class&lt;br /&gt;
of. dependants maintained. In the new scale, the instalments for such&lt;br /&gt;
empl. yees are varied according to the total amount on which rebate may&lt;br /&gt;
be claimed by the employee in respect of dependants. This alteration&lt;br /&gt;
will simplify the application of the scale by employers. A copy of the&lt;br /&gt;
scale is attached.&lt;br /&gt;
The regulations contain provisions which will enable farmers,&lt;br /&gt;
businessmen and other taxpayers from whose income instalment deductions&lt;br /&gt;
are not made, to obtain the benefit of the reduced incomne tax and&lt;br /&gt;
, ocial services contribution rates in the provisional amounts payable by&lt;br /&gt;
them in respect of the income of the year ending 30th June, 1948.&lt;br /&gt;
" Normally, the provisional tax and contribution payable by such a&lt;br /&gt;
taxpayer would be equal to the income tax and social services contribution,&lt;br /&gt;
respectively, assessed for the financial year 1946-47. However, in&lt;br /&gt;
view of the fact that the rates of income tax and social services contribution&lt;br /&gt;
for the financial year 1947-48 will be lower than those for the&lt;br /&gt;
financial year 1946-47, the regulations provide for a reduction in the&lt;br /&gt;
provisional tax and contribution otherwise payable for the financial&lt;br /&gt;
year 1947-48. Broadly, in cases where the taxpayer will be liable to&lt;br /&gt;
both income tax and social services contribution, the reduction will le Is.&lt;br /&gt;
in the &#339; 1 for each &#339; 1 of the taxable income derived by him during the&lt;br /&gt;
year ending 30th June, 1947. In other cases, the reduction will be&lt;br /&gt;
graduated up to a maximum of Is. in the &#339; 1 for each &#339; 1 of the taxable&lt;br /&gt;
inconie derived by the taxpayer during the year ending 30th June, 1947.&lt;br /&gt;
The regulations also prescribe the metals to which section 23 ( p)&lt;br /&gt;
the Act shall apply. Section 23 exempts income derived by a&lt;br /&gt;
bona fide prospector from the sale, transfer or assignment by him of his&lt;br /&gt;
rights to mine for gold and for such metals and minerals as arc prescribed.&lt;br /&gt;
The metals prescribed for the purpose of this provision are&lt;br /&gt;
antimony, arsenic, beryllium, bismuth, cobalt, copper, mercury, molybdenuin,&lt;br /&gt;
nickel, tin and vanadium."&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 125, page 28; No. 126, page 29.)&lt;br /&gt;
FISHING INDUSTRY.&lt;br /&gt;
WHALING-AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY.&lt;br /&gt;
On 9th June, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
" On 20th November, 1945, Cabinet approved of proposals for Australian&lt;br /&gt;
participation for whaling in the Southern Hemisphere. Since&lt;br /&gt;
then an officer of the Fisheries Division of the Department of&lt;br /&gt;
Post-war Reconstruction has attended an International Whaling &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conference. An inter-departmental conunittee, representing the&lt;br /&gt;
Departments of the Treasury, Labour, Commerce, Supply and&lt;br /&gt;
Shipping, Post-war Reconstruction and Repatriation has considered&lt;br /&gt;
the general prospects of the industry. and particularly&lt;br /&gt;
in the light of information received from Britain that the delivery&lt;br /&gt;
of a factory ship would not ' be made until 1950 at the earliest.&lt;br /&gt;
It was considered that Australia's initial entry into the industry&lt;br /&gt;
should be through land stations and that, when they had been&lt;br /&gt;
established and personnel trained, consideration could be given to&lt;br /&gt;
pelagic operations.&lt;br /&gt;
The Minister for Commerce ( Mr. Pollard) informed Cabinet to-&lt;br /&gt;
( lay that the present position was that the building of a factory ship&lt;br /&gt;
could not he completed until 1950 and that the proposal to secure a&lt;br /&gt;
factory ship as part of Japanese reparations was being investigated by&lt;br /&gt;
the Department of External Affairs but, even if aproved, there would&lt;br /&gt;
he delay in delivery. It appeared that the Australian industry should&lt;br /&gt;
be developed on shore-based operations from the New South Wales and&lt;br /&gt;
Western Australian coasti and by pelagic operations based on Hobartthe&lt;br /&gt;
latter being subject to personnel being trained at the land stations&lt;br /&gt;
and prospects carefully checked.&lt;br /&gt;
Cabinet decided to conmmence negotiations for the cingagcllent of&lt;br /&gt;
a whaling expert."&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 108, page 8; No. 110, page 14.)&lt;br /&gt;
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. CREDIT.&lt;br /&gt;
On llth June, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
" A credit of &#339; stg. 500,000 has been granted to the Government of&lt;br /&gt;
Czechoslovakia through the Commonwealth Bank of Australia for the&lt;br /&gt;
purchase of Australian wool. The period of the credit is one year.&lt;br /&gt;
Repayment has been guaranteed by the Government of Czechoslovakia.&lt;br /&gt;
. It is ! a condition of the agreement that Czechoslovakia will make cash&lt;br /&gt;
purchases of Australian wool to a value at least equal to the amount of&lt;br /&gt;
the guaranteed credit.&lt;br /&gt;
" Before the war, Czechoslovakia was becoming an increasingly&lt;br /&gt;
important buyer of Australian wool. It is considered that the credit&lt;br /&gt;
will assist in the early re-establishment of the woollen industry in&lt;br /&gt;
that country." DEFENCE.&lt;br /&gt;
POST-WAR-UNITED STATES CO-OPERATION.&lt;br /&gt;
On 11th June, 1947, the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr. Evatt)&lt;br /&gt;
and the United States Ambassador ( Mr. Butler) said-&lt;br /&gt;
The Commander-in-Chief of the United States Navy, Army and&lt;br /&gt;
Air Forces in the Pacific area ( Admiral L. E. Denfeld) has had discussions&lt;br /&gt;
with the Australian Government and service authorities on &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7&lt;br /&gt;
matters of mutual interest in the Pacific. The purpose of his visit was&lt;br /&gt;
to ensure the continuance of the close co-operation between the United&lt;br /&gt;
States and Australian services which existed through the war period&lt;br /&gt;
and which contributed so much to victory in the Pacific.&lt;br /&gt;
There is a practical identity of Pacific interests and excellent relationships&lt;br /&gt;
existing between the United States and Australia. The discussions&lt;br /&gt;
Admiral Denfeld has had with the Prime Minister ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
Chifley), the MAinister for External Affairs, the Minister for the Navy&lt;br /&gt;
( Mr. Riordan), and service authorities have covered mutual interests&lt;br /&gt;
of the two countries in the Pacific, and it is natural that such discussions&lt;br /&gt;
should be repeated from time to time. They are the natural&lt;br /&gt;
outcome of the close association between the two Governments which&lt;br /&gt;
characterized the war period and, being purely defensive in character,&lt;br /&gt;
are completely in accord with the principles and purposes of the&lt;br /&gt;
United Nations. The discussions during the last few days in Australia&lt;br /&gt;
have been entirely successful from ail points of view."&lt;br /&gt;
DEFENCE SOCIENTIFIC ADVISORY COMMITTEE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 31st July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
Following the recent appointment of Mr. A. P. Rowe as defence&lt;br /&gt;
scientific advisor and cha. irman of the Defence Scientific Advisory&lt;br /&gt;
Committee, members of the committee have been appointed as follows:-&lt;br /&gt;
The Executive Officer of the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research&lt;br /&gt;
( Dr. F. W. G. White), the Professur of Physics at Melbourne University ( Professor&lt;br /&gt;
L. H. M; xrtin), the Professor of C emistry at Melbourne University&lt;br /&gt;
( Professor E. Hartung), the Professor of Aeronautical Engineering at Sydney&lt;br /&gt;
University ( Professor A. V. Stephens), the Director of the Walter and Eliza&lt;br /&gt;
Hall Institute of Research in Pathology and Medicine ( Professor F. R. Burnet).&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 109, page 42; No. 113, page&lt;br /&gt;
POST-WAR-NEW WEAPONS, LONG RANGE WEAPONS&lt;br /&gt;
BOARD.&lt;br /&gt;
On 31st July, 1947. the Acting Minister for Post-war Reconstruction&lt;br /&gt;
( Mr. Pollard) announced National Security ( Munitions) Regulations&lt;br /&gt;
to set up within the Department of Munitions a Long Range&lt;br /&gt;
Weapons Board of Administration. The board would be responsible&lt;br /&gt;
for the conduct of factories engaged in the production of long-range&lt;br /&gt;
weapons; for the setting up of ranges and testing establishments, and&lt;br /&gt;
for testing operations; for all matters relating to scientific research&lt;br /&gt;
and the technical development and design of long-range weapons and&lt;br /&gt;
equipment. The board would consist of two representatives of the&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Munitions, three representatives of the British Ministry&lt;br /&gt;
of Supply and a representative of each of the Departments of Defence,&lt;br /&gt;
Navy, Army, Air and Works and Housing. JI &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE.&lt;br /&gt;
AWARDS FOR GALLANTRY.&lt;br /&gt;
On 12th June, 1947, the Governor-General announced the following&lt;br /&gt;
awards:-Air Force Cross.-Squadron-leader J. R. French, C. C. Henry,&lt;br /&gt;
J. G. Hoskins, J. R. Lavers, J. T. O'Brien, Flight-lieutenants R. W.&lt;br /&gt;
Adsett, E. M. Allison, M. W. Baker, M. C. Clifford, C. R. Gallwey,&lt;br /&gt;
E. T. W. Holt, P. J. Love, A. W. P. Malcolm, C. R. McNichol, J.&lt;br /&gt;
Rankin, E. B. Stacy, Flying-officers A. Burns, H. A. Kirkhouse, N. J.&lt;br /&gt;
Properjohn. Air Force Meda/.-Flight-sergeant D. W. Hosking.&lt;br /&gt;
OHIEF OF AIR STAFF--VIStT TO BRITAIN.&lt;br /&gt;
On 7th July, 1947, the Minister for Air ( Mr. Drakeford)&lt;br /&gt;
anounced that the Chief of the Air Staff ( Air Marshal G. Jones)&lt;br /&gt;
would visit Britain and the United States of \ A. merica during&lt;br /&gt;
August, 1947. He would attend a conference called by the British&lt;br /&gt;
Chief of the Air Staff ( Lord Tedder) of the comianders-in-chief of&lt;br /&gt;
Royal Air Force commands at home and overseas, and to which&lt;br /&gt;
Dominions Chiefs of Air Staff had been invited. In the United Statoft&lt;br /&gt;
America, Air Marshal Jones would attend talks with General Spaatz&lt;br /&gt;
and General Kenny , f the United States of America Air Force.&lt;br /&gt;
COMMAND CHANGES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 9th July, 1947, Mr. Drakeford announced that Air Commodore&lt;br /&gt;
P. J. McCauley, who had been appointed Chief of Staff to the&lt;br /&gt;
Commander-in-Chief of the British Commonwealth Occupation Forces&lt;br /&gt;
. in Japan, had been promoted to the acting rank of air vice-marshal.&lt;br /&gt;
On 25th July, 1947, Mr. Drakeford announced tha. t Air Commodore&lt;br /&gt;
F. R. W. Seherger had been appointed deputy-chief of the Air Staff.&lt;br /&gt;
CADET COLLEGE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 23rd July, 1947, Mr. Drakeford ' announced that commencement&lt;br /&gt;
would be made on 1st August, 1947, to establish the Royal Australian&lt;br /&gt;
Air Force Cadet College at Point Cook for the training as officers of boys&lt;br /&gt;
between the ages of 16 and 1S years. Annual courses would commence&lt;br /&gt;
in 1948 and would be of. four years' duration. Annual intake of cadets&lt;br /&gt;
would be about 24 pupilS.&lt;br /&gt;
STRENGTH AND ACTIVITIES-EXOHANGE WITH ROYAL&lt;br /&gt;
AIR FORCE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 30th July, 1947, Mr. Drakeford announced that five Royal Australian&lt;br /&gt;
Air Force crews would be sent to Britain to become members of&lt;br /&gt;
the No. 24 ( Commonwealth) Squadron on an exchange basis with the&lt;br /&gt;
Royal Air Force. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9&lt;br /&gt;
PRIMARY INDUSTRIES.&lt;br /&gt;
EXPORTS TO BRITAIN-BRITISH POLICY.&lt;br /&gt;
On 12th . June, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
The policy of the British Government on foodstuffs so far . as Austr:&lt;br /&gt;
lia is concerned is to import the maximum quantities of basic foodtruffs.&lt;br /&gt;
such as dairy products and meat, from us. Britain wants many&lt;br /&gt;
othpr product. in addition to these basic lines including-&lt;br /&gt;
IT! onlto pur chutney. apple butter, vilegar, bonox, vegemite, fruit juices,&lt;br /&gt;
e mined meat and vegetables, canned steak and vegetables, canned rabbit, canned&lt;br /&gt;
poultry, fricassee of poultry, fri,;-' nec of rabbit, fricassee of mutton, steak and&lt;br /&gt;
kidney pudding. and irish stexx.&lt;br /&gt;
: Britain do( s nor want certain foodstuffs in a processed form&lt;br /&gt;
Ilc-ausicf sli prefers tine raw iaterials. She does not want plum pudlings,&lt;br /&gt;
for instacce, from Australia, if she can obtain the flour, dried&lt;br /&gt;
fruits and fats in bulk and use these items to the best advantage.&lt;br /&gt;
Australia has been cognizant of the British Government's decision&lt;br /&gt;
lto irstrict rlth import of certain processed and semi-luxury foodstuffs.&lt;br /&gt;
It li; s beli tl.. policy of the British Ministry of Food to import food&lt;br /&gt;
stiifs in pIarticnlar formns so that the Ministry may implement its rationig&lt;br /&gt;
seljiinm. Kiinoing the position of Britain, the Australian Governmient&lt;br /&gt;
hi,-nei'. and will continue to do, everything possible to shift&lt;br /&gt;
the maxirinunl foodstuffs to Britain. The British import policy on food&lt;br /&gt;
is the concern of tihe British Government.&lt;br /&gt;
Australin has serious problems for tinned plate supplies and does&lt;br /&gt;
not always desire to send goods in cans which can be exported in bulk.&lt;br /&gt;
Australian exports to Britain of goods which are subject to import&lt;br /&gt;
restrictionLs are not appreciable and make very little impression on the&lt;br /&gt;
iquantity of foodstuffs required by the British Ministry."&lt;br /&gt;
DAIRY INDUSTRY-CONTROL.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
The Australian Dairy Produce Board was set up in October, 1924,&lt;br /&gt;
, nil consists of seventeen members appointed under the Dairy Produce&lt;br /&gt;
Export Control Act. The members comprise-&lt;br /&gt;
Four producers. iine representatives of butter and cheese factories, two&lt;br /&gt;
representatives of prdprietary and privately-owned butter and cheese factories,&lt;br /&gt;
inc representative of the Australian Council of the Australian Institute of Dairy&lt;br /&gt;
Factory Managers and Secretaries, and one representative of the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
Government. During the war, the board's activities were curtailed and under&lt;br /&gt;
National Security Act regulations, control of . the industry was taken&lt;br /&gt;
over in November, 1939, by a small committee vested with wide powers.&lt;br /&gt;
Cabinet decided to-day that legislation be prepared to amend the&lt;br /&gt;
Dairy Produce Control Act to provide for a board of twelve members,&lt;br /&gt;
with a ' Government nominee as chairman; to be vested with such additional&lt;br /&gt;
powers and functions as might be necessary in the light of circumstances&lt;br /&gt;
now obtaining in the industry. It is proposed that, when&lt;br /&gt;
the new legislation operates, National Security Act regulations will be&lt;br /&gt;
withdrawn." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DAIRY INDUSTRY-MILK, SUBSIDIES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 18th July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
" A decision as to the future control of milk will be made by the&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth Government in September, 1947. The decision to be&lt;br /&gt;
made is whether the Commonwealth should take any further interest&lt;br /&gt;
and step out, or whether control should be handed to a State or local&lt;br /&gt;
authority. If subsidies are discontinued by the Commonwealth, that&lt;br /&gt;
will mean substantial increases in milk prices to consumers. One of the&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth's difficulties is that at places such as Hobart and Launceston&lt;br /&gt;
there is no authority to which the Commonwealth can hand&lt;br /&gt;
control." AGRICULTURAL MACHINERY-EXPORT CONTROLLED.&lt;br /&gt;
On 3rd July, 1947, the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Pollard)&lt;br /&gt;
announced that controls would be exercised over the export of essential&lt;br /&gt;
agricultural machinery to ensure that the greatest possible volume&lt;br /&gt;
would be available in Australia. Types involved were--&lt;br /&gt;
Tractors, grain and fertilizer cu! tivator drills, and seed drills for cereal crops,&lt;br /&gt;
header harvesters. rezaper threshers, reapers and hinders, hay balers, side delivery&lt;br /&gt;
rakes, mowers and spare parts.&lt;br /&gt;
Token overseas shipments would be permitted as the nucleus of trade&lt;br /&gt;
must be preserved.&lt;br /&gt;
AGRICULTURAL COUNCIL MEETING-DECISIONS.&lt;br /&gt;
On S1st Jily, 1947, Mr. Pollard said that a meeting of Anstralian&lt;br /&gt;
Agricultural Council had been held. Decisions were-&lt;br /&gt;
3IARKETING O I-I; GS.-At its last meeting. cotincil adopted recotniimei( ldtioiis&lt;br /&gt;
embracing the formation of the Australian Egg E. qualization Conmmittee Limited&lt;br /&gt;
for the marketing of eggs. The Standing Conmnittee on Agriculture now&lt;br /&gt;
reported that unless the neces-iry legislation could be passed in New South&lt;br /&gt;
Wales and Victoria to enable the company to operate as from It January,&lt;br /&gt;
1S! 48, there would he disorganization in marketing and a fall in prices. Dealing&lt;br /&gt;
with the question of surplus funds from Commonwealth egg control, Council&lt;br /&gt;
expressed the view that the Commonwealth Government should be informed that&lt;br /&gt;
some portion of the fund should be distributed as working capital of tile Australian&lt;br /&gt;
Egg Equalization Committee Limited.&lt;br /&gt;
BABLEY.--Proposals for the future marketing of barley, previously agreed to&lt;br /&gt;
by representatives of Victorian and South Australian Governments and growers,&lt;br /&gt;
and trading interests in those States, were adopted by council. The proposals&lt;br /&gt;
provide for marketing barley under a pool system operating under State legislation&lt;br /&gt;
without any guaraniitee of price: growers in effect receiving the average&lt;br /&gt;
return obtained by the pool. Council decided that draft legislation prepared by&lt;br /&gt;
the South Australian Government be considered by a conference of Commonwealth.&lt;br /&gt;
Victorian and South Australian legal officers and that the draft bill&lt;br /&gt;
then be submitted to the Commonwealth Government for approval and preparation&lt;br /&gt;
as a Commonwealth Bill. The measure is to cover marketing of barley in&lt;br /&gt;
Victoria and South Australia and any other States prepared to participate.&lt;br /&gt;
ToBAcco.-Council adopted a tentative outline of Commonwealth and State&lt;br /&gt;
legislation embodying principles considered necessary for a tobacco marketing&lt;br /&gt;
scheme. The proposals envisaged a central authority charged with appraising&lt;br /&gt;
tobacco leaf submitted to it under complementary State legislation. It would be&lt;br /&gt;
necessary for the States to invest the central authority with necessary powers to &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11&lt;br /&gt;
appraise Australian tobacco leaf and allocate leaf to manufacturers. The legislation&lt;br /&gt;
would provide for a table of limits which would be used to appraise leaf&lt;br /&gt;
and should prohibit transactions except in accordance with the requirements of&lt;br /&gt;
State Acts.&lt;br /&gt;
POTArOEs.-Council noted that the Commonwealth had decided to continue&lt;br /&gt;
the contract system with potatoes to cover the 1947-48 crop. The area desired&lt;br /&gt;
was 185,000 acres calculated to give production sufficient to supply the population&lt;br /&gt;
of Australia with 2j lb. of potatoes a week throughout the year with a margin&lt;br /&gt;
of safety. It was proposed to allocate the area for 1947-48 as follows:-New&lt;br /&gt;
South Wales-31,533 acres; Victoria-66,347 acres; Queeneland-17,735 acres;&lt;br /&gt;
South Australia-7,880 acres; Western Australia-7,823 acres; Tasmania-&lt;br /&gt;
54,149 acres; Total-185,467 acres.&lt;br /&gt;
Basic price for best varieties of No. 1 grade was being raised from &#339; 12&lt;br /&gt;
to &#339; 13 10s. a ton to cover increased costs arising from the removal of the subsidy&lt;br /&gt;
on cornsacks and other increases. Council was informed that the existing&lt;br /&gt;
scheme would not be extended after the season ending 1948 and stressed the&lt;br /&gt;
necessity for all State legislation to be ready for operation before that date.&lt;br /&gt;
SOIL CONSERVATION.-Council decided that, recognizing the importance of rye&lt;br /&gt;
corn in soil conservation in Australia, immediate steps should be taken to build&lt;br /&gt;
up in the Commonwealth a comprehensive collection of the world's rye corn&lt;br /&gt;
varieties. Council recommended that a duly stubble mulch farm machine set be&lt;br /&gt;
imported and made available to the New South Wales Conservation Service for&lt;br /&gt;
testing as to efficiency.&lt;br /&gt;
FERTITIzaER.-Council adopted recommendations from the conference of Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
and State fertilizer officers as follows:-&lt;br /&gt;
Sulphate for 1947-48 would be allocated to each State in the same proportion&lt;br /&gt;
as in 1946-47.&lt;br /&gt;
Nitrate of soda for 1947-48 would be allotted as follows:-New South Wales-&lt;br /&gt;
1,100 tons; Victoria-1,100' tons; Queensland-2,000 tons: South Australia-&lt;br /&gt;
450 tons: Western Australia-1,000 tons; Tasmania-350 tons; Total--6,000&lt;br /&gt;
tons. Superphosphate supplies would be similar to the 1946-47 period-1,250,000&lt;br /&gt;
tons. Potash supplies would be ample through commercial channels. Accordingly&lt;br /&gt;
, upplies would not be allocated between the States for 1947-48.&lt;br /&gt;
INSECT PEST CONTROL.-Council agreed to recommendations by the Standing&lt;br /&gt;
Committee on Agriculture that a trial plan against plague locusts be undertaken&lt;br /&gt;
in New South Wales.&lt;br /&gt;
STocK DlsEASEs.-Recommentdations to council . by a conference of Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
and State veterinary officers on control of stock diseases were approved&lt;br /&gt;
as follows:-In view of the serious position developing in connexion. with ayian tuberculosis,&lt;br /&gt;
poultry slaughtering should be subject to inspection under&lt;br /&gt;
veterinary control in all States.&lt;br /&gt;
Tuberculosis-free herd schemes should be uniform. Schemes in operation&lt;br /&gt;
in New South Wales and Victoria, with agreed amendments to be accepted&lt;br /&gt;
as a guide.&lt;br /&gt;
Disease of Poultry.-Pullorum-free flock schemes were desirable in each&lt;br /&gt;
State and those in operation should be used as a basis by States preparing&lt;br /&gt;
echemes. An organized investigation into Birdsville and other related diseases of&lt;br /&gt;
horses be conducted by the Council for Scientific and Iudustrial Research in&lt;br /&gt;
conjunction with the Departments of Agriculture of Queensland, South&lt;br /&gt;
Australia and Western Australia and the Northern Territory Administration.&lt;br /&gt;
In the event of private institutions preparing living canine distemper&lt;br /&gt;
virus vaccine, it should be controlled by requiring it to be issued only to&lt;br /&gt;
veterinary surgeons.&lt;br /&gt;
As penicillin was widely required for the treatment of bovine mastitis&lt;br /&gt;
and other diseases, any restrictions on the issue of penicillin for veterinary&lt;br /&gt;
use should be abolished. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VEGETABLE OIL PLA. NTS.-Council was informed by the Standing Committee onl&lt;br /&gt;
Agriculture that it had considered the report of the Commonwealth mission&lt;br /&gt;
which visited the United States in 1946 to inquire into the soybean industry:&lt;br /&gt;
The committee informed council that it had accepted recommendations as&lt;br /&gt;
fnllows:-Commonwealth and State Governments should take energetic action to&lt;br /&gt;
promote the economic production of vegetable oil plants in Australia.&lt;br /&gt;
The Commonwealth and States should set up a Vegetable Oils Committee&lt;br /&gt;
to recommend broad policy on vegetable oil production to the council. Funds&lt;br /&gt;
should be made available to undertake an intensive programme of plant&lt;br /&gt;
breeding and selection and testing of soybeans and the vegetable oil producing&lt;br /&gt;
plants appropriate to their environment.&lt;br /&gt;
The Council for Scientific and Industrial Research should undertake investigation&lt;br /&gt;
into the industrial uses of vegetable oils. To allow manufacturers to&lt;br /&gt;
exploit the possibilities of soybean oil, permits be issued for the importation&lt;br /&gt;
of soybeans. MIGRATION.&lt;br /&gt;
OVERSEAS OFFICES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 12th June, 1947, the Minister for Immigration ( Mr. Calwell)&lt;br /&gt;
announced that nine new Australian immigration offices would be&lt;br /&gt;
opened as soon as arrangements could be completed at Oslo, The Hague.&lt;br /&gt;
Paris, Berlin, San Francisco and New York, Shanghai, New Delhi and&lt;br /&gt;
Cairo. The offices would deal with all migration matters, including&lt;br /&gt;
official migration schemes, and the handling of landing permits, passports&lt;br /&gt;
and the like. Duties of the offices at San Francisco and New&lt;br /&gt;
York would include reception of applications and selection for the&lt;br /&gt;
Government's new assisted passage scheme for United States ex-service-&lt;br /&gt;
NATIONAL ECONOMIC PLAN.&lt;br /&gt;
SALES AND TRANSFERS OF LAND-ADMINISTRATION.&lt;br /&gt;
ROYAL COMMISSION.&lt;br /&gt;
On 13th June, 1947, the Attorney-Genera! ( Dr. Evatt) announced&lt;br /&gt;
that Judge Kirby, of the New South Wales District Court, had been&lt;br /&gt;
appointed a Royal Commissioner to inquire into and report on certain&lt;br /&gt;
matters arising out of the administration of land sales control. Terms&lt;br /&gt;
of reference were-&lt;br /&gt;
Whether there was misconduct or wrulg-doig on the part of any person in&lt;br /&gt;
or in coninexion with the handling of or dealing with any of the following transactions&lt;br /&gt;
by the Sydney Land Sales Control office of the Department of the&lt;br /&gt;
Treasury, or the Canberra Land Sales Control office of that department:-&lt;br /&gt;
The transactions submitted for the Treasurer's consent by or on behalf&lt;br /&gt;
of Stanley Evan Parry, Edward Richard Courtney McCormac, Sub&lt;br /&gt;
. division Estates and Land Pty. Ltd., Burke Naughton Pty. Ltd., and&lt;br /&gt;
Australian Securities Ltd.; and&lt;br /&gt;
The transactions specified by Frederick Alan Lush in his letter of 23rd&lt;br /&gt;
May, 1947, to the Prime Minister.&lt;br /&gt;
If you are of opinion that there was any such misconduct or wrong-doing&lt;br /&gt;
what person or persons were guilty of it and in what did it consist. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FIXATION OF WAGES AND SALARIES-REGULATIONS&lt;br /&gt;
FURTHER AMENDED.&lt;br /&gt;
On 13th June, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
The Executive Council has approved a further re-organization of&lt;br /&gt;
the wage-pegging provisions of National Security ( Economic Organization)&lt;br /&gt;
Regulations. The amendment now made will permit action to . be&lt;br /&gt;
taken under the 40-hour week legislation recently passed in New South&lt;br /&gt;
Wales without danger of conflict with the wage-pegging provisions of&lt;br /&gt;
the regulations. The amendment will, however, apply also to any similar measures&lt;br /&gt;
that may be passed in other States. Its effect is to permit the payment&lt;br /&gt;
of remuneration at an altered rate where the alteration is consequential&lt;br /&gt;
on a reduction in working hours made under any State Act coming into&lt;br /&gt;
force after to-day."&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 122, page 22; No. 125, page&lt;br /&gt;
THE GOVERNMENT.&lt;br /&gt;
POLICY-PRIME MINISTER'S SPEECH, JUNE, 1947.&lt;br /&gt;
On 15th June, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said*-&lt;br /&gt;
The Labour party is the greatest political party to-day that Australia&lt;br /&gt;
has ever known and the only political party that proved, in the&lt;br /&gt;
years of war, capable of governing this country. The Labour party at&lt;br /&gt;
. uch conferences as this voices its views and discusses not only internal&lt;br /&gt;
problems but also gives some thought to international problems associated&lt;br /&gt;
with the life of this nation.&lt;br /&gt;
I feel that the work of the Labour movement in New South Wales&lt;br /&gt;
and in the federal sphere during the past six years is not a story I need&lt;br /&gt;
reiterate. .1 do not say that there have not been some shortcomings.&lt;br /&gt;
am one, privileged as I have been to lead the Federal Parliamentary&lt;br /&gt;
Labour party, who realizes that in the life of a government there are&lt;br /&gt;
some things that call for criticism. Criticism is not a bad thing, but I&lt;br /&gt;
rhink criticism should be based on facts and should be directed, not&lt;br /&gt;
towards individuals particularly, but. generally towards the methods&lt;br /&gt;
used. " Now, after six years in which the people have trusted the Labour&lt;br /&gt;
party in the federal sphere and in a majority of States, we are faced&lt;br /&gt;
with an equally grave responsibility, although not in the atmosphere of&lt;br /&gt;
danger and war nor with the same difficulties. But we face a re-orientation&lt;br /&gt;
of some of the views on some of the problems. We can fact our&lt;br /&gt;
internal problems in an atmosphere of full employment and a better&lt;br /&gt;
standard of living than in most countries to-day. We live in a very&lt;br /&gt;
troubled world. Grent economic problems face other countries to-day.&lt;br /&gt;
Europe is in a very bad way and many persons feel frustrated and disappointed&lt;br /&gt;
that leading men of the world cannot find solutions to great&lt;br /&gt;
At the inn! conferuce of trhe New S uth W le brh: inich tih A.\ Istrahm;&lt;br /&gt;
.; iahour p; ir y. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;problems which beset the world and set a road of guidance for the&lt;br /&gt;
future. That is because countries hold such widely diverse views of&lt;br /&gt;
what should be the methods and what guidance should ' be given.&lt;br /&gt;
Australia can look at the problems very clearly. Great opportunities&lt;br /&gt;
and the fulfilment or the achievement of the matters that those&lt;br /&gt;
opportunities offer rests with the people in Australia-the Government&lt;br /&gt;
can legislate and provide machinery.&lt;br /&gt;
In the Pacific, Australia is an isolated island continent, but it&lt;br /&gt;
c: an no longer stay out of the affairs of the world or for protection in&lt;br /&gt;
defence depend on Britain. The economic problems which beset Britain&lt;br /&gt;
to-day have left her in a position in which she must look to the&lt;br /&gt;
Dominions to play a great part in maintaining stability and security.&lt;br /&gt;
' This country, which is young and a country I hope which will grow&lt;br /&gt;
to greater proportions offered opportunities and the Labour party is the&lt;br /&gt;
only political party capable of governing the people and giving effect&lt;br /&gt;
to their wishes.&lt;br /&gt;
Those opportunities must not be lost. First, we must face the&lt;br /&gt;
problem of bringing here hundreds of thousands of people from other&lt;br /&gt;
countries. If British people are available so much the better, hut manpower&lt;br /&gt;
in Britain is much needed to-day, so we must turn to Europe&lt;br /&gt;
for hundreds to build up this country. We must determine the best&lt;br /&gt;
methods to build Australia and fulfil our destiny. Because of isolation.&lt;br /&gt;
we are far from the stress and strife in Europe. We ' have sonime reasonable&lt;br /&gt;
stability. The efforts of the Government have been able not only&lt;br /&gt;
to . meet the effects of war, but also the transition to peace. Some persons&lt;br /&gt;
believe that because there is prosperity-because there are more&lt;br /&gt;
jobs than people to fill them, because there are high prices from overseas&lt;br /&gt;
exports-that that particular state of affairs, particularly in&lt;br /&gt;
regard to prices, might last for ever. We must be prepared, in giving&lt;br /&gt;
consideration to our economic affairs, for a reduction in those prices. It&lt;br /&gt;
is possible that some measure of decline will come in the market before&lt;br /&gt;
many years are passed. We must, in planning the economy of this&lt;br /&gt;
country, realize that there is . likely to be some recession in the money&lt;br /&gt;
coming to this country from our exports.&lt;br /&gt;
In the world of interna. tional affairs, Australia has played a great&lt;br /&gt;
part. It has participated in all the councils of the nations of the world.&lt;br /&gt;
The Minister for External Affairs ( Dr. Evatt), the Australian High&lt;br /&gt;
Commissioner in the United Kingdom ( Mr. Beasley), the Australian&lt;br /&gt;
Minister at Washington ( Mr. Makin) and the Australian High Commissioner&lt;br /&gt;
to Canada ( Mr. Forde)-all representatives of the Labour&lt;br /&gt;
movement-have played their part in seeing that Australia has been&lt;br /&gt;
heard. We cannot any longer depend on Britain for the defence of this&lt;br /&gt;
country. There may be a feeling of frustration that so little has been&lt;br /&gt;
achieved so far towards a lasting peace, but there can be no mistake in&lt;br /&gt;
the minds of people that there shall be an improved living standard&lt;br /&gt;
and their objective is to achieve by some means or other some peace for&lt;br /&gt;
the workers of the world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;" Internally, we are living in a period of full employment. That&lt;br /&gt;
has been one of the ideals of the Labour movement, but for the first time&lt;br /&gt;
in my association with the Labour movement we have achieved that&lt;br /&gt;
object. There must be no faltering in the Federal or . State Labour&lt;br /&gt;
parties to ensure that that condition of affairs is maintained and, of&lt;br /&gt;
course, to maintain the standard of living of the people. That does not&lt;br /&gt;
rest with politicians and it does not rest with parliaments; it rests&lt;br /&gt;
with the trade unions and the workers of this country. Unless they&lt;br /&gt;
are prepared to play their part and give to the nation and to the&lt;br /&gt;
community the very best that they can give, those objectives cannot be&lt;br /&gt;
achieved. " I say that the trade union movement owes not only a duty to their&lt;br /&gt;
own organizations, but a duty to the community in which they live and&lt;br /&gt;
the nation to which they belong. I hope that leaders in the trade union&lt;br /&gt;
movement will be inspired in their efforts to see that some of the&lt;br /&gt;
industrial troubles which arise will be reduced. I understand that&lt;br /&gt;
strikes prove a corrective for many injustices. I can understand an&lt;br /&gt;
industrial stoppage on principle, but there have been a. number of&lt;br /&gt;
stoppages during recent years not connected with such matters. There&lt;br /&gt;
have been stoppages in connexion with demarcation disputes-not disputes&lt;br /&gt;
with Governments but dispute among the workers. It" is shocking&lt;br /&gt;
that trade unions in a matter of demarcation are not prepared&lt;br /&gt;
to take it to a judicial authority. They are like a comic opera and&lt;br /&gt;
persons working together who create these situations are not working&lt;br /&gt;
for the common good.&lt;br /&gt;
" I make it very clear that you should take from these conferences&lt;br /&gt;
through the country the realization that this is not a movement&lt;br /&gt;
organized for the glorification of its leaders or trade union leaders, but&lt;br /&gt;
for the benefit of the people and workers of the country. Personal animosities&lt;br /&gt;
cannot be avoided, but whatever they are they have to be subjugated&lt;br /&gt;
to the great masses of the people. I ask you to infuse the fire&lt;br /&gt;
and spirit which characterized the pioneers of the Labour movement&lt;br /&gt;
into the hundreds and thousands throughout the country and see that&lt;br /&gt;
Labour is returned to power.&lt;br /&gt;
There are persoins who try to cling to the coat-tails of the Labour&lt;br /&gt;
movement to espouse philosophies which are not philosophies of the&lt;br /&gt;
Labour movement. I say that this is a country of freedom of expression&lt;br /&gt;
and freedom to establish any political philosophy, but let those persons&lt;br /&gt;
preach their philosophy from their own platform. The Labour movement&lt;br /&gt;
lives and achieves the ideals and aspirations of the great working&lt;br /&gt;
class persons of this country. The working class consists of men&lt;br /&gt;
and women who work, whether manually or otherwise, for the country&lt;br /&gt;
and give of their best in their daily toil, whatever that may be.&lt;br /&gt;
The Labour party is unique among political parties because in&lt;br /&gt;
six States it has its organizations. Men come from 4,000 miles apart&lt;br /&gt;
who bring to that Federal Parliamentary Labour party many diverse&lt;br /&gt;
views. It is no easy matter to cater for the many parts of Australia&lt;br /&gt;
in federal policy, and that is done by federal conference and translated &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;into action by the Federal Labour party. It is a great achievement for&lt;br /&gt;
a party to create such solidarity as that. There is only one way to&lt;br /&gt;
achieve such things, whatever personal feelings we have, and that is by&lt;br /&gt;
solidarity. The history of this and every country shows that the people&lt;br /&gt;
will not trust parties who are not able to govern themselves and trust&lt;br /&gt;
only parties who have ways and methods of achieving their objective.&lt;br /&gt;
T think it does no harm to the Labour party or trade union movement&lt;br /&gt;
( which forms the foundation of the Labour party) when criticism is&lt;br /&gt;
levelled from time to time provided the criticism is based on facts. We&lt;br /&gt;
do not wish to live in a mutual admiration society. I have in my party&lt;br /&gt;
over 70 federal members drawn from all parts of Australia. It is not&lt;br /&gt;
to be expected that they will agree on every proposal or be able to&lt;br /&gt;
: gree with one another always. They always agree on objectives, but&lt;br /&gt;
sometimes nor on the methods to achieve those objectives. That doe.&lt;br /&gt;
not harm the Labour movement. No party can live unless it is progressive&lt;br /&gt;
and pressing forward. It must go onwards or die. The con-&lt;br /&gt;
: servative parties of this country, because of the diverse interests and&lt;br /&gt;
animositie. which exist between persons opposed to Labour methods,&lt;br /&gt;
are not able to survive. The solidarity of this movement, particularly&lt;br /&gt;
in the war period, was the solidarity necessary for the welfare and preservation&lt;br /&gt;
of this country.&lt;br /&gt;
In regard to international affairs, our relations with other countries,&lt;br /&gt;
our defence policy and the building up of industries are some&lt;br /&gt;
, f the great problems only Labour governments are capable of solving.&lt;br /&gt;
Relations with other nations of the world must go through the Federal&lt;br /&gt;
Government. The Federal Labour party should know the feelings and&lt;br /&gt;
v. iews of the people we represent. Out of these conferences you will&lt;br /&gt;
give an indication to the Federal Labour party of your outlook on the&lt;br /&gt;
questions of the future. I do not think that some persons in Australia&lt;br /&gt;
fully realize the changed order in the world to-day. We have a proud&lt;br /&gt;
history, but we must not live in the past. The methods of 20 years&lt;br /&gt;
ngo are no good to-day. We live in a troubled world. We must be&lt;br /&gt;
prepared to keep to the fundamentals of the Labour party, but always&lt;br /&gt;
be prepared to modify the general outlook of our views on the affairs&lt;br /&gt;
of the world and, in turn, on our own affairs as the affairs of the world&lt;br /&gt;
affect us. We have to prepare to build a stronger nation in the Pacific&lt;br /&gt;
than to-day, and try to look into the future. Many think just of to-day&lt;br /&gt;
or just a year or two ahead. They feel that some particular features&lt;br /&gt;
affect them personally and that they are the only ones that matter.&lt;br /&gt;
I ask those persons to give some thought to overseas affairs and the&lt;br /&gt;
future of this country. We must keep ourselves in close contact with&lt;br /&gt;
the affairs of the world and in close contact with other nations. I&lt;br /&gt;
believe that only by close co-operation with the people of Great&lt;br /&gt;
Britain and the people of America-indeed, with the English-speaking&lt;br /&gt;
peoples of the world-can -we keep world peace in the future.&lt;br /&gt;
" It may be that the Australian Government has had differences&lt;br /&gt;
with Great Britain on administrative matters. Whatever those differences&lt;br /&gt;
and however justifiable, one fact is completely clear-we in the &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pacific must maintain a close co-operation not only with America but&lt;br /&gt;
with Great Britain. Regarding Great Britain, apart from sentimental&lt;br /&gt;
reasons, a great material factor applies. Great Britain has been the&lt;br /&gt;
greatest market for Australian primary product exports, and if only for&lt;br /&gt;
material reasons close co-oppration with Great Britain for trade is&lt;br /&gt;
essential. " It is a great thing in the Labour movement to feel that we take&lt;br /&gt;
in thousands of unions and branches. Men and women are working&lt;br /&gt;
for no reward to themselves ' but to give effect to the wishes of the Labour&lt;br /&gt;
movement. It is a great thing and a great comfort for any one leading&lt;br /&gt;
a party or associated in some task of leadership of a party to know&lt;br /&gt;
that these men and women support them. I know that in Australia&lt;br /&gt;
hundred. of thousands have been in the Labour movement for 30 or&lt;br /&gt;
years without seeking any reward for themselves but for the Labour&lt;br /&gt;
movement to be placed in power. The future of this country and the&lt;br /&gt;
future of the Labour movement rest with the people themselves. Every&lt;br /&gt;
oC e must bhe prepared, whatever be his calling, whatever his duty, in&lt;br /&gt;
this timc. of opportunities, to give of his very best. There is only one&lt;br /&gt;
way of achieving success and that way is hard work. I ask nothing&lt;br /&gt;
more of the movement but to stick solidly together. It has been trusted&lt;br /&gt;
lby the peophl to perform the great tasks connected with the problems&lt;br /&gt;
of the war and to carry on the tasks associated with the transition into&lt;br /&gt;
peace and plan for the years ahead. That is the great trust the people&lt;br /&gt;
have placed in us. and I ask the Labour movement to give to those&lt;br /&gt;
chosen to lead all the help that cun be given for the needs of the community&lt;br /&gt;
and the needs of the nation. By that means can the Labour&lt;br /&gt;
movement remain great. If that is done, I have no fear that the&lt;br /&gt;
Labour movement will go on growing stronger, and greater, in the&lt;br /&gt;
interests of Australia."&lt;br /&gt;
ACTING MINISTER FOR INFORMATION.&lt;br /&gt;
On 20th June, 1947, Mr. Chiflcy said--&lt;br /&gt;
The Minister for Munitions ( Senator Armstrong) will act as&lt;br /&gt;
Minister for Immigration and Minister for Information during the&lt;br /&gt;
absence overseas of Mr. Calwell from 19th June. 1947. until his&lt;br /&gt;
return. ACTING MINISTER FOR EXTERNAL AFFAIRS.&lt;br /&gt;
On Srh July, 1947, the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr. Evatt)&lt;br /&gt;
said that he would leave Sydney on 11th July, 1947, for Japan, where&lt;br /&gt;
he would be the guest of the Supreme Commander, Allied Powers&lt;br /&gt;
( General MacArthur). While in Japan, he would visit the. Australian&lt;br /&gt;
forces at Kure and consult with General MacArthur and the Australian&lt;br /&gt;
representatives to ascertain at first hand facts essential to the consideration&lt;br /&gt;
of the peace settlement with Japan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 14th July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said&lt;br /&gt;
The Minister for Health ( Senator McKenna) will act as Attorney-&lt;br /&gt;
General from 11th July, 1947, and I will act as Minister for External&lt;br /&gt;
Affairs during the temporary absence overseas of Dr. Evatt."&lt;br /&gt;
CONVERSION LOAN.&lt;br /&gt;
NEW YORK OPERATION, JUNE, 1947.&lt;br /&gt;
On 15th June, 1947, the Prime 11inister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
A Commonwealth loan has been issued in New York for 38,000,000&lt;br /&gt;
dollars to pay off a Commonwealth 5 per cent. loan that matures in&lt;br /&gt;
1957, but over which an option of redemption is being exercised.&lt;br /&gt;
The terms of the new loan provide for a coupon rate of 31 per&lt;br /&gt;
cent. for ten years as to 19,000,000 dollars and -a coupon rate of 31 per&lt;br /&gt;
cent. for 20 years as to 19,000,000 dollars, the issue price to the public&lt;br /&gt;
in both cases being 974 per cent. The yield to the investor in the case&lt;br /&gt;
of the 31 per cent. bonds will be &#339; 3 11s. 1d. and for the 3 per cent.&lt;br /&gt;
bonds &#339; 3 13s. 7d.&lt;br /&gt;
The new loan will result in a ; aving of interest to the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
and to the Governments of Victoria, Queensland, South Australia,&lt;br /&gt;
Western Australia and Tasmania."&lt;br /&gt;
NEW YORK OPERATIONS, 1946-47.&lt;br /&gt;
On 14th July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
In July, 1946, Australia commenced to refinance American loans&lt;br /&gt;
for which there was an option of redemption before maturity dates.&lt;br /&gt;
Total loans raised by the Commonwealth and the States in respect of&lt;br /&gt;
which amounts were outstanding at 30th June, 1946, amounted to&lt;br /&gt;
200,000,000 dollars, of which there was an option of redemption by&lt;br /&gt;
September, 1947, of 128,000,000 dollars. The summary of operations&lt;br /&gt;
since July, 1946, is:-&lt;br /&gt;
Date M06e&#339; lAmnIt R a te. Period. I Pric r Prie~. t Loan R&lt;br /&gt;
Ruised. to Price.&lt;br /&gt;
Million Per&lt;br /&gt;
dollars. cent. Years.&lt;br /&gt;
August, 1946 20 3-10 100 984 New Soutit \ Vales, 5 pcr&lt;br /&gt;
cent.&lt;br /&gt;
December, 1946.. 25 3k 20 981 9819 New South \ a&#190; leR, 5 per&lt;br /&gt;
cent. 18M. dollars;&lt;br /&gt;
Queensland, 6 per cent.&lt;br /&gt;
-7M. dollars&lt;br /&gt;
February, 1947 45 31 15 99 96 CommonweAlth, 4j per&lt;br /&gt;
cent.&lt;br /&gt;
July, 1947 19 31 10 971 Commonwealth, 5 per&lt;br /&gt;
19 3j 20 97j cent.&lt;br /&gt;
" The first three operations were highly successful, the amount&lt;br /&gt;
underwritten being promptly absorbed by investors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;" The last operation has not sold as promptly as the previous issues,&lt;br /&gt;
due to a variety of reasons, the factors chiefly responsible being the&lt;br /&gt;
disturbed international situation. Whereas honds were underwritten&lt;br /&gt;
for the full amount, the underwriters were left with 2,000,000 dollars&lt;br /&gt;
of the short term and 6,500,000 dollars of the long term when the loan&lt;br /&gt;
closed on 8-th July, 1947. Sales of these securities in large parcels&lt;br /&gt;
resulted in a heavy fall on the market. At the close of business on 11th&lt;br /&gt;
July, 1947. only -2,( iOO, 000 dollars of the long term issue was&lt;br /&gt;
unplaced, the whole of the short term having been sold. The short&lt;br /&gt;
term arc selling at approximately 96 dollars and the long term at&lt;br /&gt;
94 dollars. Total interest saving over aill operations for the abovementioned&lt;br /&gt;
loans is about' 2,000.000 dollars a year.&lt;br /&gt;
" There will be no further operations by the Commonwealth on&lt;br /&gt;
the New York miarket before 1952."&lt;br /&gt;
WHEAT STABILIZATION SCHEME.&lt;br /&gt;
POST-WAR--FEDERATION PROPOSAL.&lt;br /&gt;
On 19th June, 1947, the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Pollard),&lt;br /&gt;
said that representatives of the Australian Wheat Growers Federation&lt;br /&gt;
from New South Wales, Victoria and South Australia had placed&lt;br /&gt;
proposals before him for amendments to the Government's five years&lt;br /&gt;
wheat stabilization plan. The federation asked that the guaranteed&lt;br /&gt;
floor price for wheat be based on the cost of the production, which would&lt;br /&gt;
include a remunerative wage for the grower and interest on capital&lt;br /&gt;
involved. It asked that the price of wheat for local consumption&lt;br /&gt;
as flour should be based on a cost plus principle, subject to immediate&lt;br /&gt;
and periodic review and adjustment in accordance with fluctuations in&lt;br /&gt;
cost. TJhe federation's request that the plan should not begin until the&lt;br /&gt;
marketing of the crop subsequent to its proposed amended plan coming&lt;br /&gt;
into effect would mean that the present plan as it affected 1945-46&lt;br /&gt;
and 1946-47 crops would be abandoned. It might also require the&lt;br /&gt;
abandonment of the stabilization plan in respect of the 1947-48 harvest,&lt;br /&gt;
because it was likely that time would not permit the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
and the States to pass legislation through the respective Parliaments in&lt;br /&gt;
time to make it apply to that harvest.&lt;br /&gt;
He had told the deputation that if the Government was to go on&lt;br /&gt;
with stabilization it could be expected that when prices for wheat were&lt;br /&gt;
high growers should provide some reserves for periods when prices were&lt;br /&gt;
low. If they did so. the Government was prepared to back the plan's&lt;br /&gt;
operation. It could not exclude from the operation of the plan the&lt;br /&gt;
harvest marketed when prices, as at present, were abnormally high.&lt;br /&gt;
The Government would be prepared, however, to consider an extension&lt;br /&gt;
of the plan be-' yond the 1949-50 harvest. The present Act would enable&lt;br /&gt;
that to, be donne provided State Governments were agreeable. He would &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;consider recommending to the Government that the present plan. be&lt;br /&gt;
extended for two years with provision that a review be made during&lt;br /&gt;
the period to determine whether it should be extended for a further&lt;br /&gt;
three years, making ten years in all.&lt;br /&gt;
POST-WAR PRODUCTION COSTS, INQUIRY.&lt;br /&gt;
On 4th July, 1947, Mr. Pollard said-&lt;br /&gt;
" The chairman of the Wheat Costs of Production Committee&lt;br /&gt;
informs me that over 3,000 questionaires were issued at random to&lt;br /&gt;
wheat farmers and that only 250 have been completed and returned.&lt;br /&gt;
I have informed the committee that I would not ask it to make a&lt;br /&gt;
report if it were of the opinion that the facts before it were not sufficient&lt;br /&gt;
to give a true picture of the industry. I ask wheat-growers to fill. in&lt;br /&gt;
the questionnaires and return them without delay."&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 116, page 30; No. 123, page 28.)&lt;br /&gt;
ACREAGE-1947-48.&lt;br /&gt;
On 29th July, 1947, Mr. Pollard said that Australian wheat sowings,&lt;br /&gt;
which had declined heavily during the war, had now appreciated, and&lt;br /&gt;
for 1947-48 the acreage sown would be 15,500,000 acres, compared with&lt;br /&gt;
: in average of 13,303,000 acres during the 10 years prior to the war.&lt;br /&gt;
FIGHTING FORCES.&lt;br /&gt;
CAT'IONAL SERVICES-RECONSTRCT I ON&lt;br /&gt;
TRAINING SCHEME, FIGURES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 21st June, 1947, the Minister for Labour ( Mr. Holloway) said&lt;br /&gt;
that at 23rd May, 1947, 135,648 ex-service personnel had either begun&lt;br /&gt;
training, completed training, or had been placed in employment as&lt;br /&gt;
per cent. efficient and were completing their training on the job, or&lt;br /&gt;
were still carrying on their training in the training centres under the&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth Reconstruction Training Scheme.&lt;br /&gt;
WAR SERVICE MORATORIUM-EXTENSION.&lt;br /&gt;
Oni 2nd July, 1047, the Prime Ministf-r ( Mr. Chitley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
" National Security ( War Service Moratorium) Regulations give&lt;br /&gt;
l&amp;gt; ecial rights and protection in tenancy matters to protected persons'&lt;br /&gt;
The most important protection is a provision that a tenant who is a&lt;br /&gt;
' protected person cannot be evicted unless the lessor can show that&lt;br /&gt;
suitable alternative accommodation Ls or has been available to the tenant.&lt;br /&gt;
discharged member of the forces is a protected person&lt;br /&gt;
SCabinet decided to-day that the period of p: ruotrion muder the&lt;br /&gt;
regulations to dis:: harged members of the force.; tlhir ld: ne'ila nts b"&lt;br /&gt;
extended from two years to three years.&lt;br /&gt;
The Re-establishment and Employment Act providis that land&lt;br /&gt;
owned . by a member of the forces shall not be acquired compulsorily&lt;br /&gt;
without the consent of the Attorney-General. Cabinet decided to-day&lt;br /&gt;
that the period of protection to discharged member. of the forces he&lt;br /&gt;
ixtended from one year to two years." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RETURNED FROM ACTIVE SERVICE BADGE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 17th July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
" When the badge was introduced in 1941 it \ was laid down&lt;br /&gt;
that it would be issued at the time of discharge or, in the cast,&lt;br /&gt;
of the Royal Australian Navy, at the cessation of hostilities:&lt;br /&gt;
Recently it has been represented that eligible serving members&lt;br /&gt;
of the forces who may be permitted to wear civilian clothes were at&lt;br /&gt;
a disadvantage by comparison with discharged members because they&lt;br /&gt;
were not in possession of the appropriate emblem denoting their having&lt;br /&gt;
participated in active service. It has been decided that the authority&lt;br /&gt;
under which eligible personnel who are still serving in the Royal&lt;br /&gt;
Australian Navy may be issued with the ' Returned from Active&lt;br /&gt;
Service' badge shall be extended to apply to eligible serving members&lt;br /&gt;
of the Australian Military Forces and the Royal Australian Air Force."&lt;br /&gt;
PEACE.&lt;br /&gt;
JAPAN-WHALING EXPEDITION.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2sird June, 1947, the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr. Evatt&lt;br /&gt;
said-On 7th August, 1946, the Japanese Government was authorized&lt;br /&gt;
by S. C. A. P. to undertake a whaling expedition to the Antarctic during&lt;br /&gt;
the 1946-47 season. Principal reasons given for the authorization were&lt;br /&gt;
. hortage of food in Japan and world shortage of oils and fats. There&lt;br /&gt;
was no prior consultation with interested Allied Governments, such as&lt;br /&gt;
\ nstralia, Britain, New Zealand and Norway.&lt;br /&gt;
The Australian Government immediately made strong representations&lt;br /&gt;
to the United States on grounds of past prejudicial action by&lt;br /&gt;
Japanese ships to Australian security, on earlier violations by the&lt;br /&gt;
Japanese cf international whaling regulations, and on the inefficiency&lt;br /&gt;
and wastefulness of Japanese methods. It was a matter for special&lt;br /&gt;
concern to Australia that decisions of this kind should be made while&lt;br /&gt;
the occupation of Japan was still proceeding and in advance of the&lt;br /&gt;
peace settlement, and without reference to the overall question of&lt;br /&gt;
reparations. The Australian prntest was supported by Norway, Britain&lt;br /&gt;
aind New Zealand.&lt;br /&gt;
After the Australian representations, it was agreed that an Australian&lt;br /&gt;
observer should accompany the expedition; furthermore, that&lt;br /&gt;
an international flag should be substituted for Japanese insignia; that&lt;br /&gt;
the routes to be taken by the expedition to and from the Antarctic&lt;br /&gt;
should be notified to interested governments and that the oil obtained&lt;br /&gt;
as a result of the expedition should be subject to allocation by the International&lt;br /&gt;
Emergency Food Council. Authorization of the expedition&lt;br /&gt;
became operative only for the 1946-47 season, the United States undertalking&lt;br /&gt;
that other interested governments would be fully consulted should &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;: ny further Japanese activities outside Japanese wa. ters be contemplated.&lt;br /&gt;
The United States agreed that the future of the Japanese whaling&lt;br /&gt;
industry and the disposal of Japanese whaling equipment was a&lt;br /&gt;
matter for decision by the Allies.&lt;br /&gt;
" The Australian Government is opposed to the re-establishment&lt;br /&gt;
of the Japanese whaling industry in Antarctic waters. Such re-establishment,&lt;br /&gt;
which in effect means the creation again of naval potential, is&lt;br /&gt;
ipposed to a just settlement with Japan and should be strenuously&lt;br /&gt;
resisted by every Allied country which contributed to victory in the&lt;br /&gt;
Pacific war. When it became apparent recently that, notwithstanding&lt;br /&gt;
the undertaking regarding consultation and the adverse report by the&lt;br /&gt;
Australian observer with . the first expedition, it was proposed to send a&lt;br /&gt;
second Japanese expedition to the Antarctic, the Australian Government&lt;br /&gt;
made the positive and practical suggestion to the United States&lt;br /&gt;
that a unit of the Japanese whaling fleet be operated by Australia, with&lt;br /&gt;
the aid of Britain, New Zealand and Norway. Food, fats and oils&lt;br /&gt;
from the expedition would be at the disposal of S. C. A. P. for distribution.&lt;br /&gt;
The Australian offer was communicated to the United States&lt;br /&gt;
State Department, and while under consideration the announcement of&lt;br /&gt;
a second expedition was made.&lt;br /&gt;
The decision of 22nd June, 1947, to approve of a second Japanese&lt;br /&gt;
whaling expedition for 1947-48, thereby by-passing . the Far Eastern&lt;br /&gt;
Commission, which alone is supposed to determine questions of policy&lt;br /&gt;
and which actually has this matter on its business sheet for 26th June,&lt;br /&gt;
is opposed to the best long-term Allied interests. The Australian&lt;br /&gt;
Government intends to press this question in the Far Eastern Commission&lt;br /&gt;
to secure a review of the present proposal.&lt;br /&gt;
" The ultimate disposition of Japanese whaling facilities and equipmnent,&lt;br /&gt;
as well as the question of the future of the Japanese whaling&lt;br /&gt;
industry, must be a matter for Allied consultation and decision. The&lt;br /&gt;
appropriate place for any decision that may be taken is the peace&lt;br /&gt;
table." JAPAN-BRITISH COMMONWEALTH CONFERENCE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 23rd June, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
The . preliminary conference of British Commonwealth countries&lt;br /&gt;
to discuss the peace treaty with Japan will meet in Canberra on 26th&lt;br /&gt;
August, 1947." JAPAN-ADVISORY COMMITTEE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 8th July, 1947, Dr. Evatt said that he was establishing an&lt;br /&gt;
ndvisory committee to examine questions related to the Japanese peace&lt;br /&gt;
settlement. The committee would meet under the chairmanship of Sir&lt;br /&gt;
Frederic Eggleston, formerly Australian Minister to China and later &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to the United States. Sir Frederic had been working on problems&lt;br /&gt;
related to the Japanese settlement in conjunction with departmental&lt;br /&gt;
officers both at Canberra and abroad. The committee would include&lt;br /&gt;
members of Parliament in addition to a representative group of Australians&lt;br /&gt;
versed in one aspect or another of the subject.&lt;br /&gt;
JAPAN-PROPOSED UNITED STATES MEETING.&lt;br /&gt;
On 17th July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
Australia is always prepared to take part in any discussions that&lt;br /&gt;
will expedite the Pacific peace settlement and ' appreciates the present&lt;br /&gt;
proposal of the United States Government to hold a conference of eleven&lt;br /&gt;
nations on 19th August, 1947. But the date is entirely unsuitable to&lt;br /&gt;
Australia in view of the British Commonwealth conference on 26th&lt;br /&gt;
August, 1947."&lt;br /&gt;
On 18th July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
Australia will attend the coliference convened by the United&lt;br /&gt;
States Government on the Japanese peace settlement, but on the date&lt;br /&gt;
will depend which Minister will attend, and whether the Minister for&lt;br /&gt;
External Affairs ( Dr. Evatt) can fit in his engagements with the&lt;br /&gt;
conference." NATIONAL THEATRE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 23rd June, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chiflcy) saidpropose&lt;br /&gt;
to appoint a committee soon after Parliament reassembles&lt;br /&gt;
in September, 1947, to examine the possibility of establishing&lt;br /&gt;
a national theatre at Canberra. Some persons believe that the theatre&lt;br /&gt;
is for educational purposes but I think it should also have an entertainment&lt;br /&gt;
value as well. I believe that it would be possible to have a small&lt;br /&gt;
theatre to which leading players in companies from the States could be&lt;br /&gt;
hrought to give performances."&lt;br /&gt;
.( For earlier references, please see No. 98, page 13.)&lt;br /&gt;
MOTOR CAR PRODUCTION.&lt;br /&gt;
CAR CHASSIS IMPORTS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 24th June, 1947, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Courtice)&lt;br /&gt;
; nlnounced that imports of pressed metal body panels, not fabricated&lt;br /&gt;
beyond trimming of the edges, would be permitted for use in the manufacture&lt;br /&gt;
in Australia of bodies for car and truck chassis, provided the&lt;br /&gt;
pane! s were shlipped from the country of origin to Australia on or&lt;br /&gt;
before 31st December, 1947. The imports were permitted because of the&lt;br /&gt;
present shortage of steel sheets suitable for motor vehicle body manufacture&lt;br /&gt;
and to assist in making the maximum number of motor vehicles&lt;br /&gt;
available to Australian essential users in the shortest possible time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JAPAN.&lt;br /&gt;
TRADE-PRIVATE TRADING.&lt;br /&gt;
On 26th June, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
The control authorities in Japan have fixed 15th August, 1947, as&lt;br /&gt;
the date on which the resumption of private international commercial&lt;br /&gt;
relations with Japan will be authorized. Because of accommodation&lt;br /&gt;
difficulties, only 400 private trade representatives will be allowed entry&lt;br /&gt;
into Japan in the initial stages and the length of their stay will be&lt;br /&gt;
limited to 21 days unless arrangements are made by the Governments&lt;br /&gt;
concerned with the control authorities for an extension of this period.&lt;br /&gt;
:\ ustralia has been provisionially allotted a quota of 24 representatives.&lt;br /&gt;
" An inter-departmental committee is engaged in considering the&lt;br /&gt;
priority to be accorded to private traders who desire to visit Japan and&lt;br /&gt;
interested persons are invited to submit applications before 5th July,&lt;br /&gt;
1947. Traders who desire to arrange for the purchase of Japanese&lt;br /&gt;
goods should submit full particulars to the Department of Trade and&lt;br /&gt;
C: ustoms, while those interested in selling goods to Japan should furnish&lt;br /&gt;
, letails to the Department of Commerce and Agriculture.&lt;br /&gt;
" In the early stages private trade will not reach substantial proportions.&lt;br /&gt;
Because of prior commitments, the control authorities have&lt;br /&gt;
indicated that cotton textiles, raw silk and tea will not be available&lt;br /&gt;
immediately for s-ale to private traders. The Commonwealth Government&lt;br /&gt;
has arranged for the purchase of 12,000,000 yards of cotton textiles&lt;br /&gt;
and quantities of raw silk and will continue these purchases until&lt;br /&gt;
private traders are permitted to operate. Purchases on private account&lt;br /&gt;
will be governed -by the range and quantity of goods available and the&lt;br /&gt;
limitations imposed by the Australian import licensing system.&lt;br /&gt;
Australian exports to Japan are likely to be restricted to wool and&lt;br /&gt;
a; few minor commodities not subject to international control nor&lt;br /&gt;
covered by long-term contracts with other countries."&lt;br /&gt;
On 16th July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
" A number of applications have been received from businessmen&lt;br /&gt;
who desire to send representatives to Japan. A selection has been made&lt;br /&gt;
by an inter-departmental committee to determine the limited number&lt;br /&gt;
who will comprise the first party to visit Japan. The interests concerned&lt;br /&gt;
will be notified of the selections at -an early date.&lt;br /&gt;
Priority has been accorded to firms which ' had extensive pre-war&lt;br /&gt;
interests in Japanese trade and representatives of associations and&lt;br /&gt;
manufacturers who are anxious to obtain supplies of essential commodities&lt;br /&gt;
for use in Australian industry.&lt;br /&gt;
" An overall consideration has been the class of goods in which it&lt;br /&gt;
is desired to trade. In this connexion, when private trade with Japan&lt;br /&gt;
is resumed, raw silk and cotton textiles will not be available for purchase&lt;br /&gt;
by private traders immediately. Merchant-to-merchant trading will be&lt;br /&gt;
permitted in other goods, but imports to Australia will be subject to&lt;br /&gt;
licensing control on the basis at present accorded to imports from hard &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;currency areas. Import licences will be granted only for essential goods&lt;br /&gt;
which are not available in adequate quantities from local or sterling&lt;br /&gt;
sources of supply. Licences will not be granted for importation of fancy&lt;br /&gt;
goods, toys, crockery and other less essential goods that featured in prewar&lt;br /&gt;
trade with Japan.&lt;br /&gt;
As each party will be allowed to stay in Japan for only a limited&lt;br /&gt;
ipriod, further opportunities will occur for visits by Australian business&lt;br /&gt;
representatives. Commercial interests not included in the first party&lt;br /&gt;
will receive consideration in subsequent parties."&lt;br /&gt;
TRADE-WOOL.&lt;br /&gt;
On l2nd July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
Following negotiations . between the Comnimonwealth Government&lt;br /&gt;
and the Supreme Command Allied Powers in Japan, 7,481 bales of particular&lt;br /&gt;
types of low grade wool were shipped to Japan in May, 1947.&lt;br /&gt;
Arrangements were made for payment in dollars in New York as a&lt;br /&gt;
set-off against the purchase price of raw silk obtained in Japan by the&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth Government.&lt;br /&gt;
Following representations by Cabinet decided . to-day that&lt;br /&gt;
further negotiations be instituted for the sale of somewhat better types&lt;br /&gt;
of wool. The Minister for Commerce ( Mr. Pollard) has been authorized&lt;br /&gt;
to take up the negotiations and, if successful, . the Australian Wool&lt;br /&gt;
Realization Commission will larrange for the purchase and shipment bf&lt;br /&gt;
the wool to Japan."&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 123, page 36; No. 124, page 22;&lt;br /&gt;
No. 125, page 29.)&lt;br /&gt;
RECONSTRUCTION.&lt;br /&gt;
U. N. R. R. A.-AUSTRALIA'S PART.&lt;br /&gt;
On 30th June, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chlifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
" I have to-day received the following message from the Director-&lt;br /&gt;
General of U. N. R. R. A. at Washington ( Major-General Lowell W.&lt;br /&gt;
Rooks):-" To-day U. N. R. R. A.' s operations substantially come to an end in&lt;br /&gt;
Europe. In a public statement I have referred to the results achieved&lt;br /&gt;
by this international organization and to the pro. blems which still&lt;br /&gt;
confront the world in restoring its economy.&lt;br /&gt;
I should like to take this opportunity of extending to the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
Government and to the people of Australia the great appreciation&lt;br /&gt;
for the generous and effective contribution they have made to the&lt;br /&gt;
work of this organization. Those contributions, with similar assistance&lt;br /&gt;
from other uninvaded members of the United Nations, have provided&lt;br /&gt;
the means of saving the lives of endless millions of people in the war&lt;br /&gt;
devastated countries. From its experience, U. N. R. R. A. knows how&lt;br /&gt;
much that assistance h'as been appreciated, and there exists to-day in &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the hearts of millions of people throughout the world a very real&lt;br /&gt;
gratitude to the people of Australia for the supplies and services they&lt;br /&gt;
have received through the organization of U. N. R. R. A.&lt;br /&gt;
I should like to thank you also for the provision of so many fine and&lt;br /&gt;
experienced meu and women to serve with U. N. R. R. A. in many parts&lt;br /&gt;
of the world. They have served with distinction and success and have&lt;br /&gt;
dlone much to enhance the reputation of their country.&lt;br /&gt;
U. N. R. R. A. has done its best to carry out the instructions of the&lt;br /&gt;
United Nations in commencing the work of economic recovery in many&lt;br /&gt;
parts of the world. U. N. R. R. A. trusts that this work will be carried on&lt;br /&gt;
quickly and effectively, realizing that one of the essentials of world&lt;br /&gt;
peace is thatr rea. onable economic conditions shall exist in all countries."&lt;br /&gt;
WOMEN'S WAR ORGANIZATIONS.&lt;br /&gt;
W. A. A. A. F.-CESSATION.&lt;br /&gt;
On 30th June, 1947, the Minister for Air ( Mr. Drakeford) said&lt;br /&gt;
that the Women's Auxiliary Australian Air Force, which had a peak&lt;br /&gt;
strength of 26.245, had ceased to function that day.&lt;br /&gt;
PRICES.&lt;br /&gt;
GOODS DECLARED "-BANANAS, REVOCATION.&lt;br /&gt;
On 1st July, 1947, the Minister for Customs ( Senator Courtice)&lt;br /&gt;
announced that it had been decided to lift growers' ceilings on bananas.&lt;br /&gt;
Retail margins on bananas would continue to be fixed. Wholesale prices&lt;br /&gt;
would be kept under notice and control would be re-imposed if there&lt;br /&gt;
was any suggestion of exploitation of the market.&lt;br /&gt;
GOODS DECLARED "-PINEAPPLES, REVOCATION.&lt;br /&gt;
On 1st July, 1947, Senator Courtice announced that it had been&lt;br /&gt;
decided to lift growers' ceilings on pineapples. Retail margins on&lt;br /&gt;
pineapples would continue to be fixed. If prices rose to a level that&lt;br /&gt;
suggested exploitation, consideration would be given to re-imposing&lt;br /&gt;
controls. CIVIL AVIATION.&lt;br /&gt;
BRITAIN-AUSTRALIA SERVICE-QANTAS LTD.,&lt;br /&gt;
AGREEMENT, DIRECTORS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
Following the conclusion of the agreement by which Qantas&lt;br /&gt;
Empire Airways Ltd., has been taken over by the Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
Government, Cabinet decided to-day to appoint Mr. W. H. Fysh as&lt;br /&gt;
general manager, with the vice-chairman of the Australian National&lt;br /&gt;
Airlines Commission ( Mr. W. C. Taylor), the Treasury member of that&lt;br /&gt;
commission ( Mr. G. P. N. Watt) and Sir Keith Smith as members&lt;br /&gt;
of the boai'd of directors."&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 123, page &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;POST-WAR-INTERNAL ROUTES, AIRWAYS CHARGES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 4th July, 1947, the Minister for Civil Aviation ( Mr. Drakeford)&lt;br /&gt;
announced that the Government had decided to introduce charges for the&lt;br /&gt;
use by operators of aircraft of airways facilities provided by the&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth. Modern air transport demanded increasing ground&lt;br /&gt;
facilities, aeradio, and navigational aids and meteorological services,&lt;br /&gt;
and it had become customary throughout the world for the authority&lt;br /&gt;
providing the airways facilities to make charges for their use, designed&lt;br /&gt;
to recoup part of the expenditure. It had been" decided that a system&lt;br /&gt;
of air route charges should be applied on regular services regardless of&lt;br /&gt;
the number of landings involved. Aircraft used for purposes other&lt;br /&gt;
than regular airline services would be classified according to the nature&lt;br /&gt;
of the use to which they were put, and annual fees would be charged.&lt;br /&gt;
Payment of charges would be introduced as from 1st August, 1947.&lt;br /&gt;
On 25th July, 1947, Mr. Drakeford announced details of the system&lt;br /&gt;
of charges for the use of Commonwealth aerodromes and air route facilities&lt;br /&gt;
to he payable as from 1st August, 1947. It was estimated that the&lt;br /&gt;
charges would bring in about &#339; 300,000 a year, but that would recoup&lt;br /&gt;
the Commonwealth for only a small portion of its annual expenditure&lt;br /&gt;
on maintenance of air ports and airways facilities. Aircraft would be&lt;br /&gt;
divided into four classes-&lt;br /&gt;
Those used for purely private purposes: tlhoie used fir tle hllim. ris purpo. ses&lt;br /&gt;
of the owner: those used for reiumnerative purposes other th: rin n r I,; gilari rline&lt;br /&gt;
and those used for the operation of airline services.&lt;br /&gt;
The first three classes would pay an annual fee which would be&lt;br /&gt;
lowest in the private category and progressively higher in the other two&lt;br /&gt;
classes. The fee would be based on the weight of the aircraft and would&lt;br /&gt;
cover the use of any aerodromes and airways facilities. Examples of the&lt;br /&gt;
annual charges payable by owners of aircraft in eacl of the three classes&lt;br /&gt;
were:-SClass 1. Clw 2. Class 3.&lt;br /&gt;
t d.&lt;br /&gt;
Tiger Moth 3 5 1 0 9 15 0&lt;br /&gt;
D. H. 4 ( l) raon) 8 2 ti 17 5 0 25 7 6&lt;br /&gt;
Anson 14 12 6 29 5 0 43 17 6&lt;br /&gt;
Operators of aircraft used on regular aircraft services would not pay&lt;br /&gt;
the annual charges for those aircraft but would pay a charge in respect&lt;br /&gt;
of each route unit traversed. To determine the number of units the&lt;br /&gt;
routes had been classified having regard to their length, the number of&lt;br /&gt;
aerodromes and emergency landing ground and the availability of&lt;br /&gt;
navigational aids. The comparatively short Melbourne-Sydney stage&lt;br /&gt;
was rated as a two-unit route, while a much longer but less highly&lt;br /&gt;
developed route such as the Derby-Kimberley Stations route was classified&lt;br /&gt;
as one unit. A basic charge had been fixed for each type of aircraft &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a~ nd the amnount payable for c ach flight would be the basic charge&lt;br /&gt;
multiplied by the number of units, traversed. Examples of the charges&lt;br /&gt;
were: M15esi1. 3 W. u y. Adelaide or Hohart-D. C. 3. &#339; 4 14S. lid.-D. U. 4.&lt;br /&gt;
Adelaide to Pertli-D. C. 3. &#339; 9 9s.; &#339; 27 11.&lt;br /&gt;
Sydney to Tamnworth-Aniioi, I Is. 3d.&lt;br /&gt;
Brisbane to Cbarleville-D. C. 3, f2 7 s. 3
Melbourne or Adelaide to Broken Hill-D. C. 3, &#339; 2 3d.&lt;br /&gt;
Perth to Wiluna-D. H. 89, 7s. 6d.&lt;br /&gt;
Uiuuurr-Nornaiton-~ o~ urryD. H83.3s. fid.&lt;br /&gt;
Alice SprYin1' S-Wynidhani-Alicc Springs-D. H. 90. I ( h.&lt;br /&gt;
Cairns : to Horn Island-D. H. 89, 7s. 6d.&lt;br /&gt;
Trans-Australia. Airlines andl Qantas Empire Airways Ltd. would&lt;br /&gt;
pay the charges on the Same basis as other airline operators.&lt;br /&gt;
The charges did not apply to aircraft used on regular international&lt;br /&gt;
nir services. Charges for-those services would be promnulgated later.&lt;br /&gt;
I. C. A. O.-AUSTRALJAN REPRESENTATIVE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 10th July, 1947, Mr. Drakeford announced that Dr. K. N. . E.&lt;br /&gt;
Bradfield had been appointed Australian representative at the International&lt;br /&gt;
Civil Aviation Organization's head-quarters at Montreal,&lt;br /&gt;
Clanada. INTIERN~ AL ROU't'ES-LICENCES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 25th July, 1947, Mr. Drakeford announced that the interdepartmental&lt;br /&gt;
committee set up to consider applications for licences&lt;br /&gt;
to operate internal air services had made recommendations as follows.-&lt;br /&gt;
Nsw SOUTH WALES.-Sydney-Broken Hill with possible extension to Adelaide;&lt;br /&gt;
Sydniey-Taruworth-Gleui hInes; Sydney-Corowa; Sy( lney-Cootam undra-Griffith:&lt;br /&gt;
Sydney. Te niora-G rif Nth; Sydney-Old Bar-Kempsey-Coff's Harbour-Grafton-&lt;br /&gt;
Casino; Sydney--Jcrvis Bay; Toor-awcenahl-, Narrabri-Goondiwindi; Walget-St.&lt;br /&gt;
( 3ecrge; Bourke-Th argomnindith; Bourke-Wincannia and Bourke-Cobar-Parkes&lt;br /&gt;
Vic-roRIA.-Melo ure-Wat rrnainItool Melbotaune-Bairiisdale itid/ or Sale;&lt;br /&gt;
Melbourne-Ararat-Nhill: M. el hourrite-1e idll-Corowit and Melbounw~-Echuca-&lt;br /&gt;
Deniliquin-Hay. QUEBESiLsAbOn.--e -n ky-Fonit-MtchlI; Brisba ne-' ren terfield-G lei i&lt;br /&gt;
i nnes; Rockliani pton-Lon-reaclI: Townsville-Charters Towers-Jul ja Creek-&lt;br /&gt;
Cloncurry; Brishanp-Coolangatt a-Cats iino and Cairns -G eorge town -Croydon.&lt;br /&gt;
NORTHERN AUSTRALIA.&lt;br /&gt;
DEVELOPMENT COMMITTEE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
" In 1945, the Northern Australia Development Committee -was&lt;br /&gt;
appointed comprising representatives of the Commonwealth, Queensland&lt;br /&gt;
and Western Australian Governments. Matters of policy are canczidered&lt;br /&gt;
by the Minister for the Interior ( Mir. Johnson). the Premiers&lt;br /&gt;
, if Queenqland and Western Australia and myself. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;" The committee h-as prepared a comprehensive report dealing&lt;br /&gt;
specifically with general measures for the relief of disabilities; specific&lt;br /&gt;
measures for the development of industries; and measures necessary to&lt;br /&gt;
develop specific regions.&lt;br /&gt;
Cabinet decided to-day that a sub-committee, comprising the Minister&lt;br /&gt;
for the Interior, the Minister for Post-war Reconstruction and&lt;br /&gt;
myself as Treasurer and Acting Minister for Defence, should examine&lt;br /&gt;
the report -and recommendations of the committee, and report to&lt;br /&gt;
Cabinet." EXTERNAL TERRITORIES.&lt;br /&gt;
NEW GUINEA-PAPUA-WAR GRATUITY FOR NATIVES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
The question of payment of war gratuity for natives of New&lt;br /&gt;
Guinea and Papua was considered by the Parliamentary Committee&lt;br /&gt;
which furnished a report on the question of war gratuity. The outstanding&lt;br /&gt;
service rendered by these natives was fully recognized, but the&lt;br /&gt;
Iommittee was not in possession of sufficient information to enable a&lt;br /&gt;
recommendation to be made as to the appropriate method of rewarding&lt;br /&gt;
their service. The question has been since considered after consultation&lt;br /&gt;
with the Departments of External Territories, the Navy and the Army.&lt;br /&gt;
" C: abinet to-day approved of a gratuity for natives of New Guinea&lt;br /&gt;
and Papua who were enlisted as members of the forces, payment to be&lt;br /&gt;
at the rate of 5s. a month for each month of service; the gratuity not&lt;br /&gt;
to be paid for any period prior to 7th Pecember, 1941; no qualifying&lt;br /&gt;
period to be required; native members who have been discharged for&lt;br /&gt;
disciplinary reasons to be ineligible for the gratuity; payment to be&lt;br /&gt;
made as early as practicable.&lt;br /&gt;
An ex gratia payment has been approved, subject to the conditions&lt;br /&gt;
approved for natives enlisted in the forces, for the following classes&lt;br /&gt;
of civilian natives-members of the New Guinea Police Force and the&lt;br /&gt;
Royal Papuan Constabulary; civilians employed as combatant soldiers&lt;br /&gt;
by the Allied Intelligence Bureau prior to their enlistment in the " M&lt;br /&gt;
Special Unit Infantry Battalion on 1st February. 1945.'&lt;br /&gt;
SERVICE PAY RATES.&lt;br /&gt;
REPATRIATION-COMMISSION, APPOINTMENTS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
" Following the recent death of the Deputy Chairman of the&lt;br /&gt;
Repatriation Commission ( Mr. John Webster), Cabinet to-day&lt;br /&gt;
appointed Brigadier H. H. Hammer as a member of the commission&lt;br /&gt;
until 14th October, 1950. iMr. II. F. Gascoigne-Roy and Mr. T. S.&lt;br /&gt;
Hooks have be-en : iI. poinied A'scinmt CoTininissionrer; ninitil I13th July.&lt;br /&gt;
1950." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RATIONING.&lt;br /&gt;
SUGAR-REVOCATION.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifey) said-&lt;br /&gt;
" Cabinet decided to-day that rationing of sugar be abandoned forthwith.&lt;br /&gt;
The principal reasons for introducing sugar rationing no longer&lt;br /&gt;
; apply. Sugar rationing in Australia does not greatly help Britain. There&lt;br /&gt;
is an arrangement whereby the United States, Canada and Britain draw&lt;br /&gt;
equal per capita shares from the world's sugar supply. For every&lt;br /&gt;
10,000 tons of sugar contributed by Australia to the pool, Britain&lt;br /&gt;
draws only about 2,000 tons. Distribution of sugar is decided by the&lt;br /&gt;
World Emergency Food Council. World production of sugar showed a&lt;br /&gt;
marked increase in the 1946-47 season."&lt;br /&gt;
MEAT-CONTINUANCE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
Cabinet was informed to-day that representatives of the Meat and&lt;br /&gt;
Allied Trades Federation had asked the Minister for Comunerce ( Mr.&lt;br /&gt;
Pallard) and the Minister for Customs ( Senator Courtice) that rationing&lt;br /&gt;
and price control of meat should be removed from 15th August,&lt;br /&gt;
1947, that being the period of flush supply.&lt;br /&gt;
The meat position in Britain is acute and on : 3th .1 ine, 1947, the&lt;br /&gt;
Chancellor of the Exchequer ( Dr. Dalton) announced in the House of&lt;br /&gt;
Commons that there would be a further cut in the imeat ration from&lt;br /&gt;
is. 4d. worth a week ( including 4d. worth of canned meat) to is. 2d.&lt;br /&gt;
worth a week.&lt;br /&gt;
Cabinet decided that it was not possible to remove the controls.&lt;br /&gt;
It would be very wrong for the Commonwealth Government to permit&lt;br /&gt;
unrestricted consumption of meat when the British people are having&lt;br /&gt;
their meagre ration further reduced. The matter will be brought before&lt;br /&gt;
Cabinet again when there are indications that -upply of meat in Australia&lt;br /&gt;
will be sufficient to provide not only an unrestricted Au. l tralian&lt;br /&gt;
demand but an adequate amount for export to Brit: liii."&lt;br /&gt;
SHIPBUILDING.&lt;br /&gt;
IOST-WAR--DE-REQUISIT rONING.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
Cabinet decided to-day that interstate and intra-state -vessels ( but&lt;br /&gt;
not including passenger and other vessels required by and under charter&lt;br /&gt;
to the Navy Department) be de-requisitioned at the earliest possible&lt;br /&gt;
date and that the Minister for Shipping ( Senator Ashley) de-requisition&lt;br /&gt;
individual vessels as they terminate voyages and come into position&lt;br /&gt;
for re-delivery at home ports. But the Minister is empowered to defer&lt;br /&gt;
the de-requisitioning of particular vessels when such action is regarded&lt;br /&gt;
by him as essential to ensure efficient conduct of particular . rvice for&lt;br /&gt;
example the services to New Guinea and adjacent islands. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details associated with the matter will be dealt with by a Cabinet&lt;br /&gt;
sub-committee comprising Senator Ashley, the Minister for Customs&lt;br /&gt;
( Senator Courtice) and myself."&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 126, page 41.)&lt;br /&gt;
AUSTRALIAN MILITARY FORCES.&lt;br /&gt;
ROYAL MILITARY COLLEGE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 2nd July, 1947, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Chambers)&lt;br /&gt;
announced that the intake of cadets into the Royal Military College,&lt;br /&gt;
Duntroon. w'ould be increased in 1948 to 60 Australians and ten New&lt;br /&gt;
Zealanders. AUSTRALIAN BROADCASTING COMMISSION.&lt;br /&gt;
APPOINTMENTS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 3rd July, 1947, the Postmaster-General ( Senator Cameron)&lt;br /&gt;
announced that Mr. J. S. Hanlon and Professor J. D. G. Medley had&lt;br /&gt;
been appointed members of the Australian Broadcasting Commission&lt;br /&gt;
for three years from 1st July, 1947.&lt;br /&gt;
TARIFF.&lt;br /&gt;
EXPORTS-STANDARDS.&lt;br /&gt;
On ith July, 1947, the Minister for Commerce ( Mr. Pollard) said&lt;br /&gt;
that Australian manufacturers must pay greater attention to the sales&lt;br /&gt;
of their prodncts overseas if present industrial employment and production&lt;br /&gt;
levels were to be maintained. There were no grounds for complacency&lt;br /&gt;
in the fact that, despite export restrictions to ensure supplies&lt;br /&gt;
for local needs, value of manufactures exported would probably reach&lt;br /&gt;
&#339; 45,000,000. The figures had been achieved at a time when many competitive&lt;br /&gt;
European countries had not reached their full export capacity&lt;br /&gt;
of manufactures. Once local demand fell to normal, Australian surplus&lt;br /&gt;
production would have to be exported, or productive capacity reduced&lt;br /&gt;
with consequent unemployment. Manufacturers should remember that&lt;br /&gt;
not only Australian production would reduce local demands.&lt;br /&gt;
A good deal of Australian secondary industry had been built up&lt;br /&gt;
behind protective harriers but a considerable section of it had never&lt;br /&gt;
met the full shock of competition from imported goods, nor participated&lt;br /&gt;
in the exucting business of overseas trading. Overseas countries had&lt;br /&gt;
accepted Australian export methods to date, but would continue to do so&lt;br /&gt;
only if the export business procedures practised by many Australian&lt;br /&gt;
manufacturers and exporters were radically changed. To gain and&lt;br /&gt;
hold thl export markets they would soon require manufacturers and&lt;br /&gt;
exporters should conform to trading practices followed by competitor&lt;br /&gt;
nations. Goods should be strongly packed, correctly labelled and documented&lt;br /&gt;
and of competitive quality. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.32&lt;br /&gt;
NETHERLANDS EAST INDIES.&lt;br /&gt;
POLICY-MEDIATION.&lt;br /&gt;
On 9th July, 1947, the Minister for External Affair. i ( Dr. Evat)&lt;br /&gt;
said that the Australian Government welcomed reports that further progress&lt;br /&gt;
had been made towards a permanent settlement in Indonesia.&lt;br /&gt;
The de facto authority of the republic, on the basis of the Linggadjati&lt;br /&gt;
Agreement, which had been recognized by several goveriineiint, including&lt;br /&gt;
the British and United States Governments, and which the Australian&lt;br /&gt;
Government recognized, implied the acceptance by the Republican&lt;br /&gt;
Government of very great responsibility; and the Republican&lt;br /&gt;
Government, -as one of the negotiating parties and as a future essential&lt;br /&gt;
element in the interim Federal State, had accepted the responsibility.&lt;br /&gt;
The Australian Government sent representatives to Indonesia to assist&lt;br /&gt;
in solving problems related to the recommencement of trade. The Australian&lt;br /&gt;
Government wished both parties to understand that, if, in the&lt;br /&gt;
interests of agreement between Dutch and Republican authorities on&lt;br /&gt;
economic and political matters, the good offices of the Australian&lt;br /&gt;
Government would be helpful, Australia would continue to do anything&lt;br /&gt;
in its power to afford both the Netherlands and Indonesian authorities&lt;br /&gt;
its assistance. Further, the Australian Government would give to the&lt;br /&gt;
interim Federal Government, when established, advice and assistance in&lt;br /&gt;
such matters as trade, finance, communications, and rconorni&lt;br /&gt;
rehabilitation and development.&lt;br /&gt;
POL[ CY-SECRITRTY COUNCIL.&lt;br /&gt;
On 30th , July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
" The Australian Government has ilnstricted its representative on&lt;br /&gt;
the Security Council to draw the attention of the Security Council to&lt;br /&gt;
the situation in Indonesia under Article 39 of the United Nation.&lt;br /&gt;
Charter. Australia has taken action ten days after hostilities commenced&lt;br /&gt;
in rndonisia, because, in accordance with Article 33 of the&lt;br /&gt;
Charter. the parties to any dispute are obliged to seek a solution by&lt;br /&gt;
negotiation or mediatics. Strenuous attempts have been made in consultation&lt;br /&gt;
wilh other Governments, particularly Britain, United States&lt;br /&gt;
and India, to bring ' about a solution in that way. However, it is felt&lt;br /&gt;
that further delay is not justified because of the loss of life being&lt;br /&gt;
sustained. " The policy Australia has adopted in past disputes has been to&lt;br /&gt;
urge an investigation under Article 34 of the Charter before any decisions&lt;br /&gt;
are reached. However, the situation in Indonesia differs from&lt;br /&gt;
any previously brought before the council. Hostilities are being&lt;br /&gt;
carried on. Investigation is not required to establish the crucial fact.&lt;br /&gt;
and, before the Council determines further action, it is essential that&lt;br /&gt;
hostilities cease. For this reason, Australia has drawn the attention&lt;br /&gt;
of the Council to the situation under Article 39 of the Charter and&lt;br /&gt;
thereby gives power to the council immediately to order the cessation&lt;br /&gt;
of hostilities and subsequently to take such further steps as are necessary&lt;br /&gt;
to restore peace. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;33&lt;br /&gt;
This is the first time that this article has been invoked and it is&lt;br /&gt;
the hope of the Government, in taking this section, that not only will&lt;br /&gt;
hostilities cease, but that the Council will prove its worth in dealing&lt;br /&gt;
quickly and effectively with a situation of this kind.&lt;br /&gt;
" In making this move, Australia still maintains the judicial attitude&lt;br /&gt;
which it has . always maintained in considering any situation before&lt;br /&gt;
the council. No attempt will be made to pre-judge the issue, and discussion&lt;br /&gt;
of merits of the case will be avoided. The Australian representative&lt;br /&gt;
will ask first that the necessary steps be taken to terminate&lt;br /&gt;
hostilities, and, second, without discussing the merits of the situation,&lt;br /&gt;
that both parties act upon Article 17 of the Linggadjati Agreement,&lt;br /&gt;
which specifically provides that, in the event of disagreement between&lt;br /&gt;
the two parties arising out of the agreement, a third party will be&lt;br /&gt;
asked to arbitrate, or, failing that, the matter should be referred to&lt;br /&gt;
the Chief Justice of the International Court. If the Australian proposal&lt;br /&gt;
is given effect to without delay or debate on procedural issues,&lt;br /&gt;
and if it is readily admitted by the Council that the situation is one&lt;br /&gt;
within its jurisdiction, there should be good prospect of an immediate&lt;br /&gt;
cessation of hostilities, and an immediate negotiation between the two&lt;br /&gt;
parties with the assistance of a third party of their own choosing.&lt;br /&gt;
Members of the Council should not therefore have to arbitrate or to&lt;br /&gt;
pass judgment on the merits of the case.&lt;br /&gt;
Action along these lines can be taken by the Council only if the&lt;br /&gt;
Republican Government, not being a member of the United Nations,&lt;br /&gt;
undertakes to observe the obligations and duties of the United Nations&lt;br /&gt;
Charter, and in particular undertakes to observe Article 25, which&lt;br /&gt;
obliges members to carry out the decisions of the council."&lt;br /&gt;
BRITAIN.&lt;br /&gt;
PRINCESS ELIZABETI-ENGAGEMENT.&lt;br /&gt;
On 10th July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
I have to-day asked the Governor-General ( Mr. McKell) to convey&lt;br /&gt;
to His Majesty the King the following message:-&lt;br /&gt;
On behalf of the Government and people of Australia and my wife and myself&lt;br /&gt;
I send loyal and affectionate greetings to your Majesties and offer to Her Royal&lt;br /&gt;
Highness Princess Elizabeth our felicitations and best wishes on the occasion&lt;br /&gt;
of the announcement of her betrothal to Lieutenant Philip Mountbatten.&lt;br /&gt;
PRINCESS ELIZABETH-BETROTHAL.&lt;br /&gt;
On 31st July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
At a meeting of the Executive Council to-night, the Governor-&lt;br /&gt;
General ( Mr. McKell) read the following message from His Majesty&lt;br /&gt;
the King:-&lt;br /&gt;
I should be glad if you, as my personal replresentaltiv in tih CiiII vn,\ allt Ih&lt;br /&gt;
of Australia, would convey to your Executive Council that I have to-day, in&lt;br /&gt;
accordance with the provision of the Royal Marriages Act 1772, declareld in&lt;br /&gt;
Council my formal consent to the marriage of my daughter, the Princess&lt;br /&gt;
Elizabeth, to Lieutenant Philip Mountbatten.&lt;br /&gt;
5009.-2 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my motion, it was decided-' That the message of His Majesty&lt;br /&gt;
be notified in the Co. mvwonwealth of Australia Gazette for general&lt;br /&gt;
information STERLING BALANCES.&lt;br /&gt;
On 30th July, 1947, Mr. Chifley said-&lt;br /&gt;
" Discussions are still proceeding between the British Government&lt;br /&gt;
and the Commonwealth Government in an endeavour to reach some&lt;br /&gt;
arrangements on Australian sterling balances at London that will helpl&lt;br /&gt;
Britain, compatible with the protection of Australia's economic&lt;br /&gt;
interests." ( For earlier references, please see No. 126, page 31.)&lt;br /&gt;
BUDGET 1946-47.&lt;br /&gt;
SUMMARY OF YEAR'S TRANSACTIONS.&lt;br /&gt;
On 10th July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) announced&lt;br /&gt;
approximate figures of receipts and expenditure for 1946-47 as&lt;br /&gt;
follows:-SUMMARY.&lt;br /&gt;
EXPENDITURE. 1944-45.1945-46. 1946-47.&lt;br /&gt;
Approximate.&lt;br /&gt;
Part 1.-Departments and Services other&lt;br /&gt;
than Business Undertakings and&lt;br /&gt;
Territories of the Commonwealth 295,296,278 306,456,954 311,587,508&lt;br /&gt;
;'. trt 2.-Business Undertakings 30,321,644 31,294,195 35,951,734&lt;br /&gt;
P;,. rt 3.-Territories of the Commonwealth 1,371,583 1,635,664 4,517,328&lt;br /&gt;
Part 4.-Payments to or for the States 47,868,821 49,614,350 60,373,227&lt;br /&gt;
374,858,326 389,001,163 412,429,797&lt;br /&gt;
Part 5.-Primary Production-Self-balancing&lt;br /&gt;
Items 1,995,775 1,779,238 18,819,506&lt;br /&gt;
'' t; dl Expenditi're for year 376,854,101 390,780,401 431,249,303&lt;br /&gt;
RzcErprs. 1944-45. 1945-46. Ap1p9r4o6x-i4m7a. te.&lt;br /&gt;
Part 1 Departments and Services other&lt;br /&gt;
than Business Undertakings and&lt;br /&gt;
Territories of the Commonwealth 343,665,511 358,372,860 380,902,387&lt;br /&gt;
Part 2.-Business Undertakings 30,737,646 30,119,738 30,956,809&lt;br /&gt;
Part 3.-Territories of the Commonwealth 455,169 508,565 570,601&lt;br /&gt;
374,858,326 389,001,163 412,429,797&lt;br /&gt;
Part 5.-Primary Productio-Self-balancing&lt;br /&gt;
Items 1,995,775 1,779,238 18,819,506&lt;br /&gt;
Total Receipts for year 376,854,101 390,780,401 431,249,303 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CONSOLIDATED REVENUE FUND.&lt;br /&gt;
EXPEDrruRE. 119944444-54. 511.99 44554466.. Ap1p9ro46x-i4m7a. te.,&lt;br /&gt;
PART I.-DEPARTMENTS AND SERVICES.&lt;br /&gt;
Defence anzd Poat-uwar ( 1939-45) Charga,-&lt;br /&gt;
Defence and Allied Services-&lt;br /&gt;
Defence and Service Departments&lt;br /&gt;
Production Departments&lt;br /&gt;
Reciprocal Lend-Lease&lt;br /&gt;
War Gratuity&lt;br /&gt;
Post-war ( 1939-45) Charge. 4-&lt;br /&gt;
Public Debt Charges&lt;br /&gt;
United Kingdom Grant&lt;br /&gt;
Re-establishment and Repatriation&lt;br /&gt;
Lend-Lease Settlement&lt;br /&gt;
International Relief and Rehabilitation&lt;br /&gt;
Subsidies. Less Afiscellaneous Credits&lt;br /&gt;
Deduct amount chargeable to Loan Fund&lt;br /&gt;
Total Defence and Post-war ( 1939-45)&lt;br /&gt;
Charges-.&lt;br /&gt;
War and Repatriatiun ( 1914-18) Services-&lt;br /&gt;
Interest, Sinking Fund and Exchange&lt;br /&gt;
War Pensions&lt;br /&gt;
Other War Services&lt;br /&gt;
Total War and Repatriation ( 1914-18)&lt;br /&gt;
Services&lt;br /&gt;
Other Departments-&lt;br /&gt;
Special Appropriations-&lt;br /&gt;
Interest and Sinking Fund&lt;br /&gt;
Invalid and Old-age Pensions&lt;br /&gt;
Child Endowment&lt;br /&gt;
Widows' Pensions&lt;br /&gt;
National Welfare Fund( b)-&lt;br /&gt;
Other Special Appropriations&lt;br /&gt;
Administrative-Parliament Prime 11inister's Department&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Externaal Affairs&lt;br /&gt;
Department of the Treasury&lt;br /&gt;
Attorney-General's Department&lt;br /&gt;
Department of the Interior..&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Works and Housing 331,895,970 20,460,773 89,132,522 306,813,721 15,338,778 26,009,957 143,285 109,825,768 10,921,489 5,018,169 2,881,933&lt;br /&gt;
441,489,265 348,305,741 128,657,359&lt;br /&gt;
34,139,464 41,485,850 46,011,089 25,000,000&lt;br /&gt;
5,028,804 14,025,635 29,548,679 8,398,339&lt;br /&gt;
47,000 5,811,067 18,116,917&lt;br /&gt;
25,089,708 32,739,119 30,360,514&lt;br /&gt;
10,761,978 9,705,815 3,758,699&lt;br /&gt;
75,066,9154 103,767,486 161,194,237&lt;br /&gt;
516,556,219 452,073,227 289,851,596&lt;br /&gt;
56,559,819 74,146,909 57,821,718&lt;br /&gt;
459,996,400 377,926,318 232,029,878&lt;br /&gt;
268,040,485 152,947,643 37,325,256&lt;br /&gt;
193,955,915 224,978,675 194,704,622&lt;br /&gt;
9,120,975 8,958,552 9,038,512&lt;br /&gt;
9,250,175 9,120,616 9,302,484&lt;br /&gt;
917,724 812,715 920,536&lt;br /&gt;
19,288,874 18,891,883 19,261,532&lt;br /&gt;
3,203,243 3,413,763 2,781,260&lt;br /&gt;
21,701,127 ( a)&lt;br /&gt;
12,036,248 ( a)&lt;br /&gt;
2,965,446 ( a)&lt;br /&gt;
30,000,000 46,499,243 64,646,735&lt;br /&gt;
550,223 907,820 829,365&lt;br /&gt;
70,456,287 50,820,826 68,257,360&lt;br /&gt;
207,344&lt;br /&gt;
1,074,127 195,441&lt;br /&gt;
2,150,333 360,624 440,497 83,785 225,264&lt;br /&gt;
1,321,067 404,443&lt;br /&gt;
2,354,489 394,769 535,023 160,580 253,455&lt;br /&gt;
1,899,155 866,260&lt;br /&gt;
2,900,525 465,702 938,112&lt;br /&gt;
1,710,487&lt;br /&gt;
Paid from National Welfare Fund. For details see page 39.&lt;br /&gt;
5009.-3 Paid from National Welfare Fond. For details see page 39. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CONSOLIDATED REVENTUE FUND--cntinued.&lt;br /&gt;
Expenditure-continued. 1944-45. 1 1946-47.&lt;br /&gt;
1945-48. Approximate.&lt;br /&gt;
Part I.-Departments and Servicas--continued. I f&lt;br /&gt;
Other Departments-continued.&lt;br /&gt;
Administrative--continued.&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Civil Aviation&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Trade and Customs&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Health&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Commerce and Agriculture&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Social Services&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Supply and Shipping&lt;br /&gt;
Department of External Territories&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Immigration&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Labour and National&lt;br /&gt;
Service&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Transport&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Information&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Post-war Reconstruction&lt;br /&gt;
Total Administrative&lt;br /&gt;
Miscellaneous Services&lt;br /&gt;
Additions, New Works, Buildings, &amp;amp; c.&lt;br /&gt;
Total Expenditure-Part I.&lt;br /&gt;
PART II.-BusrNss.,&lt;br /&gt;
Conmonwealtl&lt;br /&gt;
Trans-Australian Railway&lt;br /&gt;
Central Australia Railway&lt;br /&gt;
North Australia Railway&lt;br /&gt;
Australian Capital Territory Railway&lt;br /&gt;
Miscellaneous Expenditure&lt;br /&gt;
Additions, New Works, Buildings, &amp;amp; c.&lt;br /&gt;
Total Expenditure Postmaster-Genera&lt;br /&gt;
Postmaster-General's Department&lt;br /&gt;
Additions, New Works, Buildings, &amp;amp; c.&lt;br /&gt;
Total Expenditure&lt;br /&gt;
Excess Receipts PART mI.-TERaBroRIEs c&lt;br /&gt;
Northern Territory&lt;br /&gt;
Australian Capital Territory&lt;br /&gt;
Papua-New Guinea&lt;br /&gt;
Norfolk Island&lt;br /&gt;
Additions, New Works, Buildings, &amp;amp; c.&lt;br /&gt;
Total Expenditure 428,350 747,950 162,583&lt;br /&gt;
377,234 400,901 268,129 35,374 32,420&lt;br /&gt;
( c)&lt;br /&gt;
( c)&lt;br /&gt;
( c)&lt;br /&gt;
( c) 728,105 837,936 173,979&lt;br /&gt;
406,232 600,023 272,876 44,119 72,551&lt;br /&gt;
( C)&lt;br /&gt;
( c)&lt;br /&gt;
( c) 1,269,956&lt;br /&gt;
1,183,070 206,986 569,023 698,856 326,319 54,704&lt;br /&gt;
176,624&lt;br /&gt;
1,031,658 54,618&lt;br /&gt;
330,458 526,329&lt;br /&gt;
6,965,092 8,531,456 15,462,297&lt;br /&gt;
2,787,207 1,331,754 5,225,797&lt;br /&gt;
1,842,903 1,902,360 8,675,900&lt;br /&gt;
295,296,278 306,456,954 311,587,508&lt;br /&gt;
I UNDERTAKINGS.&lt;br /&gt;
h Railways. 1,027,406 919,767 885,837&lt;br /&gt;
994,579 79?, 829 690,925&lt;br /&gt;
620,705 314,745 159,996&lt;br /&gt;
14,087 13,609 14,881&lt;br /&gt;
138,019 147,312 169,536&lt;br /&gt;
137,998 94,360 137,293&lt;br /&gt;
2,932,794 2,283,622 2,058,468&lt;br /&gt;
Vs Department.&lt;br /&gt;
23,993,463 24,774,998 26,755,407&lt;br /&gt;
3,395,387 4,235,575 7,137,859&lt;br /&gt;
27,388,850 29,010,573 33,893,266&lt;br /&gt;
482,961&lt;br /&gt;
27,871,811 29,010,673 33,893,266&lt;br /&gt;
OF THE COMMONWEALTH.&lt;br /&gt;
294,800 365,990 819,614.&lt;br /&gt;
736,898 831,289 941,275&lt;br /&gt;
6,748 6,654 1,526,344&lt;br /&gt;
4,074 4,074 4,075&lt;br /&gt;
329,063 427,657 1,226,020&lt;br /&gt;
1,371,583 1 1,635,664 4,517,328&lt;br /&gt;
Included under Defence and Post-war ( 1939-45) Charges. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;37&lt;br /&gt;
CONSOLIDATED RWENUF FUND-conti ued.&lt;br /&gt;
Expenditure-continued. 1944-45. 1945-46. 1946-47.&lt;br /&gt;
Approximate.&lt;br /&gt;
PART IV.-PAYMENTS TO OR FOR THE STATES.&lt;br /&gt;
Special Grant to South Australia 1,200,000 1,400,000 2,000,000&lt;br /&gt;
Special Grant to Western Australia 904,000 950,000 1,873,000&lt;br /&gt;
Special Grant to Tasmania 742,000 646,000 875,000&lt;br /&gt;
Federal Aid Roads and Works 2,200,902 3,327,553 4,797,325&lt;br /&gt;
Interest and Sinking Fund on Loans for&lt;br /&gt;
Local Public Works-Grant towards 100,000&lt;br /&gt;
Contributions towards Sinking Fund on&lt;br /&gt;
State Debts 1,682,869 1,615,604 1,636,120&lt;br /&gt;
Contributions towards Interest on State&lt;br /&gt;
Debts 7,584,912 7,584,912 7,584,912&lt;br /&gt;
Contributions towards Interest on Loans&lt;br /&gt;
for Drought Relief 22,035 16,052 10,103&lt;br /&gt;
Grants to States-Tax Reimbursement 33,432,103 33,521,057 39,463,847&lt;br /&gt;
Special Grants-Income Tax Reimbursement 552,172 2,132,920&lt;br /&gt;
47,868,821 49,614,350 60,373,227&lt;br /&gt;
Balance of Interest on State Debts-recoverable&lt;br /&gt;
from States 24,436,259 23,693,664 23,149,160&lt;br /&gt;
72,305,080 73,308,014 83,522,387&lt;br /&gt;
PART V.-PRIMARY PRODUCTION, SELF-BALANCING ITEMS.&lt;br /&gt;
Wheat Industry-Assistance to 1,995,775 1,779,238 1,747,383&lt;br /&gt;
Wool Use Promotion and Disposals Plan .4,497,123&lt;br /&gt;
Wool Industry Assistance 7,075,000&lt;br /&gt;
Wheat Industry Stabilization 5,500,000&lt;br /&gt;
1,995,775 1,779,228 18,819,506&lt;br /&gt;
RECEIPTS. 1944-45. 1945-46. Ap1p9r4o6x-i4m7. ate.&lt;br /&gt;
PART I.-DEPARTMENTS AND SEVICES.&lt;br /&gt;
Taxation-Customs Excise Sales Tax&lt;br /&gt;
Income Tax( a)&lt;br /&gt;
Social Services Contribution&lt;br /&gt;
Pay-roll Tax&lt;br /&gt;
Land Tax&lt;br /&gt;
Estate Duty&lt;br /&gt;
Entertainments Tax&lt;br /&gt;
Gift Duty&lt;br /&gt;
Gold Tax 21,487,538&lt;br /&gt;
45,689,133 29,671,802&lt;br /&gt;
215,534,037 11,0" 8" 8,088&lt;br /&gt;
3,64,420 3,090,200 5,026,821 329,296 342,457 I&lt;br /&gt;
28,893,682 49,066,962 33,600,175&lt;br /&gt;
194,593,578 20,000,000 11,499,243 3,782,359 3,880,041 5,069,672 392,949 383,552&lt;br /&gt;
335,923,792 351,162,213&lt;br /&gt;
Includes War-time ( Company) Tax. 45,889,732 56,356,602 36,264,642&lt;br /&gt;
156,764,940 51,000,000 13,646,735 3,679,482&lt;br /&gt;
4,018,620 5,137,805 544,672 556,434&lt;br /&gt;
373,859,664 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CONSOLID. TED REVENUE FUNn---continued.&lt;br /&gt;
Receipts--continued. 1944-45. 1945-46. Ap19-te.&lt;br /&gt;
Approximate.&lt;br /&gt;
Part 1.-Depart m ents and Serrices-continued.&lt;br /&gt;
Other Revenue-&lt;br /&gt;
Coinage Defence Civil Aviation&lt;br /&gt;
Attorney-General&lt;br /&gt;
Health Commerce and Agriculture&lt;br /&gt;
Marine Net Profit-Australian Note Issue&lt;br /&gt;
Miscellaneous Total Receipts-Part 1,307,037 126,318&lt;br /&gt;
1,172,958 140,198 11,889 87,961&lt;br /&gt;
261,068&lt;br /&gt;
2,948,472 1,685,818&lt;br /&gt;
7,741,719 604,599 250,184&lt;br /&gt;
1,166,551 135,239 13,696&lt;br /&gt;
280,933 250,991&lt;br /&gt;
2,939,405 1,569,049 7,210,647 238,677 961,294 155,418 15,747 35,156&lt;br /&gt;
147,615&lt;br /&gt;
3,792,383 1,696,433 7,042,723&lt;br /&gt;
.343,665,511 358,372,860 380,902,387&lt;br /&gt;
PART II.-BUSINESS UNDERTAKINGS.&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth Railways.&lt;br /&gt;
Trans-Australian Railway&lt;br /&gt;
Central Australia Railway&lt;br /&gt;
North Australia Railway&lt;br /&gt;
Australian Capital Territory&lt;br /&gt;
Total Revenue&lt;br /&gt;
Excess Expenditure&lt;br /&gt;
Post Office Excess Expenditure Railway 989,194&lt;br /&gt;
1,045,423 819,884 11,334&lt;br /&gt;
2,865,835 66,959 768,885 710,648 174,371 10,496&lt;br /&gt;
1,664,400 619,222 691,740 395,377 58,141 9,260&lt;br /&gt;
1,154,518 903,950&lt;br /&gt;
2,932,794 2,283,622 2,058,468&lt;br /&gt;
Postmaster-General's Department.&lt;br /&gt;
27,871,811 28,455,338 29,802,291&lt;br /&gt;
555,235 4,090,975&lt;br /&gt;
27,871,811 29,010,573 33,893,266&lt;br /&gt;
I"&lt;br /&gt;
PaRT III.--ERRITORIES OF THE COMMONWEALTH.&lt;br /&gt;
Northern Territory 84,965 116,601&lt;br /&gt;
Australian Capital Territory 370,204 391,964&lt;br /&gt;
Total Revenue&lt;br /&gt;
Excess Expenditure 148,649&lt;br /&gt;
421,952&lt;br /&gt;
455,169 508,565 570,601&lt;br /&gt;
916,414 1,127,099 3,946,727&lt;br /&gt;
1,371,583 1,635,664 4,517,328&lt;br /&gt;
PART IV.-PAYMENTS TO OR FOR THE STATES.&lt;br /&gt;
Contribuions from General Revenue 47,868,321 49,614,350 60,373,227&lt;br /&gt;
47,868,821 49,614,350 60,373,227&lt;br /&gt;
Interest on State Debts-payable by States 24,436,259 2?, 693,664 23,149,160&lt;br /&gt;
72,305,080 73,308,014 83,522,387&lt;br /&gt;
I I &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CONSOLIDATED RgFNUE FuND-contived.&lt;br /&gt;
Receipts-continued. 1944-45. 1945-46. Approximate.&lt;br /&gt;
PART V.-PRIMARY PRODUCTTON, SELF-BALANCr0 ITEMS.&lt;br /&gt;
Flour Tax 1,995,775 1,779,23S 1,747,383&lt;br /&gt;
Wool Contributory Charge 4,497,123&lt;br /&gt;
Wool Committee Operations Surplus 7,075,000&lt;br /&gt;
Wheat Export Charge 5,500,000&lt;br /&gt;
1,995,775 1,779,238 18,819,506&lt;br /&gt;
SOCIAL SECURITY.&lt;br /&gt;
EXPENDITURE-1946-47.&lt;br /&gt;
On 10th July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) announced&lt;br /&gt;
details of expenditure on social services in 1946-47 as follows'-&lt;br /&gt;
1944-45. 1945-46. Approximate.&lt;br /&gt;
National Welfare Fund-&lt;br /&gt;
Invalid and Old-age Pensions 26,962,420 29,416,673&lt;br /&gt;
Funeral Benefits 163,992 184,478 209,349&lt;br /&gt;
Widows Pensions 3,247,334 2,366,288&lt;br /&gt;
Maternity Allowance 2,542,801 2,492,495 3,026,460&lt;br /&gt;
Child Endowment 18,019,178 19,862,933&lt;br /&gt;
Unemployment and Sickness Benefits 1,144,412 1,650,125&lt;br /&gt;
Hospital Benefits 1,111,292 4,380,296&lt;br /&gt;
Tuberculosis Benefits 109,603&lt;br /&gt;
Balance for year remaining in National&lt;br /&gt;
Welfare Fund 27,293,207 2,625,008&lt;br /&gt;
Deduct amount paid from balance in 30,000,000 53,161,609 64,646,735&lt;br /&gt;
National Welfare Fund 6,662,366&lt;br /&gt;
30,000,000 46,499,243 64,646,735&lt;br /&gt;
Other Special Appropriations-&lt;br /&gt;
Invalid and Old-age Pensions 21,701.127 ( b)&lt;br /&gt;
Child Endowment 12,036,248 ( b)&lt;br /&gt;
Widows Pensions 2,965,446 ( b)&lt;br /&gt;
Total Social Services paid from Revenue 66,702,821 46,499,243 64,646,735&lt;br /&gt;
Paid from Other Special Appropriations. Paid from National Welfare Fund. Balance&lt;br /&gt;
of National Welfare Fund at 30th June, 1947, was &#339; 49,994,273.&lt;br /&gt;
COMMONWEALTH OFFICERS.&lt;br /&gt;
STRENGTH, MARCH, 1947.&lt;br /&gt;
On 14th July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
" Incorrect statements have been published that Commonwealth&lt;br /&gt;
employees numbered 556,700 in March, 1947. The fact is that in March, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Co mmon wealth Departments and statutory authorities employed only&lt;br /&gt;
156,500, the balance of 400,000 being employed by State and local&lt;br /&gt;
g~ overnment authorities.&lt;br /&gt;
" The latest bulletin issued by the Commonwealth -Statistician shows&lt;br /&gt;
that, of the total number of ' government employees, 28 per cent, were&lt;br /&gt;
employed by Commonwealth authorities, 62 per cent, by State Governments&lt;br /&gt;
and 10 per cent. -by local authorities. Nearly one-third of all&lt;br /&gt;
Commonwealth employees are employed in the Postmaster-General's&lt;br /&gt;
Department, and nearly another third in the Services departments and&lt;br /&gt;
in post-war services, including the Repatriation Department."&lt;br /&gt;
ANTARCTI CA.&lt;br /&gt;
EXPEDITION-ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE.&lt;br /&gt;
On 21st July, 1947, the Minister for Air ( Mr. Drakeford) announced&lt;br /&gt;
that a Walrus and a Kingfisher aircraft would accompany the forthcoming&lt;br /&gt;
Australian -antarctic expedition. The Walrus, equipped for&lt;br /&gt;
vertical and oblique photography, would be carried aboard an L. S. T.&lt;br /&gt;
The Kingfisher, equipped for oblique photography, would operate from&lt;br /&gt;
the Wyatt Earp. CAPITAL ISSUES.&lt;br /&gt;
COMPANIES-ISSUE OF SHARES AT A PREMIUM.&lt;br /&gt;
On 21st July, 1947, the Prime Minist&amp;amp; r ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
A statement I made in October, 1946, set out that premiums on new&lt;br /&gt;
share issues would not necessarily -be insisted upon. In that statement&lt;br /&gt;
I requested that, where an issue at par was proposed by a company&lt;br /&gt;
whose shares were appreciably above par, the application should include&lt;br /&gt;
a statement of the reasons for not requiring a premium. Since then&lt;br /&gt;
some companies -had required premiums-others had not.&lt;br /&gt;
i" I have reviewed the position and have decided that it is desirable&lt;br /&gt;
ithe interests of the Australian economy that a premium should be&lt;br /&gt;
required in all cases where there is an -appreciable margin between par&lt;br /&gt;
value and market price. I have accordingly requested the Capital&lt;br /&gt;
Issues Advisory Committee to give this aspect consideration in future.&lt;br /&gt;
The committee will not insist on prohibitive premiums but will allow&lt;br /&gt;
reasonable margins."&lt;br /&gt;
( For earlier references, please see No. 120, page 12.)&lt;br /&gt;
CENSUS.&lt;br /&gt;
ROUSING INFORMATION.&lt;br /&gt;
On 28th July, 1947, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-&lt;br /&gt;
" Census returns are -absolutely confidential. This is guaranteed by&lt;br /&gt;
Act of Parliament. They cannot, therefore, he used for any purpose as&lt;br /&gt;
has been suggested."&lt;br /&gt;
( It had been stated that the information given in regard to dwellings might&lt;br /&gt;
be used to compel small families with large houses to provide space for others.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;41&lt;br /&gt;
MINING.&lt;br /&gt;
STRATEGIC MINERALS-CONTROL.&lt;br /&gt;
On 31st July, 1947, the Acting Minister for Post-war Reconstruction&lt;br /&gt;
( Mr. Pollard) announced National Security ( Minerals) Regulations&lt;br /&gt;
giving power to acquire minerals compulsorily and to apply compensation.&lt;br /&gt;
provisions to any acquisition. The power ' would be used only in&lt;br /&gt;
connexion with strategic minerals and metals.&lt;br /&gt;
By Authority: L. F. JTOHNSTON, Commonwealth Government Printer, Canberra. &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>